<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">Coriolanus</title><title type="sub"> A tragedy. As it is acted at the Theatre-Royal in Covent-Garden. By the late James Thomson.</title><author><persName><surname>Thomson</surname><forename>James</forename><idno type="VIAF">14778969</idno></persName></author><respStmt><resp>Transformation into valid TEI P5, improving markup, filling <gi>gap</gi>s, proofreading, and expanding header.</resp><persName xml:id="JJ"><surname>Jokisch</surname><forename>Jan</forename><idno type="ORCID">0009-0003-1026-2995</idno></persName></respStmt></titleStmt>
<extent><measure quantity="110" unit="KB">About 110 kilobytes.</measure></extent><publicationStmt><authority ref="#JJ">Jan Jokisch</authority><date>2024 December</date><idno type="ECCO_Drama">K080528.000</idno><idno type="DLPS">004864247</idno><idno type="ESTC">T100060</idno><idno type="DocNo">CW114143458</idno><idno type="TCP">K080528.000</idno>
<idno type="GaleDocNo">CW3314143458</idno><idno type="ContentSet">ECLL</idno><idno type="ImageSetID">0744600800</idno><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull><titleStmt><title type="245">Coriolanus: A tragedy. As it is acted at the Theatre-Royal in Covent-Garden. By the late James Thomson.</title><author>Thomson, James, 1700-1748.</author></titleStmt>
<extent>[8],62,[2]p. ; 8⁰.</extent><publicationStmt><publisher>printed for A. Millar,</publisher><date>1749.</date><pubPlace>London :</pubPlace></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note>With a half-title and a final epilogue leaf.</note><note>Catchword on p.58: of.</note><note>The ornaments are those used by William Bowyer.</note><note>Reproduction of original from the British Library.</note><note>English Short Title Catalog, ESTCT100060.</note><note>Electronic data. Farmington Hills, Mich. : Thomson Gale, 2003. Page image (PNG). Digitized image of the microfilm version produced in Woodbridge, CT by Research Publications, 1982-2002 (later known as Primary Source Microfilm, an imprint of the Gale Group).</note></notesStmt>
</biblFull></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Subset of the ECCO project. Included were all dramatic texts excluding operas, primarily musical forms, ballets, pantomimes, entertainments, etc. All files have been proofread systematically to produce highly improved though not yet critical versions of the plays.</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>This electronic text is based on the ECCO Text Creation Partnership, which originally keyed the file from page images and partially proofread for accuracy. To improve upon the raw ECCO TCP file, the file was transformed into valid TEI P5, <gi>gap</gi>s were filled following the original edition, and the text systematically proofread for frequent OCR mistakes. Furthermore, the attribution of dialog to speakers, the distinction between stage directions and dialog, stage directions and speech prefixes, stage directions and headings as well as the segmentation of the play into acts and scenes was checked systematically and corrected whenever deemed necessary.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><langUsage><language ident="en">eng</language></langUsage></profileDesc></teiHeader><text xml:lang="en">
<front>
<div1 type="frontispiece">
<pb facs="1" ana="y"/>
<p>CORIOLANUS.
A
TRAGEDY.</p>
<p>[Price One Shilling and Six Pence.]</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="publisher'sadvertisement">
<pb facs="2"/>
<head>BOOKS printed for A. MILLAR.</head>
<p>THE Complete Works of <hi>James Thomson,</hi> in 3 vol.
Octavo, Price bound 15s. containing,</p>
<list>
<item>Vol. I. The Seasons: A Hymn; a Poem to the Memory
of Sir <hi>Isaac Newton; Britannia,</hi> a Poem; and <hi>Sophonisba,</hi> a Tragedy.</item>
<item>Vol. II. Antient and Modern <hi>Italy</hi> compar'd; <hi>Greece,
Rome, Britain,</hi> and the Prospect, being the Five Parts
of <hi>Liberty,</hi> a Poem; <hi>Agamemnon,</hi> a Tragedy; <hi>Edward</hi>
and <hi>Eleonora,</hi> a Tragedy; and a Poem to the Memory
of the late Lord Chancellor <hi>Talbot.</hi></item>
<item>Vol. III. <hi>Tancred</hi> and <hi>Sigismunda,</hi> a Tragedy; the Castle
of Indolence, and allegorical Poem, written in Imitation
of <hi>Spenser; Coriolanus,</hi> a Tragedy; and <hi>Alfred,</hi> a Mask:
This last written by Mr. <hi>Thomson</hi> and Mr. <hi>Mallet.</hi></item>
</list>
<p>The Second or Third Volume to be had separate; as
are most of the Pieces.</p>
<p>⁂ The SEASONS are to be had alone, in a neat Pocket
Edition, Price bound 3s.</p>
<list>
<head>Next Month will be Publish'd,</head>
<item>In Six Volumes 12mo, Price bound 18s.
1. The History of TOM JONES, a Foundling, by <hi>Henry
Fielding</hi> Esq.
—Mores hominum multorum.</item>
<item>2. <hi>Ophiomaches,</hi> or Deism Revealed. In Eight Dialogues.
In Two Volumes.</item>
</list>
</div1>
<div1 type="titlepage">
<pb facs="4"/>
<p>CORIOLANUS.
A
TRAGEDY.
As it is Acted at the
THEATRE-ROYAL
IN
<hi>COVENT-GARDEN.</hi></p>
<p>By the late <hi>JAMES THOMSON.</hi></p>
<p><hi>LONDON,</hi>
Printed for A. MILLAR at <hi>Buchanan's</hi> Head in
the <hi>Strand.</hi> MDCCXLIX.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="dramatispersonae">
<pb facs="3"/>
<head>The Persons Represented.</head>
<list>
<label>CAIUS MARCIUS CORIOLANUS.</label>
<item>Mr. <hi>Quin.</hi></item>
<label>ATTIUS TULLUS, General of the <hi>Volscian</hi> Army.</label>
<item>Mr. <hi>Ryan.</hi></item>
<label>GALESUS, one of the Deputies of the <hi>Volscian</hi> States attending the Camp.</label>
<item>Mr. <hi>Delane.</hi></item>
<label>The other Deputies of the <hi>Volscian</hi> States.</label>
<item> </item>
<label>VOLUSIUS, one of the Principal <hi>Volscian</hi> Officers.</label>
<item>Mr. <hi>Sparks.</hi></item>
<label>TITUS, Freed-man of GALESUS.</label>
<item>Mr. <hi>Ridout.</hi></item>
<label>MARCUS MINUCIUS, Consul and Principal of the Deputation from <hi>Rome</hi> to CORIOLANUS.</label>
<item>Mr. <hi>Bridgwater.</hi></item>
<label>POSTHUMUS COMINIUS, a Consular Senator, one of the Deputation, and who had been the <hi>Roman</hi> General at the taking of <hi>Corioli.</hi></label>
<item>Mr. <hi>Anderson.</hi></item>
<label>VETURIA, Mother of CORIOLANUS.</label>
<item>Mrs. <hi>Woffington.</hi></item>
<label>VOLUMNIA, Wife of CORIOLANUS.</label>
<item>Miss <hi>Bellamy.</hi></item>
<label><hi>Roman</hi> Senators, Priests, Augurs, &amp;c. of the first
Deputation. <hi>Roman</hi> Ladies, in the Train of
VETURIA and VOLUMNIA, of the second Deputation.</label>
<item> </item>
<label>Volscian OFFICERS, LICTORS, SOLDIERS, &amp;c.</label>
<item> </item>
</list>
</div1>
<set><p>SCENE, The <hi>Volscian</hi> Camp.</p></set>
<div1 type="prologue">
<pb facs="21"/>
<head>PROLOGUE</head>
<stage>Spoken by Mr. QUIN.</stage>
<l>I Come not here your Candour to implore</l>
<l>For Scenes, whose Author is, alas! no more;</l>
<l>He wants no Advocate his Cause to plead;</l>
<l>You will yourselves be Patrons of the Dead.</l>
<l>No Party his Benevolence confin'd</l>
<l>No Sect—alike it flow'd to all Mankind.</l>
<l>He lov'd his Friends (forgive this gushing Tear:</l>
<l>Alas! I feel I am no Actor here)</l>
<l>He lov'd his Friends with such a Warmth of Heart,</l>
<l>So clear of Int'rest, so devoid of Art,</l>
<l>Such generous Freedom, such unshaken Zeal,</l>
<l>No Words can speak it, but our Tears may tell.—</l>
<l>O candid Truth, O Faith without a Stain,</l>
<l>O Manners gently firm, and nobly plain,</l>
<l>O sympathizing Love of others Bliss,</l>
<l>Where will you find another Breast like His?—</l>
<l>Such was the Man—the Poet well you know:</l>
<l>Oft has he touch'd your Hearts with tender Woe:</l>
<l>Oft in this crouded House with just Applause</l>
<l>You heard him teach fair Virtue's purest Laws;</l>
<l>For his chaste Muse employ'd her Heav'n-taught Lyre</l>
<l>None but the noblest Passions to inspire,</l>
<l>Not one immoral, one corrupted Thought,</l>
<l>One Line, which dying he could wish to blot.</l>
<l>Oh may To-night your favourable Doom</l>
<l>Another Laurel add to grace his Tomb:</l>
<l>Whilst he, superior now to Praise or Blame,</l>
<l>Hears net the feeble Voice of Human Fame.</l>
<l><pb facs="22"/>
Yet if to those whom most on Earth he lov'd,</l>
<l>From whom his pious Care is now remov'd,</l>
<l>With whom his liberal Hand, and bounteous Heart</l>
<l>Shar'd all his little Fortune could impart,</l>
<l>If to those Friends your kind Regard shall give</l>
<l>What they no longer can from His receive,</l>
<l>That, that, even now, above yon starry Pole,</l>
<l>May touch with Pleasure his immortal Soul.</l>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 n="1" type="act">
<pb facs="5"/>
<head>CORIOLANUS.
A
TRAGEDY.</head>
<div2 n="1" type="scene">
<head>ACT I. SCENE I.</head>
<stage>The Volscian Camp.</stage>
<stage>ATTIUS TULLUS, VOLUSIUS.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>VOLUSIUS.</speaker>
<l>WHENCE is it, TULLUS, that our Arms are stopt</l>
<l>Here on the Borders of the <hi>Roman</hi> State?</l>
<l>Why sleeps that Spirit, whose Heroic Ardour</l>
<l>Urg'dy ou to break the Truce, and pour'd our Host,</l>
<l>From all th'united Cantons of the <hi>Volsci,</hi></l>
<l>On their unguarded Frontier? Such Designs</l>
<l>Brook rot an Hour's Delay; their whole Success</l>
<l>Depends on instant vigorous Execution.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>VOLUSIUS, I approve thy brave Impatience;</l>
<l>And will to thee, in Confidence of Friendship,</l>
<l>Disclose my secret Soul. Thou know'st GALESUS,</l>
<l><pb n="2" facs="6"/>
Whose Freedom <hi>CAIUS MARCIUS,</hi> once his Guest,</l>
<l>Of all the Spoil of sack'd <hi>Corioli,</hi></l>
<l>Alone demanded; and who thence to <hi>Rome,</hi></l>
<l>From Gratitude and Friendship, follow'd MARCIUS;</l>
<l>Whence lately to our <hi>Antium</hi> he return'd,</l>
<l>With Overtures of Peace propos'd by <hi>Rome.</hi></l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>VOLUSIUS.</speaker>
<l>I know him well; an antiquated Sage</l>
<l>Of that romantic School, <hi>Pythagoras</hi></l>
<l>Establish'd here on our <hi>Hesperian</hi> Shore;</l>
<l>Whose gentle Dictates only serve to tame</l>
<l>Enfeebled Mortals into Slaves.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>GALESUS,</l>
<l>Doubtless, possesses many civil Virtues;</l>
<l>Is gentle, good; for Rectitude of Heart</l>
<l>And Innocence of Life by all rever'd.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>VOLUSIUS.</speaker>
<l>Pardon me, TULLUS, if my faithful Bluntness</l>
<l>Deems you too lib'ral in his Praise. In Peace,</l>
<l>Such may perhaps do well, when Prating rules</l>
<l>An idle World; but in tempestuous Times</l>
<l>They are stark naught, these visionary Statesmen,</l>
<l>Fit Rulers only for their golden Age.</l>
<l>The rugged Genius of rapacious <hi>Rome</hi></l>
<l>For other Men, and other Counsels, calls.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>Your Thoughts are mine—I only meant to tell thee</l>
<l>The Part he bears in this ill-tim'd Delay.</l>
<l>Soon as our gather'd Army march'd from <hi>Antium,</hi></l>
<l>The <hi>Roman</hi> Senate, whose attentive Caution</l>
<l>Watch'd all our Motions, took at once th' Alarm</l>
<l>And sent a Herald, ere we past their Borders,</l>
<l>With formal Ceremony, to demand</l>
<l>The Cause of our Approach.—Had I been Master,</l>
<l>I would have answer'd at the Gates of <hi>Rome.</hi></l>
<l>But this GALESUS, who attends our Camp</l>
<l>Among the <hi>Volscian</hi> Deputies, so pleaded</l>
<l><pb n="3" facs="7"/>
The Laws of Nations, made such loud Complaints</l>
<l>Against th' Infraction of the Publick Faith,</l>
<l>So teaz'd us with the Pedantry of States,</l>
<l>That I was forc'd, unwilling, to permit</l>
<l>His Freedman, TITUS, to be sent to <hi>Rome</hi></l>
<l>With our Demands. If these the Senate grants,</l>
<l>We then are in the Toils of Peace entangled,</l>
<l>In spite of all my Efforts to avoid them.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>VOLUSIUS.</speaker>
<l>O 'tis a wild Chimera! Peace with <hi>Rome!</hi></l>
<l>Dream not of that, unless die <hi>Volscian</hi> Courage</l>
<l>Be quite subdu'd, and only seeks to gild</l>
<l>A vile Submission with that specious Name.</l>
<l>Learn Wisdom from your Neighbours. Peace with
<hi>Rome</hi></l>
<l>Has quell'd the <hi>Latines,</hi> tam'd their free-born Spirit,</l>
<l>And by her Friendship honour'd them with Chains.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>She ne'er will grant it on the just Conditions</l>
<l>I now have brought the <hi>Volsci</hi> to demand:</l>
<l>The Restitution of our conquer'd Cities,</l>
<l>And fair Alliance upon equal Terms.</l>
<l>I know the <hi>Roman</hi> Insolence will scorn</l>
<l>To yield to this: and TITUS must return</l>
<l>Within three Days, the longest Term allow'd him;</l>
<l>Of which the Third is near elaps'd already.</l>
<l>Then even GALESUS will not dare to stop us,</l>
<l>With superstitious Forms, and solemn Trisles,</l>
<l>From letting loose th'unbridled Rage of War</l>
<l>Against those hated Tyrants of <hi>Hesperia.</hi></l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>VOLUSIUS.</speaker>
<l>Thanks to the Gods! my Sword will then be free.</l>
<l>Then, poor <hi>Corioli!</hi> thy bleeding Wounds,</l>
<l>Thy Treasures sack'd, thy captivated Matrons,</l>
<l>Shall amply be reveng'd by thy VOLUSIUS:</l>
<l>Then, TULLUS, from the losty Brows of MARCIUS</l>
<l>Thou may'st regain the wreaths his conquering hand,</l>
<l><pb n="4" facs="8"/>
By partial Fortune aided, tore from thine.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>O my VOLUSIUS! thou, who art a Soldier,</l>
<l>A try'd and brave one too, say, in thy Heart</l>
<l>Dost thou not scorn me? thou, who saw'st me bend</l>
<l>Beneath the half-spent Thunder of a Foe,</l>
<l>Warm from the Conquest of <hi>Corioli,</hi></l>
<l>Which, rushing furious in with those, whose Sally</l>
<l>He had repell'd, he feiz'd almost alone;</l>
<l>And gave to Fire and Sword. Yet thence he flew,</l>
<l>Scorning the Plunder of our richest City,</l>
<l>His Wounds undrest, without a Moment's Respite,</l>
<l>To where our Armies on the fearful Edge</l>
<l>Of Battle stflood; and, asking of the Consul</l>
<l>To be oppos'd to me, with mighty Rage,</l>
<l>Resistless, bore us down.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>VOLUSIUS.</speaker>
<l>True Valour, TULLUS,</l>
<l>Lies in the Mind, the never-yielding Purpose,</l>
<l>Nor owns the blind Award of giddy Fortune.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>My Soul, my Friend, my Soul is all on Fire!</l>
<l>Thirst of Revenge consumes me! the Revenge</l>
<l>Of generous Emulation, not of Hatred.</l>
<l>This happy <hi>Roman,</hi> this proud MARCIUS haunts me.</l>
<l>Each troubled Night when Slaves and Captives sleep,</l>
<l>Forgetful of their Chains, I, in my Dreams,</l>
<l>Anew am vanquish'd; and, beneath his Sword</l>
<l>With Horror sinking, feel a tenfold Death,</l>
<l>The Death of Honour. But I will redeem—</l>
<l>Yes, MARCIUS, I will yet redeem my Fame.</l>
<l>To face thee once again is the great Purpose</l>
<l>For which alone I live.—Till then how slow,</l>
<l>How tedious lags the Time! while Shame corrodes
me,</l>
<l>With many a bitter Thought; and injur'd Honour</l>
<l>Sick, and desponding, preys upon itself.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="5" facs="9"/>
<speaker>VOLUSIUS.</speaker>
<l>It fast approaches now, the Hour of Vengeance,</l>
<l>To this fam'd Land, to ancient <hi>Latium</hi> due.</l>
<l>Unballanc'd <hi>Rome,</hi> at Variance with herself,</l>
<l>To Order lost, in deep and hot Commotion,</l>
<l>Stands on the dangerous Point of civil War;</l>
<l>Her haughty Nobles and seditious Commons</l>
<l>Reviling, fearing, hating one another:</l>
<l>While, on our part, all wears a prosperous Face:</l>
<l>Our Troops united, numerous, high in Spirit,</l>
<l>As if their Gen'ral's Soul inform'd them all.</l>
<l>O long-expected Day!</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>Go, brave VOLUSIUS,</l>
<l>Go breathe thy Ardour into every Breast,</l>
<l>That when the <hi>Volscian</hi> Envoy shall return,</l>
<l>Whom ere the Close of Evening I expect,</l>
<l>One Spirit may unite us in the Cause</l>
<l>Of generous Freedom, and our native Rights,</l>
<l>So long opprest by <hi>Rome's</hi> encroaching Power,</l>
</sp>
</div2>
<div2 n="2" type="scene">
<head>SCENE II.</head>
<stage>TULLUS alone.</stage>
<sp>
<l>GALESUS said that MARCIUS stands for Consul.</l>
<l>O favour thou his suit, propitious <hi>Jove!</hi></l>
<l>That I may brave him at his Army's Head,</l>
<l>In all the Majesty of sovereign Pow'r!</l>
<l>That the whole Conduct of the War may rest</l>
<l>Oh us alone, and prove by its Decision,</l>
<l>Which of the two is worthiest to command—</l>
</sp>
</div2>
<div2 n="3" type="scene">
<pb n="6" facs="10"/>
<head>SCENE III.</head>
<stage>TULLUS, OFFICER.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>Ha! why this Haste? you look alarm'd.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>OFFICER.</speaker>
<l>My Lord,</l>
<l>One of exalted Port, his Visage hid,</l>
<l>Has plac'd himself upon your sacred Hearth,</l>
<l>Beneath the dread Protection of your <hi>Lares;</hi></l>
<l>And sits majestic there in solemn Silence.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>Did you not ask him who, and what he was?</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>OFFICER.</speaker>
<l>My Lord, I could not speak; I felt appall'd,</l>
<l>As if the Presence of some God had struck me.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>Come, Dastard! let me find this Man of Terrors.</l>
</sp>
</div2>
<div2 n="4" type="scene">
<head>SCENE IV.</head>
<stage>The back Scene opens, and discovers CORIOLANUS
as described above.</stage>
<stage>CORIOLANUS, TULLUS.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS,</speaker>
<stage>after some Silence.</stage>
<l>Illustrious Stranger—for thy high Demeanour</l>
<l>Bespeaks thee such—who art thou?</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="7" facs="11"/>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<stage>[Rising and unmuffling his Face.</stage>
<l>View me, TULLUS—</l>
<stage>[After some pause.</stage>
<l>Dost thou not know me?</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>No. That noble Front</l>
<l>I never saw before. What is thy Name?</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>Does not the secret Voice of hostile Instinct,</l>
<l>Does not thy swelling Heart declare me to thee?</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>Gods! can it be?—</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
<l>Yes. I am CAIUS MARCIUS;</l>
<l>Known to thy smarting Country by the Name</l>
<l>Of CORIOLANUS. That alone is left me,</l>
<l>That empty Name, for all my Toils, my Service,</l>
<l>The Blood which I have shed for thankless <hi>Rome.</hi></l>
<l>Behold me banish'd thence, a Victim yielded</l>
<l>By her weak Nobles to the maddening Rabble.</l>
<l>I seek Revenge. Thou may'st employ my Sword,</l>
<l>With keener Edge, with heavier Force against her,</l>
<l>Than e'er it fell upon the <hi>Volscian</hi> Nation.</l>
<l>But if thou, TULLUS, dost refuse me this,</l>
<l>The only Wish of my collected Heart,</l>
<l>Where every Passion in one burning Point</l>
<l>Concenters, give me Death: Death from thy Hand</l>
<l>I sure have well deserv'd—Nor shall I blush</l>
<l>To take or Life or Death from ATTIUS TULLUS.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>O CAIUS MARCIUS ! in this one short Moment,</l>
<l>That we have friendly talk'd, my ravish'd Heart</l>
<l>Has undergone a great, a wonderous Change.</l>
<l>I ever held thee in my best Esteem;</l>
<l>But this Heroic Confidence has won me,</l>
<l>Stampt me at once thy Friend. I were indeed</l>
<l><pb n="8" facs="12"/>
A Wretch as mean as this thy Trust is noble,</l>
<l>Could I refuse thee thy Demand—Yes, MARCIUS!</l>
<l>Thou hast thy Wish! take half of my Command:</l>
<l>If that be not enough, then take the whole.</l>
<l>We have, my Friend, a gallant Force on Foot,</l>
<l>An Army, MARCIUS, fit to follow thee.</l>
<l>Go, lead them on, and take thy full Revenge.</l>
<l>All should unite to punish the Ungrateful.</l>
<l>Ingratitude is Treason to Mankind.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS,</speaker>
<stage>embracing him.</stage>
<l>Thus, generous TULLUS, take a Soldier's Thanks,</l>
<l>Who is not practis'd in the Gloss of Words—</l>
<l>Thou Friend indeed! Friend to my Cause, my Quarrel!</l>
<l>Friend to the darling Passion of my Soul!</l>
<l>All else I set at nought!—Immortal Gods!</l>
<l>I am new-made, and wonder at myself!</l>
<l>A little while ago, and I was nothing;</l>
<l>A powerless Reptile, crawling on the Earth,</l>
<l>Curs'd with a Soul that restless wish'd to wield</l>
<l>The Bolts of <hi>Jove!</hi> I dwelt in <hi>Erebus,</hi></l>
<l>I wander'd through the hopeless Glooms of Hell,</l>
<l>Stung with Revenge, tormented by the Furies!</l>
<l>Now, TULLUS, like a God, you draw me thence,</l>
<l>Throne me amidst the Skies, with Tempest charg'd,</l>
<l>And put the ready Thunder in my Hand!</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>What I have promis'd, MARCIUS, I will do.</l>
<l>Within an Hour at farthest we expect</l>
<l>The Freedman of GALESUS back from <hi>Rome,</hi></l>
<l>Who carry'd to the Senate our Demands.</l>
<l>Their Answer will, I doubt not, end the Truce,</l>
<l>And instant draw our angry Swords against them.</l>
<l>Till then retire within my inmost Tent,</l>
<l>Unknown to all but me, that when our Chiefs</l>
<l>Meet in full Council to declare for War,</l>
<l>I may produce thee to their wondering Eyes,</l>
<l><pb n="9" facs="13"/>
As if descended from avenging Heaven</l>
<l>To humble lofty <hi>Rome,</hi> and teach her Justice.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>To thy Direction, TULLUS, I resign</l>
<l>My future Life: my Fate is in thy Hands;</l>
<l>And, if I judge aright, the Fate of <hi>Rome.</hi></l>
</sp>
<trailer>The End of the First <hi>ACT.</hi></trailer>
</div2>
</div1>
<div1 n="2" type="act">
<pb n="10" facs="14"/>
<head>ACT II.</head>
<div2 n="1" type="scene">
<head>SCENE I.</head>
<stage>GALESUS, TITUS.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>GALESUS.</speaker>
<l>INDEED! my TITUS, I had Hopes that <hi>Rome,</hi></l>
<l>Vext as she is with her domestic Broils,</l>
<l>Her Frontier weak, her Armies unprepar'd,</l>
<l>Might have comply'd with our Demands, and given us</l>
<l>The same Alliance granted to the <hi>Latines.</hi></l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TITUS.</speaker>
<l>The Senate scarce would hear the Terms I offer'd;</l>
<l>But order'd me to bear this Answer back:</l>
<l>"If first the <hi>Volsci</hi> take up Arms, the <hi>Romans</hi></l>
<l>"Will be the last to lay them down."</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>GALESUS.</speaker>
<l>Alas!</l>
<l>This Answer seals the Doom of many a Wretch.</l>
<l>Unchain'd <hi>Bellona</hi> from her Temple rushes,</l>
<l>With all the Crimes and Vices in her Train.</l>
<l>Earth fades at her Approach. To rural Peace,</l>
<l>Fair Plenty, and the social Joy of Cities,</l>
<l>Soon will succeed Rage, Rapine, Devastation,</l>
<l>Each cruel Horror sanctify'd by Names.</l>
<l>O Mortals! Mortals! when will you, content</l>
<l>With Nature's Bounty, that in fuller Flow,</l>
<l>Still as your Labours open more its Sources,</l>
<l>Abundant gushes o'er the happy World;</l>
<l><pb n="11" facs="15"/>
When will you banish Violence, and Outrage,</l>
<l>To dwell with Beasts of Prey in Woods and Desarts?</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TITUS.</speaker>
<l>Never till <hi>Rome</hi> shall change her conquering Maxims.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>GALESUS.</speaker>
<l>Her haughty Spirit now will soar beyond</l>
<l>Its usual Pitch, upborne by CAIUS MARCIUS.</l>
<l>Stands he not for the Consulate?</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TITUS.</speaker>
<l>He did.</l>
<l>But is no more a Citizen of <hi>Rome.</hi></l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>GALESUS.</speaker>
<l>What mean'st thou, TITUS?</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TITUS.</speaker>
<l>MARCIUS is from <hi>Rome</hi></l>
<l>Banish'd for ever.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>GALESUS.</speaker>
<l>O immortal Powers!</l>
<l>On what Pretence could they to Exile doom</l>
<l>Their wisest Captain, and their bravest Soldier?</l>
<l>Nor less renown'd for Piety, for Justice,</l>
<l>An uncorrupted Heart, and purest Manners.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TITUS.</speaker>
<l>The Charge against him was entirely groundless,</l>
<l>What not his Enemies themselves believ'd,</l>
<l>Affecting of tyrannic Power in <hi>Rome.</hi></l>
<l>His real Crime was only some hot Words,</l>
<l>Struck from his fiery Temper, in the Senate,</l>
<l>Against those factious Ministers of Discord,</l>
<l>The Tribunes of the People. They to Rage,</l>
<l>And frantic Fury, rous'd the mad Plebeians;</l>
<l>By whom supported in their bold Attempt,</l>
<l>They durst presume to summon to the Bar</l>
<l>Of an enrag'd and partial Populace,</l>
<l>The most illustrious Senator of <hi>Rome.</hi></l>
<l>To this the Nobles yielded—and, with his,</l>
<l>Gave up their own and Childrens Rights for ever.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="12" facs="16"/>
<speaker>GALESUS.</speaker>
<l>O shameful Weakness in a <hi>Roman</hi> Senate,</l>
<l>So much renown'd for Firmness! Yet, my TITUS,</l>
<l>Spite of my Love to MARCIUS, I must own it,</l>
<l>The vigorous Soil whence his Heroic Virtues</l>
<l>Luxuriant rise, if not with careful Hand</l>
<l>Severely weeded, teems with Imperfections.</l>
<l>His lofty Spirit brooks no Opposition.</l>
<l>His Rage, if once offended, knows no Bounds.</l>
<l>He deems Plebeians, with Patrician Blood</l>
<l>Compar'd, the Creatures of a lower Species,</l>
<l>Mere menial Hands by Nature meant to serve him.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TITUS.</speaker>
<l>It was this high Patrician Pride undid him.</l>
<l>The furious People triumph'd in his Ruin</l>
<l>As if they had expell'd another <hi>Tarquin:</hi></l>
<l>While, like a captive Train, the vanquish'd Nobles</l>
<l>Hung their dejected Heads in silent Shame.</l>
<l>MARCIUS alone seem'd unconcern'd; tho' deep</l>
<l>The latent Tempest boil'd within his Breast,</l>
<l>Choak'd up and smother'd with excessive Rage.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>GALESUS.</speaker>
<l>You were his Guest at <hi>Rome,</hi> and therefore, TITUS,</l>
<l>Might on this sad Occasion be permitted</l>
<l>To join your Tears with his domestic Friends.</l>
<l>Saw you that moving Scene?</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TITUS.</speaker>
<l>I did, GALESUS.</l>
<l>I follow'd MARCIUS home—His Mother, there,</l>
<l>VETURIA, the most venerable Matron</l>
<l>These Eyes have e'er beheld, and soft VOLUMNIA,</l>
<l>His lovely, virtuous Wife, amidst his Children,</l>
<l>Spread on the Ground, lay lost in dumb Despair.</l>
<l>He swelling stood a while, and could not speak,</l>
<l>Th'affronted Hero struggling with the Man;</l>
<l>Then thus at last he broke the gloomy Silence:</l>
<l>"'Tis done. The guilty Sentence is pronounc'd.</l>
<l>"Ungrateful <hi>Rome</hi> has cast me from her Bosom.</l>
<l><pb n="13" facs="17"/>
"Support this Blow with Fortitude and Courage,</l>
<l>"As it becomes two generous <hi>Roman</hi> Matrons.</l>
<l>"I recommend my Children to your Care.</l>
<l>"Farewel. I go, I quit, without Regret,</l>
<l>"A City grown an Enemy to Virtue."</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>GALESUS.</speaker>
<l>Oh godlike MARCIUS! oh unconquer'd Strength</l>
<l>And Dignity of Mind ! How much superior</l>
<l>Is such a Soul to all the Power of Fortune!</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TITUS.</speaker>
<l>This said, he sternly try'd to break away:</l>
<l>When, holding in her Hand his eldest Son,</l>
<l>VETURIA follow'd; while the poor VOLUMNIA,</l>
<l>All drown'd in Tears, and bearing in one Arm</l>
<l>Their youngest, yet an Infant, with the other</l>
<l>Hung clinging at his Knees—he, turning to them,</l>
<l>Half soften'd, half severe, breath'd from his Soul</l>
<l>These broken Accents—"Cease your vain Complaints.</l>
<l>"Mother, you have no more a Son; and thou,</l>
<l>"Thou best of Women! thou, my dear VOLUMNIA!</l>
<l>"No more a Husband"—Pierc'd with these dire
Words,</l>
<l>VOLUMNIA lifeless sunk: and off he flung,</l>
<l>With wild Precipitation.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>GALESUS.</speaker>
<l>Thy sad Tale</l>
<l>Blinds my old Eyes with Tears—But whither, tell me,</l>
<l>O whither, TITUS, bent he then his Course?</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TITUS.</speaker>
<l>Where the blind Genius of regardless Rage</l>
<l>And Desperation led. On to the Gate,</l>
<l><hi>Capena</hi> call'd, attended by the Nobles,</l>
<l>He stalk'd in sullen Majesty along;</l>
<l>Nor deign'd a Word. A godlike virtuous Anger</l>
<l>Beam'd thro' his Features, and sublim'd his Air.</l>
<l>With downcast Eyes he walk'd; or if aside</l>
<l>He chanc'd to look, each Look was great Reproach.</l>
<l><pb n="14" facs="18"/>
Thus in emphatic Silence, that made Words</l>
<l>Void and insipid all, he parted from them,</l>
<l>The Day preceding my Return from <hi>Rome;</hi></l>
<l>Nor has been heard of since, lost in th'Abyss</l>
<l>Of his own Woes.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>GALESUS.</speaker>
<l>O MARCIUS, noble MARCIUS!</l>
<l>How shall my Friendship succour thy Distress?</l>
<l>Where shall I find thee, to partake thy Sorrows,</l>
<l>And make myself Companion of thy Exile?</l>
<l>But, TITUS, we indulge Discourse too long—</l>
<l>Go, and assemble thou the <hi>Volscian</hi> Chiefs,</l>
<l>Whilst I repair to TULLUS, to inform,</l>
<l>And bring him to the Council, there to hear</l>
<l>The fatal Answer thou hast brought from <hi>Rome.</hi></l>
</sp>
</div2>
<div2 n="2" type="scene">
<head>SCENE II.</head>
<stage>Changes to TULLUS'S Tent.</stage>
<stage>CORIOLANUS, TULLUS.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>Forgive me, TULLUS, if I count the Moments</l>
<l>That stop the Purpose of thy noble Kindness,</l>
<l>And keep me here confin'd in tame Inaction.</l>
<l>Why lingers TITUS?</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>Calm thy restless Heart,</l>
<l>Brave MARCIUS; every Minute I expect him.</l>
<l>Soon from the Cloud that hides thee, shalt thou break</l>
<l>With double Brightness; soon thy firey Rage</l>
<l>Shall wither all the Strength and Pride of <hi>Rome.</hi></l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>O righteous <hi>Jove,</hi> Protector of the Injur'd!</l>
<l>If from my earliest Youth, with pious Awe,</l>
<l>I still have reverenc'd thy all-powerful Justice,</l>
<l>Still by her sacred Dictates rul'd my Actions,</l>
<l><pb n="15" facs="19"/>
O let that Justice now support my Cause,</l>
<l>And arm my strong Right-hand with all her Terrors!.</l>
<l>When that is done, be Life or Death my Lot,</l>
<l>As thy almighty Pleasure shall determine.</l>
<stage>[Enter an Officer to <hi>TULLUS.</hi></stage>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>OFFICER.</speaker>
<l>My Lord, GALESUS asks Admittance to you.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>MARCIUS, retire an Instant, till I hear</l>
<l>The Business brings him hither—Bid him enter.</l>
<stage>[Exit Officer and <hi>CORIOLANUS.</hi></stage>
<stage>Enter <hi>GALESUS.</hi></stage>
</sp>
</div2>
<div2 n="3" type="scene">
<head>SCENE III.</head>
<stage>TULLUS, GALESUS.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>GALESUS.</speaker>
<l>TULLUS, the <hi>Roman</hi> Senate has return'd</l>
<l>No other Answer, to our late Demands,</l>
<l>But absolute Denial and Defiance.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>It is what I expected—We shall teach them</l>
<l>An humbler Language soon—Hast thou assembled,</l>
<l>As I desir'd, the <hi>Volscian</hi> Chiefs in Council?</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>GALESUS.</speaker>
<l>TITUS is gone to summon their Attendance.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>It is enough—Come forth, my noble Guest!</l>
<l>And shew GALESUS how the Gods assist us.</l>
</sp>
</div2>
<div2 n="4" type="scene">
<pb n="16" facs="20"/>
<head>SCENE IV.</head>
<stage>CORIOLANUS, TULLUS, GALESUS.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>GALESUS.</speaker>
<l>O My astonish'd Soul! what do I see?</l>
<l>What! <hi>CAIUS MARCIUS! CAIUS MARCIUS</hi> here,</l>
<l>Beneath one Tent with TULLUS?</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>Ay, and more,</l>
<l>With TULLUS, now his Friend and fellow Soldier.</l>
<l>Yes, thou shalt see him thundering at the Head</l>
<l>Of <hi>Volscian</hi> Armies; he, who oft has carry'd</l>
<l>Destruction thro' their Ranks—Your Leave a Moment,</l>
<l>While to our Chiefs, and Fathers, I announce</l>
<l>Their unexpected Guest.</l>
</sp>
</div2>
<div2 n="5" type="scene">
<head>SCENE V.</head>
<stage>CORIOLANUS, GALESUS.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>Thou good old Man !</l>
<l>Close let me strain thee to my faithful Heart,</l>
<l>Which now is doubly thine, united more</l>
<l>By the Protection which thy Country gives me,</l>
<l>Than by our former Friendship.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>GALESUS.</speaker>
<l>Strange Event!</l>
<l>This is thy Work, almighty Providence!</l>
<l>Whose Power, beyond the Stretch of human Thought,</l>
<l><pb n="17" facs="23"/>
Revolves the Orbs of Empire; bids them sink</l>
<l>Deep in the deadning Night of thy Displeasure,</l>
<l>Or rise majestic o'er a wondering World.</l>
<l>The Gods by thee—I see it, CORIOLANUS,—</l>
<l>Mean to exalt us, and depress the <hi>Romans.</hi></l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>GALESUS, yes, the Gods have sent me hither;</l>
<l>Those righteous Gods; who; when vindictive Justice</l>
<l>Excites them to destroy a worthless People,</l>
<l>Make their own Crimes and Follies strike the Blow.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>GALESUS.</speaker>
<l>Cherish these Thoughts; that teach us what we are,</l>
<l>And tame the Pride of Man. There is a Power,</l>
<l>Unseen that rules th'illimitable World;</l>
<l>That guides its Motions, from the brightest Star,</l>
<l>To the least Dust of this sin-tainted Mold;</l>
<l>While Man, who madly deems himself the Lord</l>
<l>Of all, is nought but Weakness and Dependance.</l>
<l>This sacred Truths, by sure Experience taught,</l>
<l>Thou must have learnt, when, wandering all alone,</l>
<l>Each Bird, each Insect, flitting thro' the Sky,</l>
<l>Was more sufficient for itself, than thou—</l>
<l>Ah the full Image of thy Woes dissolves me!</l>
<l>The Pangs that must have torn, at parting from thee,</l>
<l>Thy Mother and thy Wife. I cannot think</l>
<l>Of that sad Scene without some Drops of Pity!</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>Who was it forc'd me to that bitter Parting?</l>
<l>Who, in one cruel hasty Moment, chas'd me</l>
<l>From Wife, from Children, Friends; and Houshold
Gods,</l>
<l>Me! who so often had protected theirs?</l>
<l>Who, from the sacred City of my Fathers</l>
<l>Drove me with Nature's Commoners to dwell,</l>
<l>To lodge beneath their wide unshelter'd Roof,</l>
<l>And at their Table feed? O blast me, Gods!</l>
<l>With ev'ry Woe! Debility of Mind,</l>
<l>Dishonour, just Contempt, and palsy'd Weakness,</l>
<l><pb n="18" facs="24"/>
If I forgive the Villains! yes GALESUS,</l>
<l>Yes, I will offer to the Powers of Vengeance</l>
<l>A great, a glorious Victim—a whole City!—</l>
<l>Why, TULLUS, this Delay?</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>GALESUS.</speaker>
<l>May CORIOLANUS</l>
<l>Be to the <hi>Volscian</hi> Nation, and himself;</l>
<l>The dread, the godlike Instrument of Justice !</l>
<l>But let not Rage and Vengeance mix their Rancour;</l>
<l>Let them not trouble with their fretful Storm,</l>
<l>Their angry Gleams, that Azure, where enthron'd</l>
<l>The calm Divinity of Justice sits</l>
<l>And pities, while she punishes, Mankind.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>What saidst thou? What, against the Powers of
Vengeance?</l>
<l>The Gods gave honest Anger, just Revenge,</l>
<l>To be the awful Guardians of the Rights</l>
<l>And native Dignity of Human kind.</l>
<l>O were it not for them, the saucy World</l>
<l>Would grow a noisome Nest of little Tyrants!</l>
<l>Each Carrion Crow, on Eagle Merit perch'd,</l>
<l>Would peck his Eyes out, and the mungril Cur</l>
<l>At pleasure bait the Lyon—No, GALESUS,</l>
<l>I would not rashly, nor on light Occasion,</l>
<l>Receive the deep Impression in my Breast;</l>
<l>But when the Base, the Brutal and Unjust,</l>
<l>Or worse than all, th' Ungrateful, stamp it there,</l>
<l>O I will then with Luxury supreme,</l>
<l>Enjoy the Pleasure of offended Gods,</l>
<l>A righteous, just Revenge!—Behold my Soul.</l>
<stage>[Enter an Officer.</stage>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>OFFICER.</speaker>
<l>My Lords, th'assembled Chiefs desire your Presence.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>GALESUS.</speaker>
<l>Come, noble MARCIUS; let My joyful Hand</l>
<l>Conduct thee thither—Doubt not thy Reception</l>
<l>Will be proportion'd to thy Fame and Merit.</l>
</sp>
</div2>
<div2 n="6" type="scene">
<pb n="19" facs="25"/>
<head>SCENE VI.</head>
<stage>The back Scene opens, and discovers the Deputies of
the <hi>Volscian</hi> States, assembled in Council. They
rise and salute <hi>CORIOLANUS;</hi> then resume their
Places.</stage>
<stage>GALESUS, TULLUS, CORIOLANUS, SENATORS.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>GALESUS.</speaker>
<l>Assembled States, and Captains of the <hi>Volsci,</hi></l>
<l>Behold the Chief so much renown'd in War;</l>
<l>Our once so formidable Foe; but now</l>
<l>Our proffer'd Friend and Soldier—CAIUS MARCIUS.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>1<span rend="sup">st</span> SENATOR.</speaker>
<l>We give him hearty Welcome, from our Souls!</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>Most noble Chiefs, and Fathers of the <hi>Volsci,</hi></l>
<l>I need not say, how by the People's Rage;</l>
<l>And the poor Weakness of the timid Nobles,</l>
<l>I am expell'd from <hi>Rome.</hi> Had I confin'd</l>
<l>My Wishes merely to a safe Retreat,</l>
<l>Some <hi>Latine</hi> City might have given me that;</l>
<l>Or any nameless Corner. What imports it,</l>
<l>Where a tame patient Exile rots in Silence?</l>
<l>But, <hi>Volscian</hi> Lords, permit me to declare,</l>
<l>I would at once cut short my useless Days,</l>
<l>Rather than be that despicable Wretch,</l>
<l>Who neither can take Vengeance on his Foes,</l>
<l>Nor serve his Friends. That is my Temper, Chiefs.</l>
<l>I shall be glad to merit, by my Sword,</l>
<l>Th'Asylum which I seek among the <hi>Volsci.</hi></l>
<l><hi>Rome</hi> is our common Foe: Then let us join</l>
<l>Our common Suffering, Passions, and Resentments.</l>
<l>Yes, tho' but one, I bring so many Wrongs,</l>
<l>So large a Share of powerful Enmity,</l>
<l><pb n="20" facs="26"/>
Into the War, as gives me the Presumption,</l>
<l>To offer to the <hi>Volscian</hi> States th'Alliance</l>
<l>Even of my single Arm.—</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>That single Arm</l>
<l>Is in itself a numerous Army, MARCIUS;</l>
<l>The <hi>Volscians</hi> so esteem it—But proceed.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>I will not mention, <hi>Volscian</hi> Chiefs, what Talent</l>
<l>The World allows me to possess in War:</l>
<l>But be it what it will, you may employ it.</l>
<l>Soldier, or Captain, in whatever Station</l>
<l>You place me, I will lose each Drop of Blood,</l>
<l>Or with this Hand I'll fix the <hi>Volscian</hi> Standard</l>
<l>On the proud Towers of Capitolian <hi>Jove.</hi></l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>Chiefs of the <hi>Volscian</hi> League, I give you Joy</l>
<l>Of our new Citizen, the noble MARCIUS.</l>
<l>The Genius of the <hi>Volscian</hi> State has sent him,</l>
<l>Whetted by Wrongs into a keener Hatred</l>
<l>Than that we bear to <hi>Rome.</hi> It were contemning,</l>
<l>With impious self-sufficient Arrogance,</l>
<l>This Bounty of the Gods, not to accept,</l>
<l>With every Mark of Honour, of his Service.</l>
<l>I, <hi>Volscians,</hi> I, even ATTIUS TULLUS, give,</l>
<l>First of you all, my Voice, that CAIUS MARCIUS</l>
<l>Be now receiv'd to high Command among us;</l>
<l>That instantly we do appoint him General</l>
<l>Of half our Troops, which here, with your Consent,</l>
<l>I to him yield.—Speak, Chiefs, is this your Pleasure?</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>1<span rend="sup">st</span> SENATOR.</speaker>
<l>It is,—We give unanimous Consent.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS,</speaker>
<stage>embracing him.</stage>
<l>MARCIUS, I joy to call thee my Companion,</l>
<l>And Collegue in this War.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="21" facs="27"/>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>By all the Gods!</l>
<l>Thou art the generous Victor of my Soul!</l>
<l>Yes, TULLUS, I am conquer'd by thy Virtue.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>GALESUS.</speaker>
<l>Tho' I have oft, on great Occasions? TULLUS,</l>
<l>Beheld thee in the Senate, and the Field,</l>
<l>Cover'd with Glory; yet, I must avow,</l>
<l>I never saw thee shew such genuine Greatness,</l>
<l>Such true Sublimity of Soul, as now.</l>
<l>To scorn th' all-powerful Charm of selfish Passions,</l>
<l>Chiefly the dazzling Pride of Emulation,</l>
<l>That noble Weakness of Heroic Minds,</l>
<l>To sink thyself that thou may'st raise thy Country;</l>
<l>To put the Sword into thy Rival's Hand,</l>
<l>And twine thy promis'd Laurels round his Brow—</l>
<l>O 'tis a Flight beyond the highest Point</l>
<l>Of Martial Glory! and what few can reach.</l>
<l>Go forth, the chosen Ministers of Justice;</l>
<l>And may that awful Power, whose secret Hand</l>
<l>Sways all our Passions, turns our partial Views</l>
<l>All to its own dread Purposes, attend you !</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>I burn to enter on the glorious Task</l>
<l>You now have mark'd me out. How slow the Time</l>
<l>To the warm Soul, that in the very Instant</l>
<l>It forms, would, execute, a great Design.</l>
<l>'Tis my Advice we march direct to <hi>Rome;</hi></l>
<l>We cannot be too quick. Let the first Dawn</l>
<l>See us in bright Array before her Walls.</l>
<l>Perhaps when they behold their Exile there,</l>
<l>Back'd by your Force, some conscious Hearts among
them</l>
<l>May feel th' Alarm of Guilt.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>I much approve</l>
<l>Of this Advice. 'Tis what I thought before,</l>
<l>Ere strengthen'd, MARCIUS, by thy mighty Arm:</l>
<l><pb n="22" facs="28"/>
But now 'tis doubly right. Here, <hi>Volscian</hi> Chiefs,</l>
<l>Here let our Council terminate—The Troops</l>
<l>Have had Repose sufficient. Strait to <hi>Rome,</hi></l>
<l>Come, let us urge our March—As yet the Stars</l>
<l>Ride in their middle Watch: we shall with Ease,</l>
<l>Reach it by Dawn.—</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>Yes, we have time—too much!</l>
<l>Six tedious Hours till Morn—But hence! away!</l>
<l>My Soul on Fire anticipates the Dawn.</l>
</sp>
<trailer>End of the Second <hi>ACT.</hi></trailer>
</div2>
</div1>
<div1 n="3" type="act">
<pb n="23" facs="29"/>
<head>ACT III.</head>
<div2 n="1" type="scene">
<head>SCENE I.</head>
<stage>CORIOLANUS, TULLUS, VOLUSIUS, TITUS, <hi>with a
Croud of</hi> Volscian <hi>Officers. Acclamations behind
the Scenes.</hi></stage>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>NO more—I merit not this lavish Praise.</l>
<l>True, we have driven the <hi>Roman</hi> Legions back,</l>
<l>Defeated, and disgrac'd—But what is this?</l>
<l>Nothing, ye <hi>Volsci,</hi> nothing yet is done.</l>
<l>We but begin the wonderous Leaf of Story,</l>
<l>That marks the <hi>Roman</hi> Doom. At length it dawns,</l>
<l>The destin'd Hour, that eases of their Fears</l>
<l>The Nations round, and sets <hi>Hesperia</hi> free.</l>
<l>Come on, my brave Companions of the War!</l>
<l>Come, let us finish at one mighty Stroke?</l>
<l>This Toil of labouring Fate—We will, or perish!</l>
<l>While, noble TULLUS, you protect the Camp,</l>
<l>I, with my Troops, all Men of chosen Valour,</l>
<l>And well-approv'd to-day, will storm the City.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TITUS.</speaker>
<l>Beneath thy animating Conduct, MARCIUS,</l>
<l>What can the <hi>Volscian</hi> Valour not perform.</l>
<l>Thy very Sight and Voice subdues the <hi>Romans.</hi></l>
<l>When, lifting up your Helm, you shew'd your Face,</l>
<l>That like a Comet glar'd Destruction on them,</l>
<l>I saw their bravest Veterans fly before thee.</l>
<l>Their ancient Spirit has with thee forsook them,</l>
<l>And Ruin hangs o'er yon devoted Walls.</l>
<stage>[Enter an Officer; who addresses himself to <hi>Coriolanus.</hi></stage>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="24" facs="30"/>
<speaker>OFFICER.</speaker>
<l>My Lord, a Herald is arriv'd from <hi>Rome,</hi></l>
<l>To say, a Deputation from the Senate,</l>
<l>Attended by the Ministers of Heaven,</l>
<l>A venerable Train of Priests and Flamens,</l>
<l>Is on the Way, address'd to you.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>To me!</l>
<l>What can this Message mean!—Stand to your Arms,</l>
<l>Ye <hi>Volscian</hi> Troops; and let these <hi>Romans</hi> pass</l>
<l>Betwixt the lowring Frown of double Files.</l>
<l>What! do they think me such a milky Boy,</l>
<l>To pay my Vengeance with a few soft Words.</l>
<l>Come, fellow Soldiers, TULLUS, come, and see.</l>
<l>If I betray the Honours you have done me.</l>
<stage>[Goes out with a Train of <hi>Volscian</hi> Officers.</stage>
</sp>
</div2>
<div2 n="2" type="scene">
<head>SCENE II.</head>
<stage>TULLUS, VOLUSIUS, <hi>who remain.</hi></stage>
<sp>
<speaker>VOLUSIUS,</speaker>
<stage>after some Silence,</stage>
<l>Are we not, TULLUS, failing in our Duty</l>
<l>Not to attend our General?</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>How! What saidst thou?</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>VOLUSIUS.</speaker>
<l>Methought, my Lord, his parting Orders were,</l>
<l>We should attend the Triumph now preparing</l>
<l>O'er all his Foes at once—<hi>Romans</hi> and <hi>Volsci!</hi></l>
<l>Come, we shall give Offence.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>Of this no more.</l>
<l>I pray thee spare thy bitter Irony.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="25" facs="31"/>
<speaker>VOLUSIUS.</speaker>
<l>Shall I then speak without Disguise?</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>Speak out:</l>
<l>With all the honest Bluntness of a Friend.</l>
<l>Think'st thou I fear the Truth?</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>VOLUSIUS.</speaker>
<l>Then, TULLUS, know,</l>
<l>Thou art no more the General of the <hi>Volsci.</hi></l>
<l>Thou hast, by this thy generous Weakness, sunk</l>
<l>Thyself into a private Man of <hi>Antium.</hi></l>
<l>Yes, thou hast taken from thy laurel'd Brow</l>
<l>The well-earn'd Trophies of thy Toils and Perils,</l>
<l>Thy springing Hopes, the fairest ever budded,</l>
<l>And heap'd them on a Man too proud before.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>He bears it high.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>VOLUSIUS.</speaker>
<l>Death, and Perdition! high!</l>
<l>With uncontroul'd Command!—You see, already,</l>
<l>He will not be encumber'd with the Fetters</l>
<l>Of our Advice. He speaks his Sovereign Will;</l>
<l>On every Hand he issues out his Orders,</l>
<l>As to his natural Slaves.—For you, my Lord,</l>
<l>He has, I think, confin'd you to your Camp,</l>
<l>There in inglorious Indolence to languish;</l>
<l>While he, beneath your blasted Eye, shall reap</l>
<l>The Harvest of your Honour.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>No, VOLUSIUS,</l>
<l>Whatever Honour shall by him be gain'd</l>
<l>Reverts to me, from whole superior Bounty</l>
<l>He drew the Means of all his glorious Deeds.</l>
<l>This mighty Chief, this Conqueror of <hi>Rome</hi></l>
<l>Is but my Creature.—</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>VOLUSIUS.</speaker>
<l>Wretched Self-Delusion;</l>
<l>He and the <hi>Volscians</hi> know he is thy Master.</l>
<l><pb n="26" facs="32"/>
He acts as such in all Things—Now by <hi>Mars,</hi></l>
<l>Could my abhorrent Soul endure the Thought</l>
<l>Of stooping to a <hi>Roman</hi> Chief, I here</l>
<l>Would leave thee in thy solitary Camp,</l>
<l>And go where Glory calls.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>Indeed, VOLUSIUS,</l>
<l>I did expect more equal Treatment from him.</l>
<l>But what of that?—The generous Pride of Virtue</l>
<l>Disdains to weigh too nicely, the Returns</l>
<l>Her Bounty meets with—Like the liberal Gods,</l>
<l>From her own gracious Nature she bestows,</l>
<l>Nor stoops to ask Reward—Yet must I own,</l>
<l>I thought he would not have so soon forgot</l>
<l>What he so lately was, and what I am.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>VOLUSIUS.</speaker>
<l>Gods! knew ye not his Character before?</l>
<l>Did you not know his Genius was to yours</l>
<l>Averse, as are Antipathies in Nature?</l>
<l>High, over-weening, tyranously Proud,</l>
<l>And only fit to hold Command o'er Slaves?</l>
<l>Hence, as repugnant to that equal Life,</l>
<l>Which is the quickening Soul of all Republicks,</l>
<l>The <hi>Roman</hi> People cast him forth; and we,</l>
<l>Shall we receive the Bane of their Repose,</l>
<l>Into our Breast? Are we less free than they?</l>
<l>Or shall we be more patient of a Tyrant?</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>All this I knew. But while his Imperfections</l>
<l>Are thy glad Theme, thou hast forgot his Virtues.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>VOLUSIUS.</speaker>
<l>I leave that Subject to the smooth GALESUS,</l>
<l>And these his <hi>Volscian</hi> Flatterers—His Virtues!</l>
<l>Trust me there is no Insolence that treads</l>
<l>So high as that which rears itself on Virtue.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>Well, be it so—I meant, that even his Vices</l>
<l>Should, on this great Occasion, serve the <hi>Volsci.</hi></l>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="27" facs="33"/>
<speaker>VOLUSIUS.</speaker>
<l>Confusion! there it is! there lurks the Sting</l>
<l>Of our Dishonour! while this MARCIUS leads</l>
<l>The <hi>Roman</hi> Armies, ours are driven before him.</l>
<l>Behold, he changes Sides; when with him changes</l>
<l>The Fortune of the War. Strait they grow <hi>Volsci</hi></l>
<l>And we victorious <hi>Romans</hi>—Such, no doubt,</l>
<l>Such is his secret Boast—Ay, this vile Brand,</l>
<l>Success itself will fix for ever on us;</l>
<l>And, TULLUS, thou, 'tis thou must answer for it.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS,</speaker>
<stage>aside.</stage>
<l>His Words are Daggers to my Heart; I feel</l>
<l>Their Truth, but am asham'd to own my Folly.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>VOLUSIUS.</speaker>
<l>O Shame! O Infamy! the Thought consumes me,</l>
<l>It scalds my Eyes with Tears, to see a <hi>Roman</hi></l>
<l>Borne on our Shoulders to immortal Fame:</l>
<l>Just in the happy Moment that decided</l>
<l>The long Dispute of Ages, that for which</l>
<l>Our generous Ancestors had toil'd and bled,</l>
<l>To see him then step in and steal our Glory!</l>
<l>O that we first had perish'd all! A People,</l>
<l>Who cannot find in their own proper Force</l>
<l>Their own Protection, are not worth the saving !</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS</speaker>
<l>It must have Way! I will no more suppress it—</l>
<l>Know, then, my rough old Friend, no less than thee</l>
<l>His Conduct hurts me, and upbraids my Folly.</l>
<l>I wake as from a Dream. What Demon mov'd me?</l>
<l>What doating Generosity? his Woes,</l>
<l>Was it his Woes! to see the brave reduc'd</l>
<l>To trust his mortal Foe? perhaps, a little</l>
<l>That work'd within my Bosom—But, VOLUSIUS,</l>
<l>That was not all—I will to thee confess</l>
<l>The Weakness of my Heart—Yes, it was Pride,</l>
<l>The dazzling Pride to see my Rival-Warriour</l>
<l>The great CORIOLANUS, bend his Soul,</l>
<l>His haughty Soul, to sue for my Protection.</l>
<l><pb n="28" facs="34"/>
Protection said I? were it that alone,</l>
<l>I had been base to have refus'd him that,</l>
<l>To have refus'd him aught a gallant Foe</l>
<l>Owes to a gallant Foe.—But to exalt him</l>
<l>To the same Level, nay above myself;</l>
<l>To yield him the Command of half my Troops,</l>
<l>The choicest acting Half—That, that was Madness!</l>
<l>Was weak, was mean, unworthy of a Man!—</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>VOLUSIUS.</speaker>
<l>I scorn to flatter thee—It was indeed.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>Curse on the Slave, GALESUS ! soothing, he</l>
<l>Seiz'd the fond Moment of Infatuation,</l>
<l>And clinch'd the Chains my generous Folly forg'd,</l>
<l>How shall I from this Labyrinth escape?</l>
<l>Must it then be! what cruel Genius dooms me,</l>
<l>In War or Peace to creep beneath his Fortune?</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>VOLUSIUS.</speaker>
<l>That Genius is thyself. If thou canst bear</l>
<l>The very Thought of stooping to this <hi>Roman,</hi></l>
<l>Thou from that Moment art his Vassal, TULLUS;</l>
<l>By that thou dost acknowledge, Parent Nature</l>
<l>Has form'd him thy Superior. But if fix'd</l>
<l>Upon the Base of manly Resolution,</l>
<l>Thou say'st—I will be free! I will command!</l>
<l>I and my Country! then—O never doubt it—</l>
<l>We shall find Means to crush this vain Intruder;</l>
<l>Even I myself—this Hand—</l>
<l>Nay, hear me, TULLUS,</l>
<l>'Tis not yet come to that, that last Resource.</l>
<l>I do not say we should employ the Dagger,</l>
<l>While other, better Means are in our Power.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>No, my VOLUSIUS, Fortune will not drive us,</l>
<l>Or I am much deceiv'd, to that Extreme:</l>
<l>We shall not want the strongest fairest Plea,</l>
<l>To give a solemn Sanction to his Fate.</l>
<l>He will betray himself. Whate'er his Rage</l>
<l><pb n="29" facs="35"/>
Of Passion talks, a Weakness for his Country</l>
<l>Sticks in his Soul, and he is still a <hi>Roman.</hi></l>
<l>Soon shall we see him tempted to the Brink</l>
<l>Of this sure Precipice—Then down, at once,</l>
<l>Without Remorse, we hurl him to Perdition!—</l>
<l>But hark! the Trumpet calls us to a Scene</l>
<l>I should detest, if not from Hope we thence</l>
<l>May gather Matter to mature our Purpose.</l>
</sp>
</div2>
<div2 n="3" type="scene">
<head>SCENE III.</head>
<stage>The back Scene opens, and discovers <hi>CORIOLANUS</hi>
sitting on his Tribunal, attended by his Lictors,
and a Croud of <hi>Volscian</hi> Officers. Files of
Troops drawn up on either Hand. In the Depth
of the Scene appear the Deputies from the <hi>Roman</hi>
Senate, <hi>M. MINUCIUS, POSTHUMUS COMINIUS,
SP. LARTIUS, P. PINNARIUS,</hi> and
<hi>Q. SULPITIUS,</hi> all Consular Senators, who had
been his most zealous Friends. And behind them
march the Priests, the Sacrificers, the Augurs,
and the Guardians of the sacred Things, drest in
their Ceremonial Habits. These advance slowly,
betwixt the Files of Soldiers, under Arms. As
<hi>TULLUS</hi> enters, <hi>CORIOLANUS</hi> rising salutes him.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>Here, noble TULLUS, sit, and judge my Conduct;</l>
<l>Nor spare to check me if I act amiss.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>MARCIUS, the <hi>Volscian</hi> Fate is in thy Hands.</l>
<stage><hi>[CORIOLANUS</hi> is seated again, and <hi>TULLUS</hi> places
himself upon a Tribunal on his Left Hand. Mean
time the <hi>Roman</hi> Deputies advance up to <hi>CORIOLANUS</hi>
and salute him, which he returns.</stage>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>What, <hi>Romans,</hi> from the Generals of the <hi>Volsci</hi></l>
<l>Is your Demand?</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="30" facs="36"/>
<speaker>MINUCIUS.</speaker>
<l>O CORIOLANUS, <hi>Rome,</hi></l>
<l>Nurse of thy tender Years, thy Parent-City,</l>
<l>Her Senators, her People, Priests, and Augurs,</l>
<l>Her every Order and Degree, by us,</l>
<l>Thy ever-zealous, still-unshaken Friends,</l>
<l>Sue in the most pathetic Terms for Peace.</l>
<l>And if in This; constrain'd, We from our Maxim,</l>
<l>Never to ask but give it, must depart;</l>
<l>It is some Consolation, in the State</l>
<l>To which thou hast by thy superior Valour</l>
<l>Reduc'd us, that we ask it from a <hi>Roman.</hi></l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>I was a <hi>Roman</hi> once, and thought the Name</l>
<l>Was hot dishonour'd by me; but it pleas'd</l>
<l>Your Lords, the Mob of <hi>Rome,</hi> to take it from me;</l>
<l>Nor will I now receive it back again.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>MILUCIUS.</speaker>
<l>The Name thou mayst reject, but canst not throw</l>
<l>The Duties from thee which that Name imports;</l>
<l>Indissoluble Duties, bound upon thee</l>
<l>By the strong Hand of Nature, and confirm'd</l>
<l>By the dread Sanction of all-ruling <hi>Jove.</hi></l>
<l>Then hear thy Country's supplicating Voice;</l>
<l>By all those Duties I conjure thee hear us.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>Well—I will hear thee; speak, declare thy Message.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>MILUCIUS.</speaker>
<l>Give Peace, give healing Peace, to two brave Nations,</l>
<l>Fatigu'd with War, arid sick of cruel Deeds!</l>
<l>To carry on Destruction's easy Trade,</l>
<l>Afflict Mankind, and scourge the World with War,</l>
<l>Is what each wicked, each ambitious Man,</l>
<l>Who lets his furious Passions loose, may do:</l>
<l>But in the flattering Torrent of Success,</l>
<l>To check his Rage, and drop th'avenging Sword,</l>
<l>When a repenting People ask it of him,</l>
<l>That is the genuine Bounty of a God.</l>
<l><pb n="31" facs="37"/>
Then urge no further this your just Resentment;</l>
<l>Which, injur'd as you are, you needs must feel,</l>
<l>But never ought to carry into Action,</l>
<l>Against your sacred Country; whence you drew</l>
<l>Your Life, your Virtues, every mortal Good,</l>
<l>That very Valour you employ against her.</l>
<l>Stop, CORIOLALUS, ere, beyond Retreat,</l>
<l>You plunge yourself in Crimes. To the fierce Joy</l>
<l>Of Vengeance push'd to barbarous Excess,</l>
<l>Repentance will succeed, and sickning Horror.</l>
<l>Consider too the slippery State of Fortune.</l>
<l>The Gods take Pleasure oft, when haughty Mortals</l>
<l>On their own Pride erect a mighty Fabrick,</l>
<l>By slightest means, to lay their towering Schemes</l>
<l>Low in the Dust, and teach them they are nothing.</l>
<l>Return, thou virtuous <hi>Roman!</hi> to the Bosom</l>
<l>Of thy imploring Country. Lo! her Arms,</l>
<l>She fondly spreads to take thee back again,</l>
<l>And by redoubled Love efface her Harshness.</l>
<l>Return, and crown thee with the noblest Wreathe,</l>
<l>Which Glory can bestow—the Palm of Mercy!</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>MARCUS MINUCIUS, and ye other <hi>Romans,</hi></l>
<l>Respected Senators, and holy Flamens,</l>
<l>Attend, and take to your Demand this Answer:</l>
<l>Why court you me, the Servant of the <hi>Volsci?</hi></l>
<l>It is to them that you must bend for Peace,</l>
<l>Which on these only Terms they will accord you.</l>
<l>"Restore the conquer'd Lands, your former Wars</l>
<l>"Have ravish'd from them: from their Towns an
Cities,</l>
<l>"Won by your Arms, withdraw your Colonies;</l>
<l>"And to the full Immunities of <hi>Rome</hi></l>
<l>"Frankly admit them, as you have the <hi>Latines.</hi>"</l>
<l>Then, <hi>Romans,</hi> you have Peace, and not till then !</l>
<l>If these are Terms which suit not your Ambition,</l>
<l>They suit the State to which the <hi>Volscian</hi> Arms</l>
<l><pb n="32" facs="38"/>
Have now reduc'd you—We have learn'd from <hi>Rome</hi></l>
<l>To use our Fortune, and command the Vanquish'd.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS,</speaker>
<stage>(aside.)</stage>
<l>Death to my Hopes! I'm now his Slave for ever.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS,</speaker>
<stage>addressing himself to the Volsci</stage>
<l>This, my illustrious Patrons and Protectors,</l>
<l><hi>Volsci,</hi> to you I ow'd. Permit me now</l>
<l>To do myself and injur'd Honour Justice.</l>
<stage><hi>[Turning again to the</hi> Romans.</stage>
<l>As to the Liberty you idly vaunt</l>
<l>To give me of returning to your City,</l>
<l>'Tis what I hold unworthy of Acceptance.</l>
<l>Can I return into th' ungrateful Bosom</l>
<l>Of a distracted State, where, to the Rage</l>
<l>Of a vile senseless Populace, the Laws</l>
<l>Are by your shameful Weakness given a Prey?</l>
<l>Who are the Men that hold the Sway among you?</l>
<l>And whom have you expell'd, as even unworthy</l>
<l>To live within the Cincture of your Walls!—</l>
<l>O the wild Thought breaks in and troubles Reason!—</l>
<l>With what, ye <hi>Romans,</hi> can the sowerest Censor,</l>
<l>The most envenom'd Malice, justly charge me?</l>
<l>Did I e'er break your Laws? Nay, did I e'er</l>
<l>Do aught that could disturb the sacred Order,</l>
<l>The Peace and social Harmony of Life;</l>
<l>Or taint your ancient Sanctity of Manners?</l>
<l>What was my Crime? I could not bear to see</l>
<l>Your Dignity debas'd: to see the Rabble,</l>
<l>Tread on the reverend grey Authority</l>
<l>Of Senatorial Wisdom: Yes, for you,</l>
<l>In your Defence I did enrage this Monster;</l>
<l>And yet you basely left me to its Fury.</l>
<l>Then talk no more of Services and Friendship:</l>
<l>A Friend, who can, and does not shield, betrays me.</l>
<l>Or if the Power was wanting, then your Senate</l>
<l>Is sunk into Servility, and Bondage,</l>
<l>Nor should a Freeman deign to sit among you.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="33" facs="39"/>
<speaker>MINUCIUS.</speaker>
<l>The Wisest are sometimes compell'd to yield</l>
<l>To popular Storms: Yet I defend not, MARCIUS,</l>
<l>Our timid Conduct; we have felt our Error,</l>
<l>And now invite thee back to aid the Senate,</l>
<l>With thy heroic Spirit to restrain</l>
<l>The giddy Rage of Faction, and to hold</l>
<l>The Reins of Government more firm hereafter.</l>
<l>As to th' Appeal which thou hast nobly made</l>
<l>In Vindication of thy spotless Fame,</l>
<l>With Pleasure we confirm it, and bear Witness</l>
<l>To all thy public and thy private Virtues:</l>
<l>But let us also beg thee not to stain</l>
<l>The Brightness of that Glory by a Crime,</l>
<l>Which, unrepented, would disgrace them all,</l>
<l>A dire rebellious War against thy Country.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>Absurd! What can you mean? To call a People,</l>
<l>Who with the last Indignity have us'd me,</l>
<l>To call my Foes my Country! No, MINUCIUS,</l>
<l>It is the generous Nation of the <hi>Volsci,</hi></l>
<l>These brave, these virtuous Men, you see around me,</l>
<l>Who, when I wander'd a poor helpless Exile,</l>
<l>Took Pity of my Injuries and Woes;</l>
<l>Forgot the former Mischiefs of my Sword;</l>
<l>Heap'd on me Kindness, Honours, Dignities;</l>
<l>Fear'd not to trust me with this high Command,</l>
<l>And plac'd me here the Guardian of their Cause:—</l>
<l>Be Witness, <hi>Jove!</hi>—It is alone their Nation</l>
<l>I henceforth will acknowlege for my Country!</l>
<l>Let this suffice—You have my Answer, ROMANS.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>COMINIUS.</speaker>
<l>This Answer, CORIOLANUS, is the Dictate</l>
<l>More of thy Pride than Magnanimity:</l>
<l>'Tis thy Revenge that gives it, not thy Virtue.</l>
<l>Art thou above the Gods? who joy to show'r</l>
<l>Their doubled Goodness on repenting Mortals?</l>
<l>But think not I intend, by This, to urge</l>
<l><pb n="34" facs="40"/>
Our proffer'd Peace, so harshly treated, further.</l>
<l>That were a Weakness ill becoming <hi>Romans.</hi></l>
<l>Yet I must tell thee, it would better fuit</l>
<l>A fierce despotic Chief of barbarous Slaves,</l>
<l>Than the calm Dignity of one who sits</l>
<l>In the grave Senate of a free Republic,</l>
<l>To talk so high, and as it were to thrust</l>
<l>Plebeians from the native Rights of Man.—</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>Ha! dost thou come the People's Advocate</l>
<l>To Me, COMINIUS! Com'st thou to insult me?</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>COMINIUS.</speaker>
<l>Nay, hear me, MARCIUS:—These grey Hairs
impower me</l>
<l>To set thee right before this great Assembly:</l>
<l>And there was once a Time, thou wouldst have heard</l>
<l>Thy General with more Deference and Patience.—</l>
<l>I tell thee then, whoe'er amidst the Sons</l>
<l>Of Reason, Valour, Liberty, and Virtue,</l>
<l>Displays distinguish'd Merit, is a Noble</l>
<l>Of Nature's own creating. Such have risen</l>
<l>Sprung from the Dust, or where had been our Honours?</l>
<l>And such in radiant Bands will rise again,</l>
<l>In yon immortal City, that, when most</l>
<l>Deprest by Fate, and near apparent Ruin,</l>
<l>Returns, as with an Energy divine,</l>
<l>On her astonish'd Foes, and shakes them from her—</l>
<l>Your Pardon, VOLSCI—But This, CORIOLANUS,</l>
<l>Is what I had to say.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>And I have heard it—</l>
<stage>[Rising from his Tribunal; and
the Priests advancing to address
him, he prevents them.</stage>
<l>For you, ye awful Ministers of Heaven,</l>
<l>Let me not hear your holy Lips profan'd</l>
<l>By urging what my Duty must refuse.</l>
<l>I bow in Adoration to the Gods;</l>
<l><pb n="35" facs="41"/>
I venerate their Servants. But there is,</l>
<l>There is a Power, their chief, their darling Care,</l>
<l>The Guardian of Mankind, which to betray</l>
<l>Were violating all—And that is JUSTICE.</l>
<l>So far my public Character demands;</l>
<l>So far my Honour.—Now, what should forbid</l>
<l>The Man, and Friend, to be indulg'd a little?</l>
<l>Permit me to embrace thee, good MINUCIUS;</l>
<l>Thee, LARTIUS; you, PINNARIUS and SULPICIUS:</l>
<l>But chiefly thee, COMINIUS, who first rais'd me</l>
<l>To Deeds of Arms; who from thy Consolar Brow</l>
<l>Took thy own Crown, and with it circled mine.</l>
<l>Tho nought can shake my Purpose, yet I wish</l>
<l>That <hi>Rome</hi> had sent me others on this Errand.</l>
<l>I thank you for your Friendship. The Protection,</l>
<l>Which you have given to those, whom once I call'd</l>
<l>By tender Names, I would not now remember.</l>
<l>How shall I—say—return your generous Goodness?</l>
<l>O there is nothing you, as Friends, can ask,</l>
<l>My grateful Heart will not with Pleasure grant you.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>COMINIUS.</speaker>
<l>We thank thee, <hi>CORIOLANUS</hi>—But a <hi>Roman</hi></l>
<l>Disdains that Favour you refuse his Country.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l><hi>To the</hi> Volscian <hi>Officers.</hi></l>
<l>See that they be, with due Regard and Safety,</l>
<l>Conducted back.</l>
<stage>[To the <hi>Roman</hi> Senators.</stage>
<l>I will suspend th' Assault,</l>
<l>Till to these Terms, of which we will not bate</l>
<l>The smallest Part, your Senate may have Time</l>
<l>To send their latest Answer. Then we cut</l>
<l>All further Treaty off. <hi>Romans,</hi> farewell.</l>
</sp>
<trailer>The End of the Third <hi>ACT.</hi></trailer>
</div2>
</div1>
<div1 n="4" type="act">
<pb n="36" facs="42"/>
<head>ACT IV.</head>
<div2 n="1" type="scene">
<head>SCENE I.</head>
<stage>TULUS alone.</stage>
<sp>
<l>WHAT is the Mind of Man? A restless Scene</l>
<l>Of Vanity and Weakness; shifting still,</l>
<l>As shift the Lights of our uncertain Knowlege;</l>
<l>Or as the various Gale of Passion breathes.</l>
<l>None ever thought himself more deeply founded</l>
<l>On what is right, nor felt a nobler Ardor,</l>
<l>Than I, when I invested CAIUS MARCIUS</l>
<l>With this ill-judg'd Command. Now it appears</l>
<l>Distraction, Folly, monstrous Folly! Meanness!</l>
<l>And down I plunge, betray'd even by my Virtue,</l>
<l>From Gulph to Gulph, from Shame to deeper Shame.</l>
</sp>
</div2>
<div2 n="2" type="scene">
<head>SCENE II.</head>
<stage>TULLUS. GALESUS.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>GALESUS.</speaker>
<l>I listen'd, TULLUS, to th' important Scene</l>
<l>That lately pass'd before us, with most strict</l>
<l>Unprejudic'd Attention; and have since</l>
<l>Revolv'd it in my Mind, both as a Man,</l>
<l>Ally,d to all Mankind, and as a <hi>Volscian.</hi></l>
<l>Indeed our Terms are high, and by the Manner</l>
<l><pb n="37" facs="43"/>
In which they were prescrib'd by CORIOLANUS,</l>
<l>Are what we cannot hope will e'er be granted.</l>
<l>They should be soften'd. Let us yield a little,</l>
<l>Conscious ourselves to a great Nation's Pride,</l>
<l>The Pride of human Nature. Could the <hi>Romans</hi></l>
<l>Stoop to such Peace, commanded by the Sword,</l>
<l>They then were Slaves, unworthy our Alliance.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>Gods! do I hear in thee, one of the Chiefs</l>
<l>Intrusted with the Honour of the <hi>Volsci,</hi></l>
<l>An Advocate for <hi>Rome?</hi></l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>GALESUS.</speaker>
<l>I glory, TULLUS,</l>
<l>To own myself an Advocate for Peace.</l>
<l>Peace is the happy natural State of Man;</l>
<l>War his Corruption, his Disgrace—</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>His Safeguard!</l>
<l>His Pride! his Glory!—What but War, just War,</l>
<l>Gave <hi>Greece</hi> her Heroes? Those who drew the Sword</l>
<l>(As we do now) against the Sons of Rapine;</l>
<l>To quell proud Tyrants, and to free Mankind.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>GALESUS.</speaker>
<l>Yes, TULLUS, when to just Defence the Warrior</l>
<l>Confines his Force, he is a worship'd Name,</l>
<l>Dear to Mankind, the First and Best of Mortals!</l>
<l>Yet still, if this can by soft Means be done,</l>
<l>And fair Accommodation, that is better.</l>
<l>Why should we purchase with the Blood of Thousands,</l>
<l>What may be gain'd by mutual just Concession?</l>
<l>Why give up Peace, the best of human Blessings,</l>
<l>For the vain cruel Pride of useless Conquest?</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>These soothing Dreams of philosophic Quiet</l>
<l>Are only fit for unfrequented Shades.</l>
<l>The Sage should quit the busy bustling World</l>
<l><pb n="38" facs="44"/>
Ill suited to his gentle Meditations,</l>
<l>And in some Desart find that Peace he loves.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>GALESUS.</speaker>
<l>Mistaken Man! Philosophy consists not</l>
<l>In airy Schemes, or idle Speculations:</l>
<l>The Rule and Conduct of all social Life</l>
<l>Is her great Province. Not in lonely Cells</l>
<l>Obscure she lurks, but holds her heavenly Light</l>
<l>To Senates and to Kings, to guide their Councils,</l>
<l>And teach them to reform and bless Mankind.</l>
<l>All Policy but her's is false, and rotten;</l>
<l>All Valour not conducted by her Precepts</l>
<l>Is a destroying Fury sent from Hell</l>
<l>To plague unhappy Man, and ruin Nations.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>To stop the Waste of that destroying Fury,</l>
<l>Is the great Cause and Purpose of this War.</l>
<l>Art thou a Friend to Peace?—subdue the <hi>Romans.</hi></l>
<l>Who, who, but they, have turn'd this antient Land,</l>
<l>Where, from <hi>Saturnian</hi> Times, harmonious Concord</l>
<l>Still lov'd to dwell, into a Scene of Blood,</l>
<l>Of endless Discord, and perpetual Rapine?</l>
<l>The Sword, the vengeful Sword, must drain away</l>
<l>This boiling Blood, that thus disturbs the Nations!</l>
<l>Talk not of Terms. It is a vain Attempt</l>
<l>To bind th' Ambitious and Unjust by Treaties:</l>
<l>These they elude a thousand specious Ways;</l>
<l>Or if they cannot find a fair Pretext,</l>
<l>They blush not in the Face of Heaven to break them.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>GALESUS.</speaker>
<l>Why then affronted Heaven will combat for us.</l>
<l>Set Justice on our Side, and then my Voice</l>
<l>Shall be as loud for War as thine; my Sword</l>
<l>Shall strike as deep; at least my Blood shall flow</l>
<l>As freely, TULLUS, in my Country's Cause.</l>
<l>But as I then would die to serve the <hi>Volscians,</hi></l>
<l>So now I dare to serve them by opposing,</l>
<l>Even with my single Voice, th' impetuous Torrent</l>
<l><pb n="39" facs="45"/>
That hurries us away beyond the Bounds</l>
<l>Of temperate Wisdom; and presume to tell thee,</l>
<l>It is thy Passion, not thy Prudence dictates</l>
<l>This haughty Language.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>Yes, it is my Passion,</l>
<l>A Passion for the Glory of my Country,</l>
<l>That scorns your narrow Views of timid Prudence.</l>
<l>Our injur'd Honour drew our Swords, and never</l>
<l>Shall they be sheath'd while I command the <hi>Volscians,</hi></l>
<l>Till <hi>Rome</hi> submits to <hi>Antium.</hi>—</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>GALESUS.</speaker>
<l><hi>Rome</hi> will perish</l>
<l>Ere she submit; and she has still her Walls,</l>
<l>The Strength of her Allies, her native Valour,</l>
<l>Which oft has sav'd her in the worst Extremes,</l>
<l>And, stronger yet than all, Despair, to aid her.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>All these will nought avail her, if our Fears</l>
<l>Come not to her Assistance—But, GALESUS,</l>
<l>Why urge you this to me? Go, talk to MARCIUS.</l>
<l>The War has given him all his Pride could hope for,</l>
<l>To see <hi>Rome</hi>'s Senate humbled at his Feet:</l>
<l>He now may wish to reign in Peace at <hi>Antium,</hi></l>
<l>And thou, perhaps, art come an Envoy from him,</l>
<l>To learn if I shall prove a quiet Subject.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>GALESUS.</speaker>
<l>Thro' this unguarded Opening of thy Soul,</l>
<l>I see what stings thee—Ah! beware of Envy!</l>
<l>If that pale Fury seize thee, thou art lost!</l>
<l>TULLUS, 'tis easier far, from the clear Breast,</l>
<l>To keep out treacherous Vice, than to expel it.</l>
<l>Farewel. Remember I have done my Duty.</l>
<stage>[Goes out.</stage>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS,</speaker>
<stage>alone.</stage>
<l>This Man discerns my Heart—Well: What of that?</l>
<l>Am I afraid its Movement should be seen?</l>
<l>I, whose clear Thoughts have never shunn'd the Light,</l>
<l><pb n="40" facs="46"/>
Must I now seek to hide them? O Misfortune!</l>
<l>To have reduc'd myself to such a State,</l>
<l>So much beneath the Greatness of my Soul,</l>
<l>That, like a Coward, I must learn to practise</l>
<l>The wretched Arts of vile Dissimulation!</l>
<l>By Heaven I will not do't—I will not stoop</l>
<l>To veil my Discontent a Moment longer.</l>
<l>But see! my Rival comes, the happy MARCIUS.</l>
<l>His haughty Mien, his very Looks, affront me.</l>
</sp>
</div2>
<div2 n="3" type="scene">
<head>SCENE III.</head>
<stage>CORIOLANUS, TULLUS.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>TULLUS, I have receiv'd Intelligence,</l>
<l>That a strong Body of the <hi>Latin</hi> Troops</l>
<l>Is in full March to raise the Siege of <hi>Rome.</hi></l>
<l>Another Day will bring them to its Aid.</l>
<l>But go thou forth, and lead the valiant Bands,</l>
<l>By thee commanded, to repel these Succours.</l>
<l>Go, and cut off from <hi>Rome</hi> its last Resource.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>I lead my Troops, from the great Scene of Action,</l>
<l>From falling <hi>Rome,</hi> which, ere To-morrow's Sun</l>
<l>Shall set, may be our Prey! Sure you forget</l>
<l>My Rank and Station—I disdain the Service:</l>
<l>Give it to some you may command. For me,</l>
<l>I own no Master but the <hi>Volscian</hi> States.</l>
<l><hi>Rome</hi> is my Object. I from <hi>Antium</hi> brought</l>
<l>The noblest Army ever shook her Walls.</l>
<l>And shall I now, on that decisive Day,</l>
<l>Doom'd by the Gods to lay her Pride in Ashes,</l>
<l>Shall I be absent from the glorious Work?</l>
<l>It is the highest Outrage even to think it.—</l>
<l>Just Gods! Dost thou presume to give thy Orders</l>
<l><pb n="41" facs="47"/>
To me? to me! thy Equal in Command?</l>
<l>Nay, thy Superior? Was it not my Hand,</l>
<l>My lavish Hand, bestow'd thy Power upon thee?</l>
<l>And know, proud <hi>Roman,</hi> that the Man who gave it,</l>
<l>Can at his Will resume it.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>I propos'd</l>
<l>This Expedition to thee as thy Friend,</l>
<l>Not as thy General, <hi>TULLUS.</hi> We are both</l>
<l>Commanders here; and for my Share of Pow'r,</l>
<l>Whene'er the Council of the <hi>Volscian</hi> States,</l>
<l>Who cloath'd me with it, shall again demand it,</l>
<l>I at their Feet will lay it down, persuaded,</l>
<l>The canker'd Tongue of Envy's Self must own,</l>
<l>That by my Service I have well deserv'd it.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS</speaker>
<l>Was it to Them, or Me, you hither came</l>
<l>To crave Protection? Was not then your Fortune,</l>
<l>Your Liberty, your Life, at my Disposal?</l>
<l>I rais'd you from the Dust, a wretched Exile,</l>
<l>An Outcast, helpless, friendless, driven to beg</l>
<l>The lowest Refuge which Despair can seek,</l>
<l>Shelter amidst thy Foes. My pitying Goodness</l>
<l>Protected, trusted, and believ'd you grateful.</l>
<l>O ill-plac'd Confidence! What for all this</l>
<l>Is thy Return? Pride; Self-sufficiency,</l>
<l>Councils apart from mine; despotic Orders;</l>
<l>The Glory of the War all pilfer'd from me:</l>
<l>And, to complete the Whole, a <hi>Latin</hi> Army</l>
<l>Now conjur'd up to draw me from the Siege;</l>
<l>Till by cajoling our tame Chiefs, and dazling</l>
<l>The senseless Eyes of the low Mob of Soldiers,</l>
<l>Thou shalt be solely seated in the Power</l>
<l>Which, thank my Folly! now is shar'd betwixt us.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>Immortal Gods! Hear I these Words from TULLUS!</l>
<l>I will be calm—I will.—Thou dost accuse me</l>
<l>Of the worst Vice that can debase Mankind,</l>
<l><pb n="42" facs="48"/>
Of black Ingratitude. On what Foundations?</l>
<l>What have I done to merit such a Charge?</l>
<l>Is it my Fault, if in the <hi>Volscian</hi> Army</l>
<l>My Name is as rever'd and great as thine?</l>
<l>Can I forbid Authority, and Fame,</l>
<l>To follow Merit and Success?—You knew</l>
<l>The Man whom you employ'd, and should have known,</l>
<l>He would not be a Cypher in Employment.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>Think'st thou my Heart can better brook than thine</l>
<l>To be that Cypher! that dishonour'd Tool!</l>
<l>Subservient to th' Ambition of another?</l>
<l>Gods! I had rather live a drudging Peasant,</l>
<l>Unknown to Glory, in some <hi>Alpine</hi> Village;</l>
<l>Than, at the Head of these victorious Legions,</l>
<l>Bear the high Name of Chief, without the Power.</l>
<l>No, MARCIUS, no. I will command indeed:</l>
<l>And thou shalt learn, with all the <hi>Volscian</hi> Army,</l>
<l>To treat their General with Respect.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>Respect!</l>
<l>O TULLUS! TULLUS! by the Powers divine!</l>
<l>I bore thee once Respect, as high as Man</l>
<l>Can shew to Man. From thee, my Foe, my Rival,</l>
<l>I nor disdain'd nor fear'd to ask Protection.</l>
<l>You gave me all I ask'd, you gave me more,</l>
<l>With noble Warmth of Heart! which, to Esteem,</l>
<l>Added the Ties to Gratitude, and Friendship.</l>
<l>Whatever since, in Council, or in Arms,</l>
<l>Has been by me atchiev'd, was done for thee.</l>
<l>My Glory all was thine. The Plams I gain'd</l>
<l>Only compos'd a Garland for his Brow,</l>
<l>Who rais'd this banish'd Man to tread on <hi>Rome.</hi></l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>To tread on him who rais'd him—That, I know,</l>
<l>Is thy ambitious Purpose; but be certain,</l>
<l>However <hi>Rome</hi> may bend beneath thy Fortune,</l>
<l>Thou shalt not find an easy Conquest here.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="43" facs="49"/>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>May <hi>Jove</hi> with Lightning strike me to the Centre!</l>
<l>If from the Day I saw thy Face at <hi>Antium,</hi></l>
<l>My Heart has ever form'd one secret Thought</l>
<l>To hurt thy Honour, or depress thy Greatness:</l>
<l>I was thy Friend, thy Soldier, and thy Servant.</l>
<l>But now I will as openly avow,</l>
<l>Thy Jealousy has, with envenom'd Breath,</l>
<l>Made such a sudden Ravage in our Friendship,</l>
<l>I know not what to think.—</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>Think me thy Foe.</l>
<l>There is no lasting Friendship with the Proud.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>Nor with the Jealous—But of this enough.</l>
<l>Come, let us turn our Fire a nobler Way:</l>
<l>We have a worthier Quarrel to pursue.—</l>
<l>It were unjust, dishonourable, base,</l>
<l>Our Pride should hurt the <hi>Volscian</hi> Cause.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>No, MARCIUS.</l>
<l>I mean to guard it better for the future:</l>
<l>The <hi>Volscian</hi> Cause is safest with a <hi>Volscian.</hi></l>
<l>I therefore claim, insist upon my Right;</l>
<l>That you shall yield me my Command in Turn.</l>
<l>The first Attack was yours: 'Tis scanty Justice,</l>
<l>The second should be mine.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>TULLUS, 'tis yours.</l>
<l>O it imports not which of us command!</l>
<l>Give me the lowest Rank among your Troops:</l>
<l>All <hi>Italy</hi> will know, the Voice of Fame</l>
<l>Will tell all future Times, that I was present;</l>
<l>That CORIOLANUS in the <hi>Volscian</hi> Army</l>
<l>Assisted, when Imperial <hi>Rome</hi> was sack'd;</l>
<l>That City which, while he maintain'd her Cause,</l>
<l>Invincible herself, made <hi>Antium</hi> tremble.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>What arrogant Presumption!</l>
</sp>
</div2>
<div2 n="4" type="scene">
<pb n="44" facs="50"/>
<head>SCENE. IV.</head>
<stage>To them VOLUSIUS, entering hastily.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>Ha! VOLUSIUS,</l>
<l>Thy Looks declare some Message of Importance.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>VOLUSIUS.</speaker>
<l>TULLUS, they do—I was to find thee, MARCIUS.</l>
<l>To thee a second Deputation comes,</l>
<l>Thy Mother, and thy Wife, with a long Train</l>
<l>Of all the noblest Ladies <hi>Rome</hi> can boast,</l>
<l>In mourning Habits clad, approach our Camp,</l>
<l>Preceded by a Herald, to demand</l>
<l>Another Audience of Thee.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>How, VOLUSIUS!</l>
<l>Said you, the <hi>Roman</hi> Ladies! Low, indeed,</l>
<l>Must be the State of <hi>Rome,</hi> when thus her Matrons</l>
<l>She sends amidst the Tumults of a Camp,</l>
<l>To beg Protection for the Men, who lie</l>
<l>Trembling behind their Ramparts—Come! once more!</l>
<l>And see me put an End to Prayers and Treaty!</l>
</sp>
</div2>
<div2 n="5" type="scene">
<head>SCENE V.</head>
<stage>TULLUS. VOLUSIUS.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>VOLUSIUS.</speaker>
<l>TULLUS, 'tis well. This answers to my Wishes.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>How? What is well? That humbled <hi>Rome</hi> once more</l>
<l>Shall deck him with the Trophies of our Arms?</l>
</sp>
<pb n="45" facs="51"/>
<sp>
<speaker>VOLUSIUS.</speaker>
<l>And hop'st thou nothing from this blest Event?</l>
<l>They who have often blasted mighty Heroes,</l>
<l>Who oft have stoln into the firmest Hearts,</l>
<l>And melted them to Folly; They, my Friend,</l>
<l>Will do what Wisdom never could effect.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>Think'st thou the Prayers and Tears of wailing Women</l>
<l>Can shake the Man, who with such cold Disdain</l>
<l>Stood firm against those venerable Consuls,</l>
<l>And spurn'd the Genius of his kneeling Country?</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>VOLUSIUS.</speaker>
<l>It was his Pride alone that made him ours.</l>
<l>That Passion kept him firm; the flattering Charm</l>
<l>Of humbling those, who in their Persons bore</l>
<l>The whole collected Majesty of <hi>Rome.</hi></l>
<l>These Women are no proper Objects for it:</l>
<l>He cannot triumph o'er his Wife and Mother.</l>
<l>On this my Hopes are founded, that these Women</l>
<l>May by their gentler Influence subdue him.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>Whate'er th' Event, he shall no longer here,</l>
<l>As wave his Passions, dictate Peace, or War.</l>
<l>Whether his stubborn Soul maintains its Firmness,</l>
<l>Or yields to Female Prayers, the <hi>Volscian</hi> Honour</l>
<l>Will be alike betray'd. If <hi>Rome</hi> prevails,</l>
<l>He stops our conquering Arms from her Destruction;</l>
<l>If he rejects her Suit, he reigns our Tyrant.</l>
<l>But, by th' Immortal Gods! his short-liv'd Empire</l>
<l>Shall never see you radiant Sun descend.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>VOLUSIUS.</speaker>
<l>Blest be those Gods that have at last inspir'd thee</l>
<l>With Resolution equal to thy Cause,</l>
<l>The Cause of Liberty!—</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>Be sure, VOLUSIUS,</l>
<l>If that should happen which thy Hopes portend;</l>
<l>Should he, by Nature tam'd, disarm'd by Love,</l>
<l><pb n="46" facs="52"/>
Respite the <hi>Roman</hi> Doom—He seals his own:</l>
<l>By Heaven! he dies.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>VOLUSIUS.</speaker>
<l>Let me embrace thee, TULLUS!</l>
<l>Now breaking from the Cloud, which, like the Sun,</l>
<l>Thy own too bounteous Beams had drawn around thee.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>You was deceiv'd, my Friend. When I with Tameness,</l>
<l>With Tameness which astonish'd thy brave Spirit,</l>
<l>Seem'd to submit to that unequal Sway</l>
<l>He arrogated o'er me; know, my Heart</l>
<l>Ne'er swell'd so high as in that cruel Moment.</l>
<l>My Indignation, like th' imprison'd Fire</l>
<l>Pent in the troubled Breast of glowing <hi>Aetna,</hi></l>
<l>Burnt deep and silent: But, collected now,</l>
<l>It shall beneath its Fury bury MARCIUS!</l>
<l>'Tis fixt. Our Tyrant dies.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>VOLUSIUS.</speaker>
<l>TULLUS, my Sword</l>
<l>Here claims to be employ'd.—Nor mine alone—</l>
<l>There are some worthy <hi>Volsci</hi> still remaining,</l>
<l>Who think with us, and pine beneath the Laurels</l>
<l>A <hi>Roman</hi> Chief bestows.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>Go, find them strait,</l>
<l>And bring them to the Space before his Tent;</l>
<l>'Tis there he will receive this Deputation.</l>
<l>Then if he sinks beneath these Womens Prayers—</l>
<l>Or if he does not—But, VOLUSIUS, wait,</l>
<l>I give thee strictest Charge to wait my Signal.</l>
<l>Perhaps I may find Means to free the <hi>Volsci</hi></l>
<l>Without his Blood. If not—We will be free.</l>
</sp>
<trailer>The End of the Fourth <hi>ACT.</hi></trailer>
</div2>
</div1>
<div1 n="5" type="act">
<pb n="47" facs="53"/>
<head>ACT. V.</head>
<div2 n="1" type="scene">
<head>SCENE I.</head>
<stage>Trumpets sounding.</stage>
<stage>The Scene discovers the Camp, a Croud of
<hi>Volscian</hi> Officers with Files of Soldiers,
drawn up as before. Enter <hi>CORIOLANUS,
TULLUS, GALESUS, VOLUSIUS.</hi> The
<hi>Roman</hi> Ladies advance slowly from the
Depth of the Stage, with <hi>VETURIA</hi> the
Mother of <hi>CORIOLANUS,</hi> and <hi>VOLUMNIA</hi>
his Wife, at their Head, all clad in Habits
of Mourning. <hi>CORIOLANUS</hi> stands
at the Head of the <hi>Volsci,</hi> surrounded by
his Lictors; but, when he perceives his
Mother and Wife, after some Struggle, he
advances, and goes hastily to embrace them.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS </speaker>
<stage>advancing.</stage>
<l>LOWER your Fasces, Lictors—</l>
<l>Oh VETURIA!</l>
<l>Thou best of Parents!</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>VETURIA.</speaker>
<l>CORIOLANUS, stop.</l>
<l>Whom am I to embrace? A Son, or Foe?</l>
<l>Say, in what Light am I regarded here?</l>
<l>Thy Mother, or thy Captive?</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="48" facs="54"/>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>Justly, Madam,</l>
<l>You check my Fondness, that, by Nature hurry'd,</l>
<l>Forgot I was the General of the <hi>Volsci,</hi></l>
<l>And you a Deputy from hostile <hi>Rome.</hi></l>
<stage>He goes back to his former Station.</stage>
<l>I hear you with Respect. Speak your Commission.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>VETURIA.</speaker>
<l>Think not I come a Deputy from <hi>Rome.</hi></l>
<l><hi>Rome,</hi> once rejected, scorns a Second Suit.</l>
<l>You have already heard whate'er the Tongue</l>
<l>Of Eloquence can plead, whate'er the Wisdom</l>
<l>Of sacred Age, the Dignity of Senates,</l>
<l>And Virtue, can enforce. Behold me here,</l>
<l>Sent by the Shades of your immortal Fathers,</l>
<l>Sent by the Genius of the <hi>Marcian</hi> Line,</l>
<l>Commission'd by my own maternal Heart,</l>
<l>To try the soft, yet stronger Powers of Nature.</l>
<l>Thus authoriz'd, I ask, nay, claim a Peace,</l>
<l>On equal, fair, and honourable Terms,</l>
<l>To Thee, to <hi>Rome,</hi> and to the <hi>Volscian</hi> People.</l>
<l>Grant it, my Son! Thy Mother begs it of thee,</l>
<l>Thy Wife, the best, the kindest of her Sex,</l>
<l>And these illustrious Matrons, who have sooth'd</l>
<l>The gloomy Hours thou hast been absent from us.</l>
<l>We, by whate'er is great and good in Nature,</l>
<l>By every Duty, by the Gods, conjure Thee!</l>
<l>To grant us Peace, and turn on other Foes</l>
<l>Thy Arms, where thou may'st purchase virtuous Glory.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>COIRIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>I should, VETURIA, break those holy Bonds</l>
<l>That hold the wide Republic of Mankind,</l>
<l>Society, together; I should grow</l>
<l>A Wretch, unworthy to be call'd thy Son;</l>
<l>I should, with my VOLUMNIA's fair Esteem,</l>
<l>Forfeit her Love; these Matrons would despise me—</l>
<l>Could I betray the <hi>Volscian</hi> Cause, thus trusted,</l>
<l><pb n="49" facs="55"/>
Thus recommended to me—No, my Mother,</l>
<l>You cannot sure, you cannot ask it of me!</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>VETURIA.</speaker>
<l>And does my Son so little know me? me!</l>
<l>Who took such Care to form his tender Years,</l>
<l>Left to my Conduct by his dying Father?</l>
<l>Have I so ill deserv'd that Trust? Alas!</l>
<l>Am I so low in thy Esteem, that thou</l>
<l>Should'st e'er imagine I could urge a Part</l>
<l>Which in the least might stain the <hi>Marcian</hi> Honour?</l>
<l>No, let me perish rather! perish All!</l>
<l>Life has no Charms compar'd to spotless Glory!</l>
<l>I only ask, thou would'st forbid thy Troops</l>
<l>To waste our Lands, and to assault yon City,</l>
<l>Till Time be given for mild and righteous Measures.</l>
<l>Grant us but One Year's Truce: Mean while thou may'st,</l>
<l>With Honour and Advantage to both Nations,</l>
<l>Betwixt us mediate a perpetual Peace.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>Alas! my Mother! That were granting all.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>VETURIA.</speaker>
<l>Canst thou refuse me such a just Petition,</l>
<l>The First Request thy Mother ever made Thee?</l>
<l>Canst thou to her Intreaties, Prayers, and Tears,</l>
<l>Prefer a savage obstinate Revenge?</l>
<l>Have Love and Nature lost all Power within thee?</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>No,—in my Heart they reign as strong as ever.</l>
<l>Come, I conjure you, quit ungrateful <hi>Rome,</hi></l>
<l>Come, and complete my Happiness at <hi>Antium,</hi></l>
<l>You, and my dear VOLUMNIA—There, VETURIA,</l>
<l>There shall you see with what Respect the <hi>Volsci</hi></l>
<l>Will treat the Wife and Mother of their General.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>VETURIA.</speaker>
<l>Treat me thyself with more Respect, my Son;</l>
<l>Nor dare to shock my Ears with such Proposals.</l>
<l>Shall I desert my Country, I who come</l>
<l>To plead her Cause? Ah no!—A Grave in <hi>Rome</hi></l>
<l><pb n="50" facs="56"/>
Would better please me, than a Throne at <hi>Antium.</hi></l>
<l>How hast thou thus forsaken all my Precepts?</l>
<l>How hast thou thus forgot thy Love to <hi>Rome?</hi></l>
<l>O CORIOLANUS, when with hostile Arms,</l>
<l>With Fire and Sword, you enter'd on our Borders,</l>
<l>Did not the fostering Air, that breathes around us,</l>
<l>Allay thy guilty Fury, and instil</l>
<l>A certain native Sweetness thro' thy Soul?</l>
<l>Did not your Heart thus murmur to itself?</l>
<l>"These Walls contain whatever can command</l>
<l>"Respect from Virtue, or is dear to Nature,</l>
<l>"The Monuments of Piety and Valour,</l>
<l>"The sculptur'd Forms, the Trophies of my Fathers,</l>
<l>"My houshold Gods, my Mother, Wife and Children!"</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>Ah! you seduce me with too tender Views!—</l>
<l>These Walls contain the most corrupt of Men,</l>
<l>A base seditious Herd; who trample Order,</l>
<l>Distinction, Justice, Laws, beneath their Feet,</l>
<l>Insolent Foes to Worth, the Foes of Virtue!</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>VETURIA.</speaker>
<l>Thou hast not thence a Right to lift thy Hand</l>
<l>Against the whole Community, which forms</l>
<l>Thy ever-sacred Country—That consists</l>
<l>Not of coeval Citizens alone:</l>
<l>It knows no Bounds; it has a Retrospect</l>
<l>To Ages past; it looks on those to come;</l>
<l>And grasps of all the general Worth and Virtue.</l>
<l>Suppose, my Son, that I to thee had been</l>
<l>A harsh obdurate Parent, even unjust:</l>
<l>How would the monstrous Thought with Horror strike thee,</l>
<l>Of plunging, from Revenge, thy raging Steel</l>
<l>Into her Breast, who nurs'd thy infant Years!—</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l><hi>Rome</hi> is no more! that <hi>Rome</hi> which nurs'd my Youth;</l>
<l>That <hi>Rome,</hi> conducted by <hi>Patrician</hi> Virtue,</l>
<l><pb n="51" facs="57"/>
She is no more! My Sword shall now chastise</l>
<l>These Sons of Pride and Dirt! Her upstart Tyrants!</l>
<l>Who have debas'd the noblest State on Earth</l>
<l>Into a sordid Democratic Faction.</l>
<l>Why will my Mother join her Cause to theirs?</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>VETURIA.</speaker>
<l>Forbid it, <hi>Jove!</hi> that I should e'er distinguish</l>
<l>My Interest from the general Cause of <hi>Rome;</hi></l>
<l>Or live to see a foreign hostile Arm</l>
<l>Reform th'Abuses of our Land of Freedom. Pausing.</l>
<l>But 'tis in vain, I find, to reason more.</l>
<l>Is there no way to reach thy filial Heart,</l>
<l>Once fam'd as much for Piety as Courage?</l>
<l>Oft hast thou justly triumph'd, CORIOLANUS;</l>
<l>Now yield one Triumph to thy widow'd Mother;</l>
<l>And send me back amidst the loud Acclaims,</l>
<l>The grateful Transports of deliver'd <hi>Rome,</hi></l>
<l>The happiest far, the most renown'd of Women!</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>Why, why, VETURIA, wilt thou plead in vain?</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS. </speaker>
<stage><hi>Aside to</hi> VOLUSIUS.</stage>
<l>See, see, VOLUSIUS, how the strong Emotions</l>
<l>Of powerful Nature shake his inmost Soul!</l>
<l>See how they tear him.—If he long resists them,</l>
<l>He is a God, or something worse than Man.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>VETURIA.</speaker>
<l>O MARCIUS, MARCIUS! canst thou treat me thus?</l>
<l>Canst thou complain of <hi>Rome</hi>'s Ingratitude,</l>
<l>Yet be to me so cruelly ungrateful?</l>
<l>To me! who anxious rear'd thy Youth to Glory?</l>
<l>Whose only Joy, these many Years, has been,</l>
<l>To boast that CORIOLANUS was my Son?</l>
<l>And dost thou then renounce me for thy Mother?</l>
<l>Spurn me before these Chiefs, before those Soldiers,</l>
<l>That weep thy stubborn Cruelty? Art thou</l>
<l><pb n="52" facs="58"/>
The hardest Man to me in this Assembly?</l>
<l>Look at me! Speak!</l>
<stage>[Pausing, during which he appears
in great Agitation.</stage>
<l>Still dost thou turn away?</l>
<l>Inexorable? Silent?—Then, behold me,</l>
<l>Behold thy Mother, at whose Feet thou oft</l>
<l>Hast kneel'd with Fondness, kneeling now at thine,</l>
<l>Wetting thy stern Tribunal with her Tears.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<stage>[Raises her.</stage>
<l>VETURIA, rise. I cannot see Thee thus.</l>
<l>It is a Sight uncomely, to behold</l>
<l>My Mother at my Feet, and that to urge</l>
<l>A Suit, relentless Honour must refuse.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>VOLUMNIA.</speaker>
<stage>[Advancing.</stage>
<l>Since CORIOLANUS, thou dost still retain,</l>
<l>In spite of all thy Mother now has pleaded,</l>
<l>Thy dreadful Purpose, Ah! how much in vain</l>
<l>Were it for me to join my Supplications!</l>
<l>The Voice of thy VOLUMNIA, once so pleasing</l>
<l>How shall it hope to touch the Husband's Heart,</l>
<l>When proof against the Tears of such a Parent?</l>
<l>I dare not urge what to thy Mother thou</l>
<l>So firmly hast deny'd—But I must weep—</l>
<l>Must weep, if not thy harsh Severity,</l>
<l>At least thy Situation. O permit me,</l>
<stage>[Taking his Hand.</stage>
<l>To shed my gushing Tears upon thy Hand!</l>
<l>To press it with the cordial Lips of Love!</l>
<l>And take my last Farewel!</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>Yet, yet, my Soul,</l>
<l>Be firm, and persevere—</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>VOLUMNIA.</speaker>
<l>Ah CORIOLANUS!</l>
<l>Is then this Hand▪ this Hand to me devoted,</l>
<l>The Pledge of Nuptial Love, that has so long</l>
<l><pb n="53" facs="59"/>
Protected, bless'd, and shelter'd us with Kindness,</l>
<l>Now lifted up against us? Yet I love it,</l>
<l>And, with submissive Veneration, bow</l>
<l>Beneath th' Affliction which it heaps upon us.</l>
<l>But O! what nobler Transports would it give thee!</l>
<l>What Joy beyond Expression! couldst thou once</l>
<l>Surmount the furious Storm of fierce Revenge,</l>
<l>And yield thee to the Charms of Love and Mercy.</l>
<l>Oh make the glorious Trial!</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>Mother! Wife!</l>
<l>Are all the Powers of Nature leagu'd against me?</l>
<l>I cannot!—will not!—Leave me, my VOLUMNIA!</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>VOLUMNIA.</speaker>
<l>Well, I obey—How bitter thus to part!</l>
<l>Upon such Terms to part! perhaps for ever!—</l>
<l>But tell me, ere I hence unroot my Feet,</l>
<l>When to my lonely Home I shall return,</l>
<l>What from their Father, to our little Slaves,</l>
<l>Unconscious of the Shame to which you doom them,</l>
<l>What shall I say?</l>
<stage>[Pausing; He highly agitated.</stage>
<l>Nay—tell me, CORIOLANUS!</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>Tell thee! What shall I tell thee? See these Tears!</l>
<l>These Tears will tell thee what exceeds the Power</l>
<l>Of Words to speak, whate'er the Son, the Husband,</l>
<l>And Father, in one complicated Pang,</l>
<l>Can feel—But leave me;—even in Pity leave me!</l>
<l>Cease, cease, to torture me, my dear <hi>VOLUMNIA!</hi></l>
<l>You only tear my Heart; but cannot shake it:</l>
<l>For by th' immortal Gods, the dread Avengers</l>
<l>Of broken Faith!—</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>VOLUMNIA.</speaker>
<stage>[Kneeling.</stage>
<l>Oh swear not, CORIOLANUS!</l>
<l>Oh vow not our Destruction!</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="54" facs="60"/>
<speaker>VETURIA.</speaker>
<l>Daughter, rise.</l>
<l>Let us no more before the <hi>Volsian</hi> People</l>
<l>Expose ourselves a Spectacle of Shame.</l>
<l>It is in vain we try to melt a Breast,</l>
<l>That, to the best Affections Nature gives us,</l>
<l>Prefers the worst—Hear me, proud Man! I have</l>
<l>A Heart as stout as thine. I came not hither,</l>
<l>To be sent back rejected, baffled, sham'd,</l>
<l>Hateful to <hi>Rome,</hi> because I am Thy Mother:</l>
<l>A <hi>Roman</hi> Matron knows, in such Extremes,</l>
<l>What Part to take—And thus I came provided.</l>
<stage>[Drawing from under her Robe a Dagger.</stage>
<l>Go! barbarous Son! go! double Parricide!</l>
<l>Rush o'er my Corse to thy belov'd Revenge!</l>
<l>Tread on the bleeding Breast of her, to whom</l>
<l>Thou ow'st thy Life!—Lo, thy first Victim!</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>Seizing her Hand.</l>
<l>Ha!</l>
<l>What dost thou mean?</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>VETURIA.</speaker>
<l>To die, while <hi>Rome</hi> is free,</l>
<l>To seize the Moment ere thou art her Tyrant.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>O use thy Power more justly! Set not thus</l>
<l>My treacherous Heart in Arms against my Reason.</l>
<l>Here! here! thy Dagger will be well employ'd;</l>
<l>Strike here! and reconcile my fighting Duties.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>VETURIA.</speaker>
<l>Off!—Set me free!—Think'st thou that Grasp, which binds</l>
<l>My feeble Hand, can fetter too my Will?</l>
<l>No, my proud Son! Thou canst not make me live,</l>
<l>If <hi>Rome</hi> must fall!—No Pow'r on Earth can do it!</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>Pity me, generous VOLSCI!—You are Men—</l>
<l>Must it then be?—Confusion!—Do I yield?</l>
<l>What is it? Is it Weakness? Is it Virtue?—</l>
<l>Well!—</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="55" facs="61"/>
<speaker>VETURIA.</speaker>
<l>What? Speak!</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>O, no!—my stifled Words refuse</l>
<l>A Passage to the Throes that wring my Heart.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>VETURIA.</speaker>
<l>Nay, if thou yieldest, yield like CORIOLANUS;</l>
<l>And what thou do'st, do nobly!</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<stage>[Quitting her Hand.</stage>
<l>There!—'Tis done!—</l>
<l>Thine is the Triumph, Nature!</l>
<stage>[To <hi>VETURIA</hi> in
a low Tone of Voice.</stage>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Ah VETURIA!</speaker>
<l><hi>Rome</hi> by thy Aid is sav'd—but thy Son lost.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>VETURIA.</speaker>
<l>He never can be lost, who saves his Country.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<stage><hi>[Turning to the</hi> Roman <hi>Ladies.</hi></stage>
<l>Ye Matrons, Guardians of the <hi>Roman</hi> Safety,</l>
<l>You to the Senate may report this Answer.</l>
<l>We grant the Truce you ask. But on these Terms:</l>
<l>That <hi>Rome,</hi> mean-time, shall to a Peace agree,</l>
<l>Fair, equal, just, and such as may secure</l>
<l>The Safety, Rights, and Honour of the VOLSCI.</l>
<stage>[To the Troops.</stage>
<l>VOLSCI, We raise the Siege. Go, and prepare,</l>
<l>By the first Dawn, for your Return to <hi>Antium.</hi></l>
<stage><hi>[As the Troops retire, and</hi> CORIOLANUS
<hi>turns to the</hi> Roman <hi>Ladies;</hi></stage>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<stage><hi>To</hi> VOLUSIUS <hi>aside.</hi></stage>
<l>'Tis as we wish'd, VOLUSIUS—To your Station.</l>
<l>But mark me well—Till thou shalt hear my Call,</l>
<l>I charge thee not to stir. One Offer more</l>
<l>My Honour bids me make to this proud Man,</l>
<l>Before we strike the Blow—If he rejects it,</l>
<l>His Blood be on his Head.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>VOLUSIUS.</speaker>
<l>Well! I obey you.</l>
<stage>[He goes out.</stage>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="56" facs="62"/>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>Be it thy Care, <hi>Galesus,</hi> that a Safeguard</l>
<l>Attend these noble Matrons back to <hi>Rome.</hi></l>
</sp>
</div2>
<div2 n="2" type="scene">
<head>SCENE II.</head>
<stage>CORIOLANUS. TULLUS.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>I plainly, TULLUS, by your Looks discern</l>
<l>You disapprove my Conduct.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>CAIUS MARCIUS,</l>
<l>I mean not to assail thee with the Clamour</l>
<l>Of loud Reproaches, and the War of Words;</l>
<l>But, Pride apart, and all that can pervert</l>
<l>The Light of steady Reason, here to make</l>
<l>A candid fair Proposal</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>Speak. I hear thee.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>I heed not tell thee, that I have perform'd</l>
<l>My utmost Promise. Thou hast been protected;</l>
<l>Hast had thy amplest, most ambitious Wish:</l>
<l>Thy wounded Pride is heal'd, thy dear Revenge</l>
<l>Completely sated; and, to crown thy Fortune,</l>
<l>At the same time, thy Peace with <hi>Rome</hi> restor'd.</l>
<l>Thou art no more a <hi>Volscian,</hi> but a <hi>Roman.</hi></l>
<l>Return, return; thy Duty calls upon thee,</l>
<l>Still to protect the City thou hast sav'd:</l>
<l>It still may be in Danger from our Arms.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>Insolent Man! Is this thy fair Proposal?</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>Be patient—Hear! By hospitable <hi>Jove!</hi></l>
<l>I mean thee well—Yes, one last Bounty more</l>
<l><pb n="57" facs="63"/>
I frankly will bestow. I have already</l>
<l>From <hi>Rome</hi> protected thee; now from the <hi>Volsci,</hi></l>
<l>From their just Vengeance, I will still protect Thee.</l>
<l>Retire. I will take care thou may'st with Safety.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>With Safety!—Heav'ns !—And think'st thou</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
<l>Will stoop to thee for Safety? No! my Safeguard</l>
<l>Is in myself, a Bosom void of Blame,</l>
<l>And the Great Gods, Protectors of the Just.—</l>
<l>O 'tis an Act of Cowardice and Baseness,</l>
<l>To seize the very Time my Hands are fetter'd,</l>
<l>By the strong Chain of former Obligations,</l>
<l>The safe sure Moment to insult me.—Gods!</l>
<l>Were I now free, as on that Day I was,</l>
<l>When at <hi>Corioli</hi> I tam'd thy Pride,</l>
<l>This had not been.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>Thou speak'st the Truth: It had not.</l>
<l>O for that Time again! Propitious Gods,</l>
<l>If you will bless me, grant it!—Know, for That,</l>
<l>For that dear Purpose, I have now propos'd</l>
<l>Thou should'st return. I pray thee, <hi>Marcius,</hi> do it!</l>
<l>And we shall meet again on nobler Terms.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>When to the <hi>Volsci</hi> I have clear'd my Faith,</l>
<l>Doubt not I shall find Means to meet thee nobly.</l>
<l>We then our generous Quarrel may decide</l>
<l>In the bright Front of some embattel'd Field,</l>
<l>And not in private Brawls, like fierce Barbarians.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>Thou canst not hope Acquittal from the <hi>Volsci.</hi>—</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>I do:—Nay more, expect their Approbation,</l>
<l>Their Thanks ! I will obtain them such a Peace</l>
<l>As thou durst never ask; a perfect Union</l>
<l>Of their whole Nation with imperial <hi>Rome</hi></l>
<l><pb n="58" facs="64"/>
In all her Privileges, all her Rights.</l>
<l>By the just Gods, I will! What would'st thou more?</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>What would I more! Proud <hi>Roman;</hi> This I would;</l>
<l>Fire the curst Forest where these <hi>Roman</hi> Wolves</l>
<l>Haunt and infest their nobler Neighbours round them;</l>
<l>Extirpate from the Bosom of this Land,</l>
<l>A false perfidious People, who, beneath</l>
<l>The Mask of Freedom, are a Combination</l>
<l>Against the Liberty of Human-kind,</l>
<l>The genuine Seed of Outlaws and of Robbers.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>The Seed of Gods!—'Tis not for thee, vain Boaster!</l>
<l>'Tis not for such as Thou, so often spar'd</l>
<l>By her victorious Sword, to talk of <hi>Rome,</hi></l>
<l>But with Respect and awful Veneration.</l>
<l>Whate'er her Blots, whate'er her giddy Factions,</l>
<l>There is more Virtue in one single Year</l>
<l>Of <hi>Roman</hi> Story, than your <hi>Volscian</hi> Annals</l>
<l>Can boast thro' all your creeping dark Duration!</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>I thank thy Rage. This full displays the Traitor.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>Ha! Traitor!</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>First, to thy own Country, Traitor!</l>
<l>And Traitor, now, to mine !</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>Ye heavenly Powers!</l>
<l>I shall break loose—My Rage—But let us part—</l>
<l>Lest my rash Hand should do a hasty Deed</l>
<l>My cooler Thought forbids.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>For the last time,</l>
<l>Hear me, and mark my Words; the sober Dictates</l>
<l><pb n="59" facs="65"/>
Of well-weigh'd Resolution. Thou and I</l>
<l>Are in that State for which resistless Nature</l>
<l>Has form'd us, Foes again—Begone—Return—</l>
<l>To head the <hi>Roman</hi> Troops. I grant thee Quittance</l>
<l>Full and complete of all those Obligations</l>
<l>Thou hast so oft insultingly complain'd</l>
<l>Fetter'd thy Hands. They now are free. I court</l>
<l>The worst thy Sword can do; whilst thou from me</l>
<l>Hast nothing to expect, but sore Destruction.</l>
<l>Quit then this hostile Camp. Once more I tell thee,</l>
<l>Thou art not here one single Hour in Safety.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>Think'st thou to fright me hence?</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>Thou wilt not then?</l>
<l>Thou wilt not take the Safety which I offer?</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<l>Till I have clear'd my Honour in your Council,</l>
<l>And prov'd before them all, to thy Confusion,</l>
<l>The Falshood of thy Charge; as soon in Battle</l>
<l>I would before thee fly, and howl for Mercy,</l>
<l>As quit the Station they have here assign'd me.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l><hi>Volusius!</hi> Hoa!</l>
</sp>
</div2>
<div2 n="3" type="scene">
<head>SCENE III.</head>
<stage>To them <hi>Volusius,</hi> and Conspirators, with their
Swords drawn.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>Seize, and secure the Traitor!</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="60" facs="66"/>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<stage>[Laying his Hand upon his Sword.</stage>
<l>Who dares approach me, dies!</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>VOLUSIUS.</speaker>
<l>Die thou!</l>
<stage>[As <hi>Coriolanus</hi> draws his Sword,
<hi>Volusius</hi> and the Conspirators
rush upon and stab him. <hi>Tullus</hi>
standing by without having
drawn his Sword.</stage>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>CORIOLANUS.</speaker>
<stage>[Endeavouring to free himself.</stage>
<l>Off!—Villains!</l>
<stage>[Falling.</stage>
<l>Oh murdering Slaves ! Assassinating Cowards!</l>
<stage>[Dies.</stage>
</sp>
</div2>
<div2 n="4" type="scene">
<head>SCENE IV.</head>
<stage>[Upon the Noise of the Tumult, enter hastily
to them <hi>Galesus,</hi> the other Deputies of the
<hi>Volscian</hi> States, Officers Friends of <hi>Coriolanus,</hi>
and <hi>Titus</hi> with a large Band of
Soldiers.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>GALESUS.</speaker>
<stage>[As he enters.</stage>
<l>Are we a Nation rul'd by Laws, or Fury?</l>
<l>How! Whence this Tumult?—</l>
<stage>[Pausing.</stage>
<l>Gods ! what do I see?</l>
<l>The noble MARCIUS slain!</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>You see a Traitor</l>
<l><pb n="61" facs="67"/>
Punish'd as he deserv'd, the <hi>Roman</hi> Yoke</l>
<l>That thrall'd us broken, and the <hi>Volsci</hi> free!</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>GALESUS.</speaker>
<l>Hear me, great <hi>Jove!</hi> Hear, all you injur'd Powers</l>
<l>Of Friendship, Hospitality, and Faith!</l>
<l>By that heroic Blood, which from the Ground</l>
<l>Reeking to you for Vengeance cries, I swear!</l>
<l>This impious Breach of your eternal Laws,</l>
<l>This daring Outrage on the <hi>Volscian</hi> Honour,</l>
<l>Shall find in me a rigorous Avenger!</l>
<l>On the same Earth, polluted by their Crime,</l>
<l>I will not live with these unpunish'd Ruffians !</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>TULLUS.</speaker>
<l>This Deed is mine: I claim it all!—These Men,</l>
<l>These valiant Men, were but my Instruments,</l>
<l>To punish him who to our Face betray'd us.</l>
<l>We shall not fear to answer to the <hi>Volsci,</hi></l>
<l>In a full Council of their States at <hi>Antium,</hi></l>
<l>The glorious Charge of having stabb'd their Tyrant!</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>GALESUS.</speaker>
<l>TITUS, till then secure them.</l>
<stage>[<hi>Tullus</hi> and Conspirators
are led off.</stage>
<stage>[Galesus, <hi>standing over the
Body of</hi> Coriolanus, after
a short Pause, proceeds.</stage>
<l><hi>Volscian</hi> Fathers,</l>
<l>And ye, brave Soldiers, see an awful Scene,</l>
<l>Demanding serious solemn Meditation.</l>
<l>This Man was once the Glory of his Age,</l>
<l>Disinterested, just, with every Virtue</l>
<l>Of civil Life adorn'd, in Arms unequall'd.</l>
<l>His only Blot was this; That, much provok'd,</l>
<l>He rais'd his vengeful Arm against his Country.</l>
<l>And, lo! the righteous Gods have now chastis'd him,</l>
<l>Even by the Hands of those for whom he fought.</l>
<l><pb n="62" facs="68"/>
Whatever private Views and Passions plead,</l>
<l>No Cause can justify so black a Deed:</l>
<l>These, when the angry Tempest clouds the Soul,</l>
<l>May darken Reason, and her Course controul;</l>
<l>But when the Prospect clears, her startled Eye</l>
<l>Must from the treacherous Gulph with Horror fly,</l>
<l>On whose wild Wave, by stormy Passions tost,</l>
<l>So many hapless Wretches have been lost.</l>
<l>Then be this Truth the Star by which we steer;</l>
<l><hi>Above</hi> Ourselves <hi>our</hi> COUNTRY <hi>should be dear.</hi></l>
</sp>
</div2>
<trailer>The END.</trailer>
</div1>
</body>
<back>
<div1 type="epilogue">
<pb facs="69"/>
<head>EPILOGUE.</head>
<stage>SPOKEN BY
Mrs. WOFFINGTON.</stage>
<l>WELL! Gentlemen! and are you still so vain</l>
<l>To treat our Sex with arrogant Disdain,</l>
<l>And think, to you alone by partial Heav'n</l>
<l>Superior Sense and sovereign Pow'r are given.</l>
<l>When in the Story told To-night, you find,</l>
<l>With what a boundless Sway we rule the Mind,</l>
<l>And, by a few soft Words of ours, with Ease,</l>
<l>Can turn the proudest Hearts just where we please?</l>
<l>If an old Mother had such pow'rful Charms,—</l>
<l>To stop a stubborn <hi>Roman</hi>'s conquering Arms,—</l>
<l>Soldiers and Statesmen of these Days, with you</l>
<l>What think you wou'd a fair young Mistress do?</l>
<l>If with my grave Discourse, and wrinkled Face,</l>
<l>I thus could bring a Hero to Disgrace,</l>
<l>How absolutely may I hope to reign</l>
<l>Now I am turn'd to my own Shape again !</l>
<l>However, I will use my Empire well;</l>
<l>And, if I have a certain magic Spell</l>
<l><pb facs="70"/>
Or in my Tongue, or Wit, or Shape, or Eyes,</l>
<l>Which can subdue the Strong, and fool the Wise,</l>
<l>Be not alarm'd: I will not interfere</l>
<l>In State-Affairs, nor undertake to steer,</l>
<l>The Helm of Government,—as we are told</l>
<l>Those Female Politicians did of old:</l>
<l>Such dangerous Heights I never wish'd to climb—</l>
<l>Thank Heav'n! I better can employ my Time—</l>
<l>Ask you to what my Pow'r I shall apply?</l>
<l>To make my Subjects blest, is my Reply.</l>
<l>My Purposes are gracious all, and kind,</l>
<l>Some may be told—and some may be divin'd:</l>
<l>One, which at present I have most at Heart,</l>
<l>To you without Reserve I will impart:</l>
<l>It is my Sovereign Will,—Hear, and obey,—</l>
<l>That you with Candour treat this <hi>Orphan Play.</hi></l>
</div1>
</back>
</text>
</TEI>
