<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The school for scandal</title><title type="sub"> a comedy; as it is performed at the Theatres-Royal, in London and Dublin.</title><author><persName><surname>Sheridan</surname><forename>Richard Brinsley</forename><idno type="VIAF">9922178</idno></persName></author><respStmt><resp>Transformation into valid TEI P5, improving markup, filling <gi>gap</gi>s, proofreading, and expanding header.</resp><persName xml:id="JJ"><surname>Jokisch</surname><forename>Jan</forename><idno type="ORCID">0009-0003-1026-2995</idno></persName></respStmt></titleStmt>
<extent><measure quantity="184" unit="KB">About 184 kilobytes.</measure></extent><publicationStmt><authority ref="#JJ">Jan Jokisch</authority><date>2024 December</date><idno type="ECCO_Drama">K125710.000</idno><idno type="DLPS">004821556</idno><idno type="ESTC">T193639</idno><idno type="DocNo">CW115661936</idno><idno type="TCP">K125710.000</idno>
<idno type="GaleDocNo">CW3315661936</idno><idno type="ContentSet">ECLL</idno><idno type="ImageSetID">1021100500</idno><availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0</licence></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull><titleStmt><title type="245">The school for scandal: a comedy; as it is performed at the Theatres-Royal, in London and Dublin.</title><author>Sheridan, Richard Brinsley, 1751-1816.</author></titleStmt>
<extent>94p. ; 8⁰.</extent><publicationStmt><publisher>printed for J. Bew,</publisher><date>1781.</date><pubPlace>London :</pubPlace></publicationStmt><notesStmt><note>Anonymous. By Richard B. Sheridan.</note><note>Reproduction of original from the Bodleian Library (Oxford).</note><note>English Short Title Catalog, ESTCT193639.</note><note>Electronic data. Farmington Hills, Mich. : Thomson Gale, 2003. Page image (PNG). Digitized image of the microfilm version produced in Woodbridge, CT by Research Publications, 1982-2002 (later known as Primary Source Microfilm, an imprint of the Gale Group).</note></notesStmt>
</biblFull></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Subset of the ECCO project. Included were all dramatic texts excluding operas, primarily musical forms, ballets, pantomimes, entertainments, etc. All files have been proofread systematically to produce highly improved though not yet critical versions of the plays.</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>This electronic text is based on the ECCO Text Creation Partnership, which originally keyed the file from page images and partially proofread for accuracy. To improve upon the raw ECCO TCP file, the file was transformed into valid TEI P5, <gi>gap</gi>s were filled following the original edition, and the text systematically proofread for frequent OCR mistakes. Furthermore, the attribution of dialog to speakers, the distinction between stage directions and dialog, stage directions and speech prefixes, stage directions and headings as well as the segmentation of the play into acts and scenes was checked systematically and corrected whenever deemed necessary.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><langUsage><language ident="en">eng</language></langUsage></profileDesc></teiHeader><text xml:lang="en">
<front>
<div1 type="titlepage">
<pb facs="1" ana="y"/>
<p>THE
SCHOOL FOR SCANDAL;
A
COMEDY;
AS IT IS PERFORMED AT THE
<hi>THEATRES-ROYAL</hi>
IN
LONDON AND DUBLIN.</p>
<p>LONDON.
PRINTED FOR J. BEW, IN PATER-NOSTER-ROW.
M,DCC,LXXXI.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="dramatispersonae">
<pb facs="2"/>
<head>DRAMATIS PERSONAE.</head>
<list>
<head>MEN.</head>
<item>SIR PETER TEAZLE,</item>
<item>SIR OLIVER SURFACE,</item>
<item>JOSEPH SURFACE,</item>
<item>CHARLES,</item>
<item>ROWLEY,</item>
<item>SIR BENJAMIN BACKBITE.</item>
<item>CRABTREE,</item>
<item>MOSES,</item>
<item>SNAKE,</item>
<item>TRIP,</item>
<item>SIR TOBY BUMPER,</item>
<item>GENTLEMEN,</item>
<item>SERVANT TO JOSEPH SURFACE,</item>
<item>SERVANT TO LADY SNEERWELL.</item>
</list>
<list>
<head>WOMEN.</head>
<item>LADY TEAZLE,</item>
<item>MARIA,</item>
<item>LADY SNEER WELL,</item>
<item>MRS. CANDOUR,</item>
<item>MAID TO LADY TEAZLE.</item>
</list>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<head><pb facs="3"/>THE
SCHOOL FOR SCANDAL.</head>
<div1 n="1" type="act">
<head>ACT I.</head>
<div2 type="scene">
<head>SCENE <stage>Lady SNEERWELL'S House.</stage></head>
<stage>Lady <hi>SNEERWELL</hi> and <hi>SNAKE</hi> discovered at a tea-table.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>Lady SNEERWELL.</speaker>
<p>THE paragraphs, you say, Mr. Snake, were all
inserted.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Snake.</speaker>
<p>They were, Madam; and as I copied them
myself in a seigned hand, there can be no suspicion
from whence they came.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Did you circulate the report of Lady
Brittle's intrigue with Captain Boastall?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Snake.</speaker>
<p>That's in as fine a train as your Ladyship could
wish; in the common course of things, I think it must
reach Mrs. Clacket's ears within twenty-four hours,
and then the business, you know, is as good as done.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Why yes, Mrs. Clacket has talents,
and a great deal of industry.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Snake.</speaker>
<p>True Madam, and has been tolerably successful
in her day; to my knowledge she has been the
cause of six matches being broken off, and three sons
disinherited; of four forced elopments, as many close
confinements, nine separate maintenances, and two divorces;
—nay, I have more than once traced her causing
a <hi>tete a tete</hi> in the Town and Country Magazine,
<pb n="4" facs="4"/>
when the parties never saw one another before in the
whole course of their lives.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Why yes, she has genius, but her
manner is too gross.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Snake.</speaker>
<p>True, Madam; she has a fine tongue, and a
bold invention; but then her colouring is too dark,
and the outlines rather too extravagant; she wants that
delicacy of hint, and mellowness of sneer, which distinguishes
your Ladyship's scandal.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>You are partial, Snake.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Snake.</speaker>
<p>Not in the least; every body will allow that
Lady Sneerwell can do more with a word or look than
many others with the most laboured detail, even though
they accidentally happen to have a little truth on their
side to support it.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Yes, my dear Snake, and I'll not deny
the pleasure I feel at the success of my schemes; <stage>(<hi>both
rise</hi>)</stage> wounded myself, in the early part of my life, by
the envenomed tongue of slander, I confess nothing
can give me greater satisfaction, than reducing others
to the level of my own injured reputation.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Snake.</speaker>
<p>True, Madam; but there is one affair, in
which you have lately employed me, wherein, I confess,
I am at a loss to guess at your motives.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>I presume you mean with regard to my
friend Sir Peter Teazle, and his family.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Snake.</speaker>
<p>I do; here are two young men, to whom Sir
Peter has acted as guardian since their father's death;
the eldest possessing the most amiable character, and
universally well spoken of; the youngest the most dissipated,
wild, extravagant young fellow in the world;
the former an avowed admirer of your Ladyship, and
apparently your favourite; the latter attached to Maria,
Sir Peter's ward, and confessedly admired by her: Now,
<pb n="5" facs="5"/>
on the face of these circumstances, it is utterly unaccountable
to me, why you, the widow of a city
Knight, with a large fortune, should not immediately
close with the passion of a man of such character and
expectation as Mr. Surface; and more so, why you are
so uncommonly earnest to destroy the mutual attachment
subsisting between his brother Charles and Maria.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Then at once, to unravel this mystery,
I must inform you, that love has no share whatever in
the intercourse between Mr. Surface and me.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Snake.</speaker>
<p>No!—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>No! his real views are to Maria, or
her fortune, while in his brother he finds a favoured
rival; he is, therefore, obliged to mask his real intentions,
and profit by my assistance.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Snake.</speaker>
<p>Yet still I am more puzzled why you should
interest yourself for his success.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Heavens! how dull you are! can't you
surmise a weakness I have hitherto through shame concealed
even from you? Must I confess it that Charles,
that profligate, that libertine, that bankrupt in fortune
and reputation, that he it is for whom I am thus anxious
and malicious; and to gain whom I would sacrifice
every thing.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Snake.</speaker>
<p>Now, indeed, your conduct appears consistent;
but pray how came you and Mr. Surface so confidential?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>For our mutual interest; he pretends
to, and recommends sentiment and liberality, but I
know him to be artful, close and malicious. In short,
a sentimental knave, while with Sir Peter, and indeed
with most of his acquaintances he passes for a youthful
miracle of virtue, good sense, and benevolence.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="6" facs="6"/>
<speaker>Snake.</speaker>
<p>Yes, I know Sir Peter vows he has not his
fellow in England, and has praised him as a man of
character and sentiment.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Yes; and with the appearance of being
sentimental, he has brought Sir Peter to favour his
addresses to Maria, while poor Charles has no friend
in the house, though I fear he has a powerful one in
Maria's heart, against whom we must direct our
schemes.</p>
</sp>
<stage><hi>Enter</hi> SERVANT.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>Servant.</speaker>
<p>Mr. Surface, Madam.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>L. Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Shew him up <stage>(<hi>exit Servant</hi>)</stage> he generally
calls about this hour—I don't wonder at people's
giving him to me for a lover.</p>
</sp>
<stage><hi>Enter</hi> JOSEPH SURFACE.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Lady Sneerwell, good morning to you—
Mr. Snake your most obedient.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Snake has just been rallying me upon
our attachment, but I have told him our real views;
I need not tell you how useful he has been to us, and
believe me, our confidence has not been ill placed.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Oh, Madam, 'tis impossible for me to suspect
a man of Mr. Snake's merit and accomplishments.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Oh, no compliments; but tell me
when you saw Maria, or what's more material to us,
your brother.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>I have not seen either since I left you, but I
can tell you they never met; some of your stories have
had a good effect in that quarter.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>The merit of this, my dear Snake, belongs
to you; but do your brother's distresses increase?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Every hour! I am told he had another execution
<pb n="7" facs="7"/>
in his house yesterday—in short, his dissipation
and extravagance exceeds any thing I ever heard.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Poor Charles!</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Aye, Poor Charles indeed! notwithstanding
his extravagance one cannot help pitying him; I
wish it was in my power to be of any essential service
to him; for the man who does not feel for the distresses
of a brother, even though merited by his own misconduct,
deserves to be—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Now you are going to be moral, and
forget you are among friends.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Gad, so I was, ha! ha!—I'll keep that
sentiment till I see Sir Peter, ha! ha! however it
would certainly be a generous act in you to rescue
Maria from such a libertine, who, if he is to be reclaimed
at all, can only be so by a person of your superior
accomplishments and understanding.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Snake.</speaker>
<p>I believe Lady Sneerwell, here's company
coming; I'll go and copy the letter I mentioned to
your Ladyship. Mr. Surface, your most obedient.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exit Snake.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Mr. Snake, your most obedient. I wonder
Lady Sneerwell, you would put any confidence in
that fellow.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Why so?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>I have discovered he has of late had several
conferences with old Rowley, who was formerly my
father's steward; he has never, you know, been a
friend of mine.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>And do you think he would betray us?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Not unlikely; and take my word for it,
Lady Sneerwell, that fellow has not virtue enough to
be faithful to his own villanies.</p>
</sp>
<stage><pb n="8" facs="8"/>
<hi>Enter</hi> MARIA.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Ah, Maria, my dear, how do you do?
What's the matter?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Maria.</speaker>
<p>Nothing, Madam, only this odious lover of
mine, Sir Benjamin Backbite, and his uncle Crabtree,
just called in at my guardian's; but I took the first opportunity
to slip out, and run away to your Ladyship.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Is that all?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Had my brother Charles been of the party
you would not have been so much alarmed.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Nay, now you are too severe; for I
dare say the truth of the matter is, Maria heard you
was here, and therefore came; but pray Maria, what
particular objection have you to Sir Benjamin, that you
avoid him so?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Maria.</speaker>
<p>Oh, Madam, he has done nothing; but his
whole conversation is a perpetual libel upon all his
acquaintance.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Yes, and the worst of it is, there is no advantage
in not knowing him, for he would abuse a
stranger as soon as his best friend, and his uncle is as
bad.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Maria.</speaker>
<p>For my part, I own wit looses its respect
with me, when I see it in company with malice;—
what think you Mr. Surface?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>To be sure, Madam,—to smile at a jest that
plants a thorn in the breast of another, is to become a
principal in the mischief.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Pash—there is no possibility of being
witty without a little ill nature; the malice in a good
thing is the barb that makes it stick.—What is your
<hi>real</hi> opinion, Mr. Surface?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Why my opinion is, that where the spirit
<pb n="9" facs="9"/>
of railery is suppressed, the conversation must be naturally
insipid.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Maria.</speaker>
<p>Well I will not answer how far slander may
be allowed, but in a man, I am sure it is despicable.—
We have pride, envy, rivalship, and a thousand motives
to depreciate each other; but the male slanderer,
must have the cowardice of a woman, before he can
traduce one.</p>
</sp>
<stage><hi>Enter</hi> SERVANT.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>Servant.</speaker>
<p>Mrs. Candour, Madam, if you are at
leisure, will leave her carriage.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Desire her to walk up. <stage>(<hi>Exit servant.</hi>)</stage>
Now, Maria, here's a character to your taste; though
Mrs. Candour is a little talkative, yet every body allows
she is the best natured sort of woman in the world.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Maria.</speaker>
<p>Yes—with the very gross affectation of
good nature, she does more mischief than the direct
malice of old Crabtree.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Faith it's very true; and whenever I hear
the current of abuse running hard against the characters
of my best friends I never think them in such danger,
as when Candour undertakes their defence.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>L. Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Hush! Hush! here she is.</p>
</sp>
<stage><hi>Enter Mrs.</hi> CANDOUR.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>Oh! my dear Lady Sneerwell; well,
how do you do? Mr. Surface your most obedient.—Is
there any news abroad? No! nothing good I suppose
—No! nothing but scandal!—nothing but scandal!</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph,</speaker>
<p>Just so indeed, Madam.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>Nothing but scandal!—Ah, Maria
how do you do child; what is every thing at an end
between you and Charles? What, he is too extravagant.
—Aye! the town talks of nothing else.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="10" facs="10"/>
<speaker>Maria.</speaker>
<p>I am sorry, Madam, the town is so ill employed.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour,</speaker>
<p>Aye, so am I child—but what can
one do? we can't stop people's tongues:—They hint
too, that your guardian and his Lady don't live so
agreeably together as they did.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Maria.</speaker>
<p>I am sure such reports are without foundation.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>Aye, so these things generally are:
—It's like Mr. Fashion's affair with Colonel Goterie;
though, indeed, that affair was never rightly cleared
up; and it was but yesterday Miss Prim assured me,
that Mr. and Mrs. Honeymoon were now become mere
man and wife, like the rest of their acquaintance. She
likewise hinted, that a certain widow in the next street,
had got rid of her dropsy, and recovered her shape in
a most surprizing manner.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>The licence of invention, some people give
themselves, is astonishing.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>'Tis so—but how will you stop
people's tongues? 'Twas but yesterday Mrs. Clacket
informed me, that our old friend, Miss Prudely, was
going to elope, and that her guardian caught her just
stepping into the York Diligence, with her dancingmaster.
I was informed too, that Lord Flimsey caught
his wife at a house of no extraordinary fame, and that
Tom Saunter and Sir Harry Idle, were to measure
swords on a similar occasion.—But I dare say there is
no truth in the story, and I would not circulate such
a report for the world.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>You report!—No, no, no.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>No, no,—tale-bearers are just as
bad as the tale-makers.</p>
</sp>
<stage><pb n="11" facs="11"/>
<hi>Enter</hi> SERVANT.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>Servant.</speaker>
<p>Sir Benjamin Backbite, and Mr. Crabtree.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exit servant.</stage>
<stage><hi>Enter Sir</hi> BENJAMIN <hi>and</hi> CRABTREE.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>Lady Sneerwell, your most obedient humble
servant. Mrs. Candour, I believe you don't know my
nephew, Sir Benjamin Backbite; he has a very pretty
taste for poetry, and shall make a rebus or a cherard
with any one.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>Oh fie! uncle.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>In faith he will: did you ever hear the
lines he made at Lady Ponto's route, on Miss Frizzle's
feathers catching fire; and the rebuses—his first is
the name of a fish; the next, a great naval commander,
and—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>Uncle, now prythee.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>I wonder, Sir Benjamin you never
publish any thing.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>Why, to say the truth, 'tis very
vulgar to print—and as my little productions are
chiefly satyrs, and lampoons on particular persons, I
find they circulate better by giving copies in confidence
to the friends of the parties;—however, I have some
love elegies, which, when favoured by this Lady's
smiles <stage>(<hi>to Maria</hi>)</stage> I mean to give to the public.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>'Foregad, Madam, they'll immortalize
you <stage>(<hi>to Maria</hi>)</stage> you will be handed down to posterity,
like Petrarch's Laura, or Waller's Sacharissa.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>Yes, Madam, I think you'll like
them <stage>(<hi>to Maria</hi>)</stage> when you shall see them on a beautiful
quarto type, where a neat rivulet of text shall
murmur through a meadow of margin;—'foregad
they'll be the most elegant things of their kind.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="12" facs="12"/>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>But, odso, Ladies, did you hear the news?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>What—do you mean the report of—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>No, Madam, that's not it—Miss Nicely
going to be married to her footman.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>Impossible!</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>'Tis very true, indeed Madam, every
thing is fixed, and the wedding liveries bespoke.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>Yes, and they do say there were very
pressing reasons for it.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>I heard something of this before.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Oh! it cannot be; and I wonder
they'd report such a thing of so prudent a Lady.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>Oh! but Madam, that is the very
reason that it was believed at once, for she has always
been so very cautious and reserved, that every body
was sure there was some reason for it at bottom.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>It is true, there is a sort of puny,
sickly reputation, that would outlive the robuster character
of an hundred prudes.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>True, Madam, there are Valetudinarians
in reputation, as well as constitution, who being
conscious of their weak part, avoid the least breath
of air, and supply their want of stamina by care and
circumspection.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mr.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>I believe this may be some mistake;
you know, Sir Benjamin, very trifling circumstances
have often given rise to the most ingenious tales.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>Very true;—but odso, Ladies did you
hear of Miss Letitia Piper's losing her lover and her
character at Scarborough.—Sir Benjamin you remember
it.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>Oh, to be sure, the most whimsical
circumstance.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Pray let us hear it.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="13" facs="13"/>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>Why, one evening, at Lady Spadille's
assembly, the conversation happened to turn upon the
difficulty of breeding Nova-Scotia sheep in this country;
no, says a lady present, I have seen an instance
of it, for a cousin of mine, Miss Letitia Piper had one
that produced twins. What, what, says old Lady
Dundizzy (whom we all know is as deaf as a post) has
Miss Letitia Piper had twins.—This, you may easily
imagine, set the company in a loud laugh; and the
next morning it was every where reported, and believed
that Miss Letitia Piper had actually been brought
to bed of a fine boy and girl.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
<p>Ha, ha, ha, ha.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>'Tis true upon my honour.—Oh, Mr.
Surface, how do you do; I hear your uncle, Sir Oliver
is expected in town; sad news upon his arrival, to hear
how your brother has gone on.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>I hope no busy people have already prejudiced
his uncle against him—he may reform.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>True, he may; for my part, I never
thought him so utterly void of principle as people
say—and though he has lost all his friends, I am told
nobody is better spoken of amongst the Jews.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>'Foregad, if the Old Jewry was a ward,
Charles would be an Alderman, for he pays as many
annuities as the Irish Tontine; and when he is sick,
they have prayers for his recovery in all their Synagogues.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>Yet no man lives in greater splendor.
They tell me, when he entertains his friends, he can sit
down to dinner with a dozen of his own securities,
have a score of tradesmen waiting in the antichamber,
and an officer behind every guest's chair.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>This may be entertaining to you, gentlemen;
<pb n="14" facs="14"/>
—but you pay very little regard to the feelings
of a brother.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Maria.</speaker>
<p>Their malice is intolerable. <stage>(<hi>Aside.</hi>)</stage> Lady
Sneerwell, I must wish you a good morning; I'm not
very well.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exit Maria.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>She changes colour.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Do, Mrs. Candour, follow her.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>To be sure I will;—poor dear girl,
who knows what her situation may he?</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Mrs. Candour follows her.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>'Twas nothing, but that she could
not bear to hear Charles reflected on, notwithstanding
their difference.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>The young lady's penchant is obvious.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>Come, don't let this dishearten you—
follow her, and repeat some of your odes to her, and
I'll assist you.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>Mr. Surface, I did not come to hurt
you, but depend on't your brother is utterly undone.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>Oh! undone as ever man was—can't
raise a guinea.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>Every thing is sold, I am told, that
was moveable.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>Not a moveable left except some old
bottles, and some pictures, and they seem to be framed
in the wainscot, egad.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>I am sorry to hear also some bad stories
of him.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>Oh! He has done many mean things,
that's certain.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>But, however, he's your brother.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>Aye! as he's your brother—we'll tell
you more another opportunity.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="15" facs="15"/>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>Yes! as he's your brother—well tell
you more another opportunity.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exeunt Crabtree and sir Benjamin.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>'Tis very hard for them, indeed, to
leave a subject they have not quite run down.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>And I fancy their abuse was no more acceptable
to your ladyship, than to Maria.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>I doubt her affections are further engaged
than we imagine;—but the family are to be
here this afternoon, so you may as well dine where you
are, we shall have an opportunity of observing her
further;—in the mean time I'll go and and plot mischief,
and you shall study.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exeunt.</stage>
</div2>
<div2 type="scene">
<head>SCENE <stage>Sir PETER TEAZLE'S House.</stage></head>
<sp>
<speaker>Sir PETER.</speaker>
<p>WHEN an old batchelor marries a young wise,
what is he to expect?—'Tis now about six
months since my Lady Teazle made me the happiest of
men—and I have been the most miserable dog ever
since.—We tifted a little going to church, and fairly
quarrelled before the bells were done ringing. I was
more than once nearly choaked with gall during the
honey moon, and had lost every satisfaction in life, before
my friends had done wishing me joy.—And yet,
I chose with caution a girl bred wholly in the country,
who had never known luxury, beyond one silk gown,
or dissipation beyond the annual gala of a race ball.—
Yet, now she plays her part in all the extravagant fopperies
of the town, with as good a grace is if she had
never seen a bush, or a grass plot out of Grosvenor-Square.
—I am sneered at by all my acquaintance—
<pb n="16" facs="16"/>
paragraphed in the news-papers—she dissipates my fortune,
and contradicts all my humours.—And yet, the
worst of it is, I doubt I love her, or I should never
bear all this—but I am determined never to be weak
enough to let her know it—No! no! no!</p>
</sp>
<stage><hi>Enter</hi> ROWLEY.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>Sir Peter, your servant, how do you find
yourself to-day?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Very bad, Master Rowley, very bad indeed.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>I'm sorry to hear that—what has happened
to make you uneasy since yesterday?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>A pretty question truly to a married man.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>Sure my Lady is not the cause!</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Why has any one told you she was dead?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>Come, come, Sir Peter, notwithstanding
you sometimes dispute and disagree, I am sure you
love her.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Aye, Master Rowley; but the worst of
it is, that in all our disputes and quarrels, she is ever
in the wrong, and continues to thwart and vex me;—
I am myself the sweetest tempered man in the world,
and so I tell her an hundred times a day.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>Indeed, Sir Peter!</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Yes—and then there's Lady Sneerwell,
and the set she meets at her house, encourage her to
disobedience; and Maria, my ward, she too presumes
to have a will of her own, and refuses the man I propose
for her; designing, I suppose to bestow herself
and fortune upon that profligate his brother.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>You know, Sir Peter, I have often taken
the liberty to differ in opinion with you, in regard to
these two young men, for Charles, my life on't will 
<pb n="17" facs="17"/>
retrieve all one day or other.—Their worthy father,
my once honoured master, at his years, was full as wild
and extravagant as Charles now is; but at his death
he did not leave a more benevolent heart to lament
his loss.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>You are wrong, Mr. Rowley, you are
very wrong;—by their father's will, you know, I became
guardian to these young men, which gave me an
opportunity of knowing their different dispositions;
but their uncle's Eastern liberality soon took them out
of my power, by giving them an early independence.
—But for Charles, whatever good qualities he might
have inherited, they are long since squandered away
with the rest of his fortune;—Joseph, indeed, is a
pattern for the young men of the age—a youth of the
noblest sentiments, and acts up to the sentiments he
professes.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>Well, well; Sir Peter, I shan't oppose
your opinion at present, though I am sorry you are
prejudiced against Charles, as this may probably be
the most critical period of his life, for his uncle, Sir
Oliver, is arrived, and now in town.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Sir Peter.</speaker>
<p>What! my old friend, Sir Oliver, is he
arrived? I thought you had not expected him this
month.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>No more we did, Sir, but his passage has
been remarkably quick.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>I shall be heartily glad to see him—'tis
sixteen years since old Noll and I met—But does he still
enjoin us to keep his arrival a secret from his nephews?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>He does, Sir, and is determined, under
a feigned character, to make trial of their different
dispositions.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="18" facs="18"/>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Ah! there is no need of it, for Joseph,
I am sure is the man.—But hark'ye, Rowley, does Sir
Oliver know that I am married?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>He does, Sir, and intends shortly to wish
you joy.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>What, as we wish health to a friend in a
consumption.—But I must have him at my house—
do you conduct him, Rowley, I'll go and give orders
for his reception <stage>(<hi>going</hi>)</stage> We used to rail at matrimony
together—he has stood firm to his text.—But Rowley,
don't give him the least hint that my wife and I disagree,
for I would have him think (<hi>Heaven forgive me</hi>)
that we are a happy couple.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>Then you must be careful not to quarrel
whilst he is here.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>And so we must—but that will be impossible!
—Zounds, Rowley, when an old batchelor
marries a young wife, he deserves—aye, he deserves
—no—the crime carries the punishment along with it.</p>
</sp>
</div2>
<trailer><hi>End of the</hi> FIRST ACT.</trailer>
</div1>
<div1 n="2" type="act">
<head>ACT II.</head>
<div2 type="scene">
<head>SCENE <stage>Sir PETER TEAZLE'S House</stage></head>
<sp>
<speaker>Sir PETER.</speaker>
<p>LADY Teazle, Lady Teazle, I won't bear it.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>L. Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Very well, sir Peter, you may bear it
or not, just as you please; but I know I ought to have
my own way in every thing, and what's more, I will.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>What, madam! is there no respect due
to the authority of a husband?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>L. Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Why, don't I know that no woman of
fashion does as she is bid after her marriage.—Though
<pb n="19" facs="19"/>
I was bred in the country, I'm no stranger to that: if
you wanted me to be obedient, you should have adopted
me, and not married me—I'm sure you were old enough.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Aye, there it is—Oons, madam, what
right have you to run me into all this extravagance?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>L. Teazle.</speaker>
<p>I'm sure I am not more extravagant than
a woman of quality ought to be.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>'Slife, madam, I'll have no more sums
squandered away upon such unmeaning luxuries; you
have as many flowers in your dressing room, as would
turn the Pantheon into a green-house; or make a Féte
Champetre at a mas—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>L. Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Lord, sir Peter, am I to blame that
flowers don't blow in cold weather; you must blame
the climate, and not me—I'm sure, for my part, I wish
it was spring all the year round, and that roses grew
under our feet.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Zounds, madam, I should not wonder at
your extravagance, if you had been bred to it—Had
you any of these things before you married me?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>L. Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Lord, sir Peter, how can you be angry
at those little elegant expences?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Had you any of those little elegant expences
when you married me?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>L. Teazle.</speaker>
<p>For my part, I think you ought to be
pleased your wife should be thought a woman of taste.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Zounds. madam, you had no taste when
you married me.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>L. Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Very true, indeed; and after having
married you, I never should pretend to taste again.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Very well, very well, madam; you have
entirely forgot what your situation was when I first saw
you.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="20" facs="20"/>
<speaker>L. Teazle.</speaker>
<p>No, no, I have not; a very disagreeable
situation it was, or I'm sure I never should have married
you.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>You forget the humble state I took you
from—the daughter of a poor country 'squire—when
I came to your father's, I found you sitting at your
tambour, in a linen gown, a bunch of keys to your
side, and your hair combed smoothly over a roll.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>L. Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Yes, I remember very well;—my daily
occupations were to overlook the dairy, superintend
the poultry, make extracts from the family receipt
book, and combany aunt Deborah's lap dog.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Oh! I am glad to find you have so good
a recollection.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>L. Teazle.</speaker>
<p>My evening employments were to draw
patterns for ruffles, which I had not materials to make
up; play at Pope Joan with the curate; read a sermon
to my aunt Deborah, or perhaps be stuck up at an old
spinnet to trum my father to sleep after a fox-chace.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Then you was glad to take a ride out
behind the buttler, upon the old dock'd coach-horse.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>L. Teazle.</speaker>
<p>No, no, I deny the butler and the coach-horse.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>I say you did. This was your situation—
Now, madam, you must have your coach, viz-a-viz,
and three powdered coachmen to walk before your
chair; and in summer, two white cats to draw you to
Kensington-Gardens; and instead of your living in that
hole in the country, I have brought you home here,
made a woman of fortune of you, a woman of quality
—in short madam, I have made you my wife.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>L. Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Well, and there is but one thing more
you can now do to add to the obligation, and that is—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="21" facs="21"/>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>To make you my widow, I suppose.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>L. Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Hem!—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Very well, madam, very well; I am
much obliged to you for the hint.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>L. Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Why then will you force me to say
shocking things to you. But now we have finished
our morning conversation, I presume I may go to my
engagements at Lady Sneerwell's.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Lady Sneerwell!—a precious acquaintance
you have made with her too, and the set that frequent
her house.—Such a set, mercy on us!—Many a
wretch who has been drawn upon a hurdle, has done
less mischief than those barterers of forged lies, coiners
of scandal, and clippers of reputation.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>L. Teazle.</speaker>
<p>How can you be so severe; I'm sure
they are all people of fashion, and very tenacious of
reputation.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Yes, so tenacious of it, they'll not allow
it to any but themselves.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>L. Teazle.</speaker>
<p>I vow, sir Peter, when I say an ill-natured
thing I mean no harm by it, for I take it for
granted they'd do the same by me.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>They've made you as bad as any of them.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>L. Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Yes—I think I bear my part with a
tolerable grace—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Grace! indeed—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>L. Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Well, but sir Peter, you know you promised
to come.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Well, I shall just call in to look after
my own character.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>L. Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Then, upon my word, you must make
haste after me, or you'll be too late.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exit L. Teazle.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>I have got much by my intended expostulation
<pb n="22" facs="22"/>
—What a charming air she has!—what a neck
and how pleasingly she shews her contempt of my authority!—
Well, though I can't make her love me,
'tis some pleasure to teaze her a little, and I think she
never appears to such advantage, as when she is doing
every thing to vex and plague me.</p>
</sp>
</div2>
<div2 type="scene">
<head>SCENE <stage>Lady SNEERWELL'S House.</stage></head>
<stage><hi>Enter Lady</hi> SNEERWELL, CRABTREE, <hi>Sir</hi> BENJAMIN,
JOSEPH, <hi>Mrs.</hi> CANDOUR, <hi>and</hi> MARIA.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>Lady SNEERWELL.</speaker>
<p>NAY, positively we'll have it.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Aye, aye, the epigram, by all means.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>Oh! Plague on it, it's mere nonsense.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>Faith, Ladies, 'twas excellent for an
extempore.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>But Ladies, you should be acquainted
with the circumstances—You must know that one
day last week, as Lady Bab Curricle was taking the
dust in Hyde Park, in a sort of duodecimo phaeton,
she desires me to write some verses on her ponies; upon
which I took out my pocket book, and in a moment
produced the following:—</p>
<l>" Sure never were seen two such beautiful ponies,</l>
<l>" Other horses are clowns, and these macaronies;</l>
<l>" To give them this title I'm sure can't be wrong,</l>
<l>" Their legs are so slim, and their tails are so long.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>There, Ladies,—done in the crack of
a whip—and on horseback too!</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Oh! a very Phoebus mounted—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>I must have a copy.</p>
</sp>
<stage><pb n="23" facs="23"/>
Enter Lady <hi>TEAZLE.</hi></stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Lady Teazle, how do you do,—I
hope we shall see sir Peter.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>I believe he will wait on your Ladyship
presently.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Maria, my love, you look grave;
come, you shall sit down to picquet with Mr. Surface.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Maria.</speaker>
<p>I take very little pleasure in cards—but
I'll do as your ladyship pleases.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>I wonder he should sit down to cards
with Maria—I thought he would have taken an opportunity
of speaking to me before sir Peter came.</p>
<stage>[Aside.</stage>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>Well, now I'll forswear his society.</p>
<stage>[Aside.</stage>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>What's the matter, Mrs. Candour?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>Why, they are so censorious they
won't allow our friend, Miss Vermilion, to be handsome.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Oh, surely she's a pretty woman.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>I'm glad you think so.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>She has a charming fresh colour.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Yes, when it is fresh put on.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>Well, I'll swear it's natural, for I've
seen it come and go.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Yes, it comes at night, and goes again
in the morning.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>True, madam, it not only goes and
comes, but what's more, egad her maid can fetch and
carry it.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>Well,—and what do you think of
her sister.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>What, Mrs. Evergreen—'foregad, she's
six and fifty if she's a day.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="24" facs="24"/>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>Nay, I'll swear two or three and sixty
is the outside—I don't think she looks more.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>Oh, there's no judging by her looks,
unless we could see her face.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Well, if Mrs. Evergreen does take
some pains to repair the ravages of time, she certainly
effects it with great ingenuity, and surely that's better
than the careless manner in which the widow Oaker
chalks her wrinkles.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>Nay, now my Lady Sneerwell, you
are too severe upon the widow—Come, it is not that
she paints so ill, but when she has finished her face, she
joins it so badly to her neck, that she looks like a
mended statue, in which the connisseur may see at once
that the head is modern, though the trunk's antique.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>What do you think of Miss Simper?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>Why she has pretty teeth.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Yes, and upon that account never shuts
her mouth, but keeps it always a-jar, as it were thus
<stage>(<hi>shews her teeth.</hi>)</stage></p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
<p>Ha, ha, ha.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>And yet, I vow that's better than the
pains Mrs. Prim takes to conceal her losses in front;—
she draws her mouth till it resembles the apperture of
a poor box, and all her words appear to slide out edgeways
as it were, thus—</p>
<p>"How do you do madam?—Yes, madam."</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Ha, ha, ha, very well, Lady Teazle;
I vow you appear to be a little severe.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>In defence of a friend, you know, it is but
just.—But here comes Sir Peter to spoil our pleasantry.</p>
</sp>
<stage>Enter Sir <hi>PETER.</hi></stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Ladies your servant—mercy upon
<pb n="25" facs="25"/>
me!—the whole set—a character dead at every sentence.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>They won't allow good qualities to any
one—not even good nature to our friend Mrs. Pursey.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>What! the old fat dowager that was at
Mrs. Quadrille's last night.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>Her bulk is her misfortune; and
when she takes such pains to get rid of it, you ought
not to reflect on her.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>That's very true, indeed.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Yes.—I'm told she absolutely lives upon
acids and small whey, laces herself with pullies;—
often in the hottest day in summer, you shall see her on
a little squat poney, with her hair platted and turned
up like a drummer, and away she goes puffing round
the ring in a full trot.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Mercy on me! this is her own relation;
a person they dine with twice a week. <stage>(Aside.</stage></p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>I vow you shan't be so severe upon
the dowager; for let me tell you, great allowances are
to be made for a woman who strives to pass for a flirt
at six and thirty.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Though surely she's handsome still;
and for the weakness in her eyes, considering how much
she reads by candle-light, 'tis not to be wondered at.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>Very true; and for her manner, I
think it very graceful, considering she never had any
education; for her mother you know, was a Welch
milliner, and her father a sugar-baker at Bristol.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>Aye, ye are both of ye too good
natured.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>Well, I never will join in the ridicule
of a friend; so I tell my cousin Ogle, and ye all
know what pretensions she has to beauty.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="26" facs="26"/>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>She has the oddest countenance—a collection
of features from all corners of the globe.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>She has, indeed, an Irish front.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>Caledonian locks.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>Dutch nose.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>Austrian lips.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>The complexion of a Spaniard.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>And teeth a la Chinoise.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>In short, her face resembles a table
drote at Spa, where no two guests are of a nation.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>Or a Congress at the close of a general
war, where every member seems to have a different
interest, and the nose and chin are the only parties
likely to join issue.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>Ha, ha, ha.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Ha, ha,—Well, I vow you are a
couple of provoking toads.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>Well, I vow you shan't carry the
laugh so—let me tell you that, Mrs. Ogle.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Sir Peter.</speaker>
<p>Madam, madam, 'tis impossible to stop
those good gentlemens tongues; but when I tell you,
Mrs. Candour, that the lady they are speaking of is a
particular friend of mine, I hope you will be so good
as not to undertake her defence.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Well said, Sir Peter, but you are a
cruel creature, too phlegmatic yourself for a with and
too peevish to allow it to others.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>True wit, madam, is more nearly allied
to good nature than you are aware of.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>True, Sir Peter; I believe they are so
near a-kin that they can never be united.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>or rather, madam, suppose them to
be man and wife, one so seldom sees them together.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="27" facs="27"/>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>But Sir Peter is such an enemy to scandal
I believe he would have it put down by Parliament.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>'Foregad, Madam, if they considered the
sporting with reputations of as much consequence as
poaching on manors, and passed an act for the preservation
of fame, they would find many would thank
them for the bill.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Oh lud!—Sir Peter would deprive
us of our <hi>privileges.</hi></p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Yes, madam; and none should then have
the liberty to kill characters, and run down reputations,
but <hi>privileged</hi> old maids, and <hi>disappointed</hi> widows.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Go, you monster!</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>But surely you would not be so severe
on those who only report what they hear?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Yes, madam, I would have law for them
too; and wherever the drawer of the lie was not to be
found, the injured party should have a right to come
on any of the endorsers.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>Well, I verily believe there never was a
scandalous story without some foundation.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Nine out of ten are formed on some malicious
invention, or idle representation.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Come, Ladies, shall we sit down to
cards in the next room?</p>
</sp>
<stage>Enter a <hi>SERVANT,</hi> who whispers Sir <hi>PETER.</hi></stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>I'll come directly—I'll steal away unperceived. <stage>[Aside.</stage></p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Sir Peter, you're not leaving us.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>I beg pardon, Ladies, 'tis particular business,
and I must—but I leave my character behind
me.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exit Sir Peter.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>Well, certainly Lady Teazle, that
<pb n="28" facs="28"/>
Lord of your's is a strange being; I could tell you
some stories of him would make you laugh heartily,
if he was not your husband.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Oh, never mind that—This way.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[They walk up, and exeunt.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>You take no pleasure in this society.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Maria.</speaker>
<p>How can I? If to raise a malicious smile
at the misfortunes and infirmities of those who are unhappy,
be a proof of wit and humour, Heaven grant
me a double portion of dulness.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>And yet, they have no malice in their hearts.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Maria.</speaker>
<p>Then it is the more inexcusable, since nothing
but an ungovernable depravity of heart, could
tempt them to such a practice.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>And is it possible, Maria, that you can
thus feel for others, and yet be cruel to me alone?—
Is hope to be denied the tenderest passion?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Maria.</speaker>
<p>Why will you persist to persecute me on a
subject on which you have long since known my sentiments.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Oh, Maria, you would not be thus deaf to me,
but that Charles, that libertine, is still a favoured rival.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Maria.</speaker>
<p>Ungenerously urged, but whatever my sentiments
are, with regard to that unfortunate young
man, be assured I shall not consider myself more bound
to give him up, because his misfortunes have lost him
the regards—even of a brother—<stage>[Going out.</stage></p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Nay, Maria, you shall not leave me with
a frown; by all that's honest I swear— <stage>(<hi>Kneels, and sees</hi>
Lady Teazle <hi>entering behind</hi>)</stage> Ah! Lady Teazle, ah!
you shall not stir— <stage>(<hi>to Maria</hi>)</stage> I have the greatest regard
in the world for Lady Teazle, but if Sir Peter
was once to suspect—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="29" facs="29"/>
<speaker>Maria.</speaker>
<p>Lady Teazle!—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>What is all this, child? You are wanting
in the next room <stage>(<hi>Exit Maria</hi>)</stage>—What is the
meaning of all this?—What! did you take her for me?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Why, you must know—Maria—by some
means suspecting—the—great regard I entertain for
your Ladyship—was—was—threatening—if I did
not desist, to acquaint Sir Peter—and I—I—was just
reasoning with her—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>You seem to have adopted a very tender
method of reasoning—pray do you usually argue on
your knees?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Why, you know she's but a child, and I
thought a little bombast might be useful to keep her
silent.—But, my dear Lady Teazle, when will you
come and give me your opinion of my library?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Why, really I begin to think it not so
proper, and you know I admit you as a lover no farther
than fashion dictates.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Oh, no more;—a mere Platonic Cicisbeo,
that every Lady is entitled to.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>No further—and though Sir Peter's
treatment may make me uneasy, it shall never provoke
me—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>To the only revenge in your power.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle,</speaker>
<p>Go, you insinuating wretch—but we
shall be missed, let us join the company.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>I'll follow your Ladyship.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Don't stay long, for I promise you
Maria shan't come to hear any more of your reasoning</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exit Lady Teazle.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>A pretty situation I am in—by gaining
the wife I shall lose the heiress.—I at first intended to
<pb n="30" facs="30"/>
make her Ladyship only the instrument in my designs
on Maria, but—I don't know how it is—I am become
her serious admirer. I begin now to wish I had
not made a point of gaining so very good a character,
for it has brought me into so many confounded rogueries,
that I fear I shall be exposed at last.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exit Joseph.</stage>
</div2>
<div2 type="scene">
<head>SCENE <stage>Sir PETER TEAZLE'S House.</stage></head>
<stage>Enter Sir <hi>OLIVER</hi> and <hi>ROWLEY.</hi></stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Ha, ha, and so my old friend is married
at last, eh Rowley,—and to a young wife out of
the country, ha, ha, ha! That he should buff to old
batchelors so long, and sink into a husband at last.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>But let me beg of you, sir, not to rally
him upon the subject, for he cannot bear it, though
he has been married these seven months.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Then he has been just half a year on the
stool of repentance. Poor Sir Peter!—But you say
he has entirely given up Charles—never sees him, eh.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>His prejudice against him is astonishing,
and I believe is greatly aggravated by a suspicion of a
connexion between Charles and Lady Teazle, and
such a report I know has been circulated and kept up,
by means of Lady Sneerwell, and a scandalous party
who associate at her house; where, as I am convinced,
if there is any partiality in the case, that Joseph is the
favourite.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Ay, ay, I know there are a set of mischievous
prating gossips, both male and female, who
murder characters to kill him, and rob a young fellow
of his good name, before he has sense enough to know
<pb n="31" facs="31"/>
the value of it.—but I am not to be prejudiced
against my nephew by any such, I promise you.
—No, no, if Charles has done nothing false or
mean, I shall compound for his extravagance.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>I rejoice, sir, to hear you say so, and am
happy to find the son of my old master has one friend
left however.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>What! shall I forget, Mr. Rowley,
when I was at his years myself;—egad, neither my
brother or I were very prudent youths, and yet, I believe
you have not seen many better men than your old
master was.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>'Tis that reflection I build my hopes on—
and my life on't! Charles will prove deserving of your
kindness—But here comes Sir Peter.</p>
</sp>
<stage>Enter Sir <hi>PETER.</hi></stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Where is he? where is Sir Oliver?—Ah,
my dear friend I rejoice to see you!—You are welcome,
indeed you are welcome,—you are welcome to England
a thousand,—and a thousand times!—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Thank you, thank, Sir Peter—and
am glad to find you so well, believe me.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Ah, Sir Oliver!—It's sixteen years since
last we saw each other—many a bout we have had
together in our time!</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Aye! I have had my share—But
what, I find you are married—hey old boy!—Well,
well, it can't be helped, and so I wish you joy with
all my heart.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Thank you, thank you—yes Sir Oliver,
I have entered into that happy state—but we won't
talk of that now.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>That's true, Sir Peter, old friends
<pb n="32" facs="32"/>
should not begin upon grievances at their first meeting,
no, no, no.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p><stage>(<hi>Aside to Sir Oliver.</hi>)</stage> Have a care, Sir,
—don't touch upon that subject.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Well,—so one of my nephews, I find,
is a wild young rogue.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Oh, my dear friend, I grieve at your
disappointment there—Charles is, indeed, a sad libertine,—
but no matter, Joseph will make you ample amends—
every body speaks well of him.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>I am very sorry to hear it; he has too
good a character to be an honest fellow—every body
speaks well of him!—'pshaw—then he has bowed
as low to knaves and fools, as to the honest dignity of
genius and virtue.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>What the plague! are you angry with
Joseph for not making enemies?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Why not, if he has merit enough to
deserve them.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Well, well, see him, and you'll be convinced
how worthy he is—He's a pattern for all the
young men of the age—He's a man of the noblest
sentiments.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Oh! plague of his sentiments—If he
salutes me with a scrap of morality in his mouth I shall
be sick directly—but don't however mistake me, Sir
Peter, I don't mean to defend Charles's errors; but
before I form my judgment of either of them, I intend
to make a trial of their hearts, and my friend
Rowley and I have planned something for that purpose.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>My life on Joseph's honour.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Well, well, give us a bottle of good
<pb n="33" facs="33"/>
wine, and we'll drink your Lady's health, and tell
you all our schemes.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Alons—done.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>And don't, Sir Peter, be too severe
against your old friend's son;—Odds my life, I am
not sorry he has run a little out of the course—for
my part, I hate to see prudence clinging to the green
suckers of youth; 'tis like ivy round the saplin, and
spoils the growth of the tree.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exeunt omnes.</stage>
</div2>
<trailer>End of the <hi>SECOND ACT.</hi></trailer>
</div1>
<div1 n="3" type="act">
<head>ACT III.</head>
<div2 type="scene">
<head>SCENE <stage>Sir PETER'S House.</stage></head>
<stage>Enter Sir <hi>PETER,</hi> Sir <hi>OLIVER,</hi> and <hi>ROWLEY.</hi></stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> PETER.</speaker>
<p>WELL, well, we'll see this man first, and then
have our wine afterwards.—But Rowley, I
don't see the jest of your scheme.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>Why, Sir, this Mr. Stanley was a near relation
of their mother's, and formerly an eminent merchant
in Dublin—he failed in trade, and is greatly
reduced; he has applied by letter to Mr. Surface and
Charles for assistance—from the former of whom he
has received nothing but fair promises; while Charles
in the midst of his own distresses, is at present endeavouring
to raise a sum of money, part of which I know
he intends for the use of Mr. Stanley.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Aye—he's my brother's son.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>Now, Sir, we propose, that Sir Oliver shall
visit them both, in the character of Mr. Stanley, as I
<pb n="34" facs="34"/>
have informed them he has obtained leave of his creditors
to wait on his friends in person—and in the
younger, believe me, you'll find one, who, in the midst
of dissipation and extravagance, has still, as our immortal
Bard expresses it. <hi>A tear for pity, and a hand
open as day for melting charity.</hi></p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>What signifies his open hand and purse,
if he has nothing to give? But where is this person
you were speaking of?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>Below, Sir, waiting your commands—you
must know, Sir Oliver, this is a friendly Jew; one who,
to do him justice, has done every thing in his power
to assist Charles—who waits— <stage>(<hi>Enter a servant</hi>)</stage> desire
Mr. Moses to walk up.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exit servant.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>But how are you sure he'll speak truth?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>Why Sir, I have persuaded him, there's
no prospect of his being paid several sums of money he
has advanced for Charles, but through the bounty of
Sir Oliver, who he knows is in town; therefore you
may depend on his being faithful to his interest—Oh!
here comes the honest Israelite—</p>
<stage><hi>Enter</hi> MOSES.</stage>
<p>Sir Oliver, this is Mr. Moses.—Mr. Moses, this is
Sir Oliver.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>I understand you have lately had great
dealings with my nephew Charles.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Moses.</speaker>
<p>Yes, Sir Oliver, I have done all I could for
him—but he was ruined before he came to me for assistance.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>That was unlucky truly, for you had
no opportunity of shewing your talent.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Moses.</speaker>
<p>None at all; I had not the pleasure of knowing
his distresses, 'till he was some thousands worse
than nothing.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="35" facs="35"/>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Unfortunate indeed! But I suppose you
have done all in your power for him.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Moses.</speaker>
<p>Yes, he knows that—This very evening I
was to have brought him a gentleman from the city,
who does not know him, and will advance him some
monies.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>What! a person that Charles has never
borrowed money of before, lend him any in his present
circumstances.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Moses.</speaker>
<p>Yes—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>What is the gentleman's name?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Moses.</speaker>
<p>Mr. Premium, of Crutched Friars, formerly
a broker.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Does he know Mr. Premium?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Moses.</speaker>
<p>Not at all.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>A thought strikes me,—suppose, Sir
Oliver you was to visit him in that character; 'twill be
much better than the romantic one of an old relation;
you will then have an opportunity of seeing Charles in
all his glory.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Egad, I like that idea better than the
other, and then I may visit Joseph afterwards as old
Stanley.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>Gentlemen, this is taking Charles rather
unawares; but Moses, you understand Sir Oliver, and
I dare say will be faithful.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Moses.</speaker>
<p>You may depend upon me.—This is very
near the time I was to have gone.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>I'll accompany you as soon as you please,
Moses, but hold—I had forgot one thing—how the
plague shall I be able to pass for a Jew?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Moses.</speaker>
<p>There is no need—the principal is a Christian.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Is he? I am very sorry for it—but
<pb n="36" facs="36"/>
then again, am I not too smartly dressed to look like
a money-lender?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Not at all—it would not be out of character
if you went in your own chariot, would it Moses?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Moses.</speaker>
<p>Not in the least.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Well, but how must I talk? There's
certainly some cant of usury, or mode of treating;
that I ought to know.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>As I take it Sir Oliver, the great point
is to be exorbitant in your demands.—Eh! Moses?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Moses.</speaker>
<p>Yes, dat is very great point.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>I'll answer for't I'll not be wanting in
that, eight or ten <hi>per cent.</hi> on the loan at least.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Moses.</speaker>
<p>Oh! if you ask him no more as dat, you'll
be ciscovered immediately.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Hey, what the plague—how much then?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Moses.</speaker>
<p>that depends upon the circumstances—if
he appears not very anxious for the supply, you should
require only forty or fifty <hi>per cent.</hi> but if you find him
in great distress, and he wants money very bad—you
must ask double.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Upon my word, Sir Oliver,—Mr. Premium
I mean—it's a very pretty trade you're learning.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Truly I think so, and not unprofitable.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Moses.</speaker>
<p>Then you know you have not the money
yourself, but are forced to borrow it of a friend.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Oh! I borrow it for him of a friend—do I?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Moses.</speaker>
<p>Yes, and your friend's an unconscionable
dog—but you can't help dat.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Oh! my friend's an unconscionable
dog—is he?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Moses.</speaker>
<p>And then he himself has not the monies by
him, but is forced to sell stock at a great loss.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="37" facs="37"/>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>He's forced to sell stock at a great loss,
—well, really, that's very kind of him.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>But hark'ye, Moses, if Sir Oliver was
to rail a little at the annuity bill, don't you think it
would have a good effect?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Moses.</speaker>
<p>Very much.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>And lament that a young man must now
come to years of discretion, before he has it in his
power to ruin himself.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Moses.</speaker>
<p>Aye! a great pity.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Yes, and abuse the public for allowing
merit to a bill, whose only object was to rescue youth
and inexperience from the rapacious gripe of usury,
and to give the young heir an opportunity of enjoying
his fortune, without being ruined by coming into
possession.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>So—so,—Moses shall give me further
instructions as we go together.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>You'll scarce have time to learn your
trade, for Charles lives but hard by.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Oh! never fear—my tutor appears so
able, that tho Charles lived in the next street, it must
be my own fault if I am not a compleat rogue before
I have turned the corner.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exeunt Sir Oliver and
Moses.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>So Rowley, you would have been partial,
and given Charles notice of our plot.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>No indeed, Sir Peter.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Well, I see Maria coming, I want to
have some talk with her.</p>
<stage>[Exit Rowley.</stage>
<stage><hi>Enter</hi> MARIA.</stage>
<p>So Maria, what is Mr. Surface come home with you?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Maria.</speaker>
<p>No, Sir, he was engaged.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="38" facs="38"/>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Maria, I wish you were more sensible to
his excellent qualities.—does not every time you are
in his company convince you of the merit of that
amiable young man?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Maria.</speaker>
<p>You know, Sir Peter, I have often told
you, that of all the men who have paid me a particular
attention, there is not one I would not sooner prefer
than Mr. Surface.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Aye, aye, this blindness to his merit, proceeds
from your attachment to that profligate brother
of his.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Maria.</speaker>
<p>This is unkind, you know, at your request,
I have forborn to see or correspond with him, as I have
long been convinced he is unworthy my regard; but
while my reason condemns his vices, my heart suggests
some pity for his misfortunes.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Ah! you had best resolve to think of him
no more, but give your heart and hand to a worthier
object.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Maria.</speaker>
<p>Never to his brother.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Have a care, Maria, I have not yet made
you know what the authority of a guardian is, don't
force me to exert it.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Maria.</speaker>
<p>I know, that for a short time, I am to obey
you as my father,—but must cease to think you so,
when you would compell me to be miserable.</p>
<stage>[Exit in tears.</stage>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Sure never man was plagued as I am; I
had not been married above three weeks, before her
father, a hale, hearty man, died,—on purpose I believe
to plague me with the care of his daughter: but here
comes my help-mate, she seems in mighty good humour;
I wish I could teaze her into loving me a little.</p>
</sp>
<stage><pb n="39" facs="39"/>
<hi>Enter</hi> LADY TEAZLE.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>What's the matter, Sir Peter? What
have you done to Maria? It is not fair to quarrel and
I not by.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Ah, Lady Teazle, it is in your power
to put me into good humour at any time.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Is it? I am glad of it—for I want you
to be in a monstrous good humour now; come do be
good humoured, and let me have two hundred pounds.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>What the plague! can't I be in a good
humour without paying for it,—but look always thus,
and you shall want for nothing. <stage>(<hi>Pulls out a pocket-book.</hi>)</stage>
There, there's two hundred pounds for you,
<stage>(<hi>going to kiss.</hi>)</stage> now seal me a bond for the payment.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>No, my note of hand will do as well.</p>
<stage>[Giving her hand.</stage>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Well, well, I must be satisfied with
that—you shan't much longer reproach me for not
having made you a proper settlement—I intend shortly
to surprize you.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Do you? You can't think, Sir Peter,
how good humour becomes you; now you look just
as you did before I married you.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Do I indeed?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Don't you remember when you used to
walk with me under the elms, and tell me stories of
what a gallant you were in your youth, and asked me
if I could like an old fellow, who could deny me nothing.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Aye, and you were so attentive and
obliging to me then.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Aye, to be sure I was, and used to take
your part against all my acquaintance, and when my
<pb n="40" facs="40"/>
cousin Sophy used to laugh at me, for thinking of
marrying a man old enough to be my father, and call
you an ugly, stiff, formal old batchelor, I contradicted
her, and said I did not think you so ugly by any means,
and that I dar'd say, you would make a good sort of a
husband.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>That was very kind of you—Well, and
you were not mistaken, you have found it so, have
not you?—But shall we always live thus happy?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>With all my heart;—I'm—I don't
care how soon we leave off quarrelling—provided you
will own you are tired first.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>With all my heart.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Then we shall be as happy as the day
is long, and never, never,—never quarrel more.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Never—never—never—and let our future
contest be, who shall be most obliging.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Aye!—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>But, my dear Lady Teazle—my love
—indeed you must keep a strict watch over your temper
—for you know, my dear, that in all our disputes
and quarrels you always begin first.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>No, no, Sir Peter, my dear, 'tis always
you that begins.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>No, no,—no such thing.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Have a care, this it not the way to live
happy if your fly out thus.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>No, no,—'tis you.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>No—'tis you.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Zounds!—I say 'tis you.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Lord! I never saw such a man in my
life—just what my cousin Sophy told me.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Your cousin Sophy is a forward, saucy,
impertinent minx.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="41" facs="41"/>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>You are a very great bear, I am sure,
to abuse my relations.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>But I am well enough served for marrying
you—a pert, forward, rural coquette, who had refused
half the honest 'squires in the country.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>I am sure I was a great fool for marrying
you—a stiff, crop, dangling old batchelor, who was
unmarried at fifty, because nobody would have him.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>You was very glad to have me—you
never had such an offer before.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Oh, yes I had—there was Sir Tivey
Terrier, who every body said would be a better match;
for his estate was full as good as yours, and—he has
broke his neck since we were married.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Very—very well, madam,—you're an
ungrateful woman; and may plagues light on me, if
I ever try to be friends with you again—You shall have
a separate maintenance.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>By all means a separate maintenance.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Very well, madam,—Oh, very well.
Aye, madam, and I believe the stories of you
and Charles—of you and Charles, madam,—were
not without foundation.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Take care, Sir Peter; take care what
you say, for I won't be suspected without a cause, I
promise you.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>A divorce!—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Aye, a divorce.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Aye, zounds! I'll make an example of
myself for the benefit of all old batchelors.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Well, Sir Peter, I see you are going to
be in a passion, so I'll leave you, and when you come
properly to your temper, we shall be the happiest
<pb n="42" facs="42"/>
couple in the world; and never—never—quarrel
more. Ha, ha, ha.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exit.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>What the devil! can't I make her angry
neither.—I'll after her—zounds—she must not presume
to keep her temper.—No, no,—she may break my
heart—but damn it—I'm determined she shan't keep
her temper.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exit.</stage>
</div2>
<div2 type="scene">
<head>SCENE <stage>CHARLES'S House.</stage></head>
<stage><hi>Enter</hi> TRIP, <hi>Sir</hi> OLIVER, <hi>and</hi> MOSES.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>Trip.</speaker>
<p>This way, gentlemen, this way.—Moses,
what's the gentleman's name?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Mr. Moses, what's my name?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Moses.</speaker>
<p>Mr. Premium—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Trip.</speaker>
<p>Oh, Mr. Premium,—very well.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exit.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>To judge by the servant, one would
not imagine the master was ruined.—Sure this was my
brother's house.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Moses.</speaker>
<p>Yes, Sir,—Mr. Charles bought it of Mr.
Joseph, with furniture, pictures, &amp;c. just as the old
gentleman left it—Sir Peter thought it a great piece
of extravagance in him.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>In my mind, the others oeconomy in
selling it to him, was more reprehensible by half.</p>
</sp>
<stage><hi>Enter</hi> TRIP.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>Trip.</speaker>
<p>Gentlemen, my master is very sorry he has
company at present, and cannot see you.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>If he knew who it is that wanted to see
him, perhaps he would not have sent such a message.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Trip.</speaker>
<p>Oh! yes, I told him who it was—I did not
forget my little Premium, no, no.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Very well, Sir; and pray what may
your name be?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="43" facs="43"/>
<speaker>Trip.</speaker>
<p>Trip, Sir, Trip, at your service.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Very well, Mr. Trip,—you have a pleasant
sort of a place here, I guess.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Trip.</speaker>
<p>Pretty well—There are four of us, who pass
our time agreeably enough—Our wages indeed, are but
small, and sometimes a little in arrear—We have but
fifty guineas a year, and find our own bags and bouquets.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Bags and bouquets!—halters and bastinadoes!</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Trip.</speaker>
<p>Oh, Moses, hark'ye—did you get that little
bill discounted for me?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Wants to raise money too!—Mercy on
me!—He has distresses, I warrant, like a Lord, and
affects creditors and duns.</p>
<stage>[Aside.</stage>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Moses.</speaker>
<p>'Twas not to be done, indeed, Mr. Trip.</p>
<stage>[Gives the note.</stage>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Trip.</speaker>
<p>No! why I thought when my friend Brush
had set his mark on it, it was as good as cash.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Moses.</speaker>
<p>No, indeed, it would not do.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Trip.</speaker>
<p>Perhaps you could get it done by way of
annuity.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>An annuity!—A footman raise money
by annuity!—Well said luxury, egad.</p>
<stage>[Aside.</stage>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Moses.</speaker>
<p>Well, but you must insure your place.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Trip.</speaker>
<p>Oh! I'll insure my life if you please.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>That's more than I would your neck.</p>
<stage>[Aside.</stage>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Trip.</speaker>
<p>Well, but I should like to have it done before
this damned registry takes place, one would not
wish to have one's name made public.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Moses.</speaker>
<p>No, certainly—but there is nothing you
could deposit?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Trip.</speaker>
<p>Why, there's none of my master's cloaths will
<pb n="44" facs="44"/>
fall very soon, I believe; but I can give a mortgage on
some of his winter suits, with equity of redemption
before Christmas—or a <hi>post obit</hi> on his blue and silver.
Now these, with a few pair of point ruffles, by way of
security <stage>(<hi>bell rings</hi>)</stage> coming, coming, Gentlemen,
if you'll walk this way, perhaps I may introduce you
now.—Moses, don't forget the annuity—I'll insure my
place, my little fellow.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>If the man is the shadow of the master,
this is the temple of dissipation indeed.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exeunt Trip, Sir Oliver, and Moses.</stage>
<stage><hi>CHARLES, CARELESS,</hi> Sir <hi>TOBY,</hi> and Gentlemen, discovered
drinking.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Ha, ha, ha,—'Fore Heaven you are in
the right—the degeneracy of the age is astonishing,
there are many of our acquaintance who are men of
wit, genius, and spirit, but then they won't drink.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Carless.</speaker>
<p>True, Charles; they sink into the more
substantial luxuries of the table, and quite neglect the
bottle.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Right—besides society suffers by it; for,
instead of the mirth and humour that used to mantle
over a bottle of Burgundy, their conversation is become
as insipid as the Spa water they drink, which has all the
pertness of Champaigne, without its spirit or flavour.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Toby.</speaker>
<p>But what will you say to those who prefer
play to the bottle?—There's Harry, Dick and
Careless himself, who are under a hazard regimen.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>'Psha! no such thing—What would you
train a horse for the course by keeping him from corn?
—Let me throw upon a bottle of Burgundy and I
never lose, at least I never feel my loss, and that's the
same thing.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="45" facs="45"/>
<speaker>1st. Gent.</speaker>
<p>True; besides, 'tis wine that determines
if a man be really in love.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>So it is—Fill up a dozen bumpers to a
dozen beauties, and she that floats at the top, is the
girl that has bewitched you.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Careless.</speaker>
<p>But come, Charles, you have not given
us your real favourite,</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Faith I have withheld her only in compassion
to you, for if I give her, you must toast a round
of her peers, which is impossible <stage>(<hi>sighs</hi>)</stage> on earth.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Careless.</speaker>
<p>We'll toast some heathen deity, or celestial
goddess to match her.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Why then bumpers—bumpers all round
—here's Maria—Maria—Sighs.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>1st. Gent.</speaker>
<p>Maria—'Pshaw—give us her sir-name.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>'Pshaw—hang her sir-name, that's too
formal to be registered on love's kalender.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>1st. Gent.</speaker>
<p>Maria, then—here's Maria.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Toby.</speaker>
<p>Maria—come, here's Maria.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Come, Sir Toby, have a care; you must
give a beauty superlative.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Toby.</speaker>
<p>Then I'll give you—Here's—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Careless.</speaker>
<p>Nay, never hesitate—But Sir Toby has
got a song, that will excuse him.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
<p>The song—The song.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<lg>
<head>SONG.</head>
<lg>
<l>Here's to the maiden of blushing fifteen,</l>
<l>Now to the widow of fifty;</l>
<l>Here's to the flaunting extravagant quean,</l>
<l>And then to the house-wife that's thrifty.</l>
<l>Let the toast pass, drink to the lass,</l>
<l>I warrant she'll find an excuse for the glass.</l>
</lg>
<lg>
<pb n="46" facs="46"/>
<l>Here's to the charmer whose dimples we prize,</l>
<l>Now to the damsel with none sir;</l>
<l>Here's to the maid with her pair of blue eyes,</l>
<l>And now to the nymph with but one sir.</l>
<l>Let the toast pass, &amp;c.</l>
</lg>
<lg>
<l>Here's to the maid with her bosom of snow,</l>
<l>Now to her that's as brown as a berry;</l>
<l>Here's to the wife with her face full of woe,</l>
<l>And now to the damsel that's merry.</l>
<l>Let the toast pass, &amp;c.</l>
</lg>
<lg>
<l>For let them be clumsy, or let them be slim,</l>
<l>Young or ancient I care not a feather;</l>
<l>So fill us a bumper quite up to the brim,</l>
<l>And e'en let us toast them together.</l>
<l>Let the toast pass, &amp;c.</l>
</lg>
</lg>
</sp>
<stage><hi>TRIP</hi> enters and whispers <hi>CHARLES.</hi></stage>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Gentlemen, I must beg your pardon,
<stage>(<hi>rising</hi>)</stage> I must leave you upon business—Careless take
the chair.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Careless.</speaker>
<p>What! this is some wench—but we won't
lose you for her.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>No, upon my honour—It is only a Jew
and a broker that are come by appointment.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Careless.</speaker>
<p>A Jew and a broker! we'll have 'em in.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Then desire Mr. Moses to walk in.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Trip.</speaker>
<p>And little Premium too, Sir,</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Careless.</speaker>
<p>Aye, Moses and Premium. <stage>(<hi>Exit Trip.</hi>)</stage>
Charles we'll give the rascals some generous Burgundy.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>No, hang it—wine but draws forth the
natural qualities of a man's heart, and to make them
drink, would only be to whet their knavery.</p>
<stage><pb n="47" facs="47"/>
<hi>Enter Sir</hi> OLIVER <hi>and</hi> MOSES.</stage>
<p>Walk in, Gentlemen, walk in; Trip give chairs; sit
down Mr. Premium, sit down Moses. Glasses Trip;
come, Moses, I'll give you a sentiment. "<hi>Here's
success to usury.</hi>" Moses, fill the gentleman a bumper.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Moses.</speaker>
<p>"Here's success to usury."</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Careless.</speaker>
<p>True, Charles; usury is industry, and
deserves to succeed.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Then here's "All the success it deserves."</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Careless.</speaker>
<p>Oh, dam'me, sir, that won't do; you demur
to the toast, and shall drink it in a pint bumber at
least.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Moses.</speaker>
<p>Oh, sir, consider Mr. Premium is a gentleman.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Carless.</speaker>
<p>And therefore loves good wine, and I'll see
justice done to the bottle.—Fill Moses, a quart.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Pray, consider gentlemen, Mr. Premium
is a stranger.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>I wish I was out of their company.</p>
<stage>[Aside.</stage>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Careless.</speaker>
<p>Come along, my boys, if they won't drink
with us we'll not stay with them; the dice are in the
next room—You'll settle your business, Charles, and
come to us.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Aye, aye,—but Careless, you must be
ready, perhaps I may have occasion for you.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Careless.</speaker>
<p>Aye, aye, bill, bond, or annuity, 'tis all
the same to me.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exit with the rest.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>Moses.</speaker>
<p>Mr. Premium is a gentleman of the strictect
honour and secrecy, and always performs what he undertakes.—
Mr. Premium, this is— <stage>(<hi>formally.</hi>)</stage></p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>'Pshaw! hold your tongue—my friend
Moses, sir, is a very honest fellow, but a little slow at
expression—I shall cut the matter very short;—
I'm an extravagant young fellow that wants to borrow
<pb n="48" facs="48"/>
money; and you, as I take it are a prudent old fellow
who has got money to lend—I am such a fool as to
give fifty per cent. rather than go without it; and you
I suppose are rogue enough to take an hundred if you
can get it. And now we understand one another, and
may proceed to business without further ceremony.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Exceeding frank, upon my word; I see
you are not a man of compliments.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>No, Sir.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Sir, I like you the better for it—However
you are mistaken in one thing; I have no money
to lend, but I believe I could procure you some from
a friend; but then he's a damn'd unconscionable dog;
is he not Moses?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Moses.</speaker>
<p>Yes, but you can't help that.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>And then he has not the money by him▪
but must sell stock at a great loss, must not he Moses?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Moses.</speaker>
<p>Yes, indeed—you know I always speak
the truth, and scorn to tell a lye.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Aye, those who speak truth usually do—
And Sir, I must pay the difference, I suppose—Why
look'ye Mr. Premium, I know that money is not to be
had without paying for it.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Well—but what security could you
give—you have not any land I suppose.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Not a mole-hill, nor a twig but what
grows in bow-pots out at the windows.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Nor any stock I presume.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>None but live stock, and they are only a
few pointers and ponies.—But pray, Sir, are you acquainted
with any of my connections?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>To say the truth I am.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Then you must have heard that I had a
<pb n="49" facs="49"/>
rich old uncle in India, Sir Oliver Surface, from whom
I have the greatest expectations.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>That you have a wealthy uncle I have
heard; but how your expectations will turn out, is
more I believe, than you can tell.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Oh yes, I'm told I am a monstrous favourite,
and that he intends leaving me every thing.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Indeed! this is the first I have heard of it.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Yes, yes, he intends making me his heir
—Does he not, Moses?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Moses.</speaker>
<p>Oh yes, I'll take my oath of that.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Egad, they'll persuade me presently
that I am in Bengal.</p>
<stage>(Aside.)</stage>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Now, what I propose, Mr. Premium, is
to give you a <hi>post obiit</hi> on my uncle's life. Though indeed
my uncle Noll has been very kind to me, and
upon my soul I shall be sincerely sorry to hear any
thing has happened to him.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Not more than I should I assure you.
But the bond you mention happens to be the worst security
you could offer me, for I might live to be an
hundred, and never recover the principal.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Oh, yes you would, for the moment he
dies, you come upon me for the money.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Then I believe I would be the most unwelcome
dun you ever had in your life.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>What, you are afraid, my little Premium,
that my uncle is too good a life.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>No, indeed I am not; though I have
heard he's as hale, and as hearty, as any man of his
years in Christendom.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Oh, there you are misinformed. No,—no,
poor uncle Oliver? he breaks a pace. The climate, sir,
<pb n="50" facs="50"/>
has hurt his constitution, and I'm told he's so much altered
of late, that his nearest relations don't know him.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>No? ha, ha, ha; so much altered of
late, that his relations would not know him. Ha,
ha, ha, that's droll, egad.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>What you are pleased to hear he's on the
decline, my little Premium.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>No, I am not;—no, no, no.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Yes, you are, for it mends your chance.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>But I am told Sir Oliver is coming
over,—nay, some say he is actually arrived.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Oh, there you are misinformed again—
No—no such thing—he is this moment in Bengal,
What! I must certainly know better than you.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Very true, as you say, you must know
better than I; though I have it from very good authority—
Have I not, Moses?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Moses.</speaker>
<p>Most undoubtedly.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>But, Sir, as I understand you want a few
hundreds immediately, is there nothing that you
would dispose of?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>How do you mean?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>For instance, now; I have heard your father
left behind him a great quantity of massy old plate.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Yes, but that is gone long ago—Moses
can inform you how, better than I can.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Good lack! all the family race cups,
and corporation bowls gone! <stage>(<hi>Aside</hi>)</stage> It was also supposed,
that his library was one of the most valuable
and compleat.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Much too large and valuable for a private
gentleman; for my part, I was always of a communicative
disposition, and thought it a pity to keep so
much knowledge to myself.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="51" facs="51"/>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Mercy on me! knowledge that has run
in the family. like a heir-loom. <stage>(<hi>Aside</hi>)</stage> And pray
how may they have been disposed of?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Oh you must ask the auctioneer that—
I don't believe even Moses can direct you there.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Moses.</speaker>
<p>No—I never meddle with books.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>The profligate! <stage>(<hi>Aside</hi>)</stage> And is there
nothing you can dispose of?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Nothing—unless you have a taste for
old family pictures. I have a whole room full of ancestors
above stairs.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Why sure you would not sell your relations!</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Every soul of them to the best bidder.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Not your great uncles and aunts.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Aye, and my grandfathers and grandmothers.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>I'll never forgive him this. <stage>(<hi>Aside</hi>)</stage>
Why,—what—Do you take me for Shylock
in the play, to raise money from me on your own flesh
and blood.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Nay, don't be in a passion, my little Premium;
what is it to you, if you have your money's
worth.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>That's very true as you say—Well,
well, I believe I can dispose of the family canvass. I'll
never forgive him this.</p>
<stage>[Aside.</stage>
</sp>
<stage><hi>Enter</hi> CARELESS.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>Careless.</speaker>
<p>Come, Charles, what the Devil are you
doing so long with the broker—we are waiting for you.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Oh! Careless, you are just come in time,
we are to have a sale above stairs.—I am going to sell
all my ancestors to little Premium.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="52" facs="52"/>
<speaker>Careless.</speaker>
<p>Burn your ancestors.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>No, no, he may do that afterwards if he
will. But Careless, you shall be auctioneer.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Careless.</speaker>
<p>With all my heart, I handle a hammer as
well as a dice box—a-going—a-going.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Bravo!—And Moses you shall be appraiser,
if we want one.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Moses.</speaker>
<p>Yes, I'll be the appraiser.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Oh the profligate!</p>
<stage>[Aside.</stage>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>But what's the matter, my little Premium?
You don't seem to relish this business.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p><stage>(<hi>Affecting to laugh</hi>)</stage> Oh, yes I do, vastly;
ha, ha, ha, I—Oh the prodigal!</p>
<stage>[Aside.</stage>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Very true, for when a man wants money,
who the devil can he make free with if he can't with
his own relations.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exit.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p><stage>(<hi>Following</hi>)</stage> I'll never forgive him.</p>
</sp>
</div2>
<trailer>End of the <hi>THIRD ACT.</hi></trailer>
</div1>
<div1 n="4" type="act">
<head>ACT IV.</head>
<div2 type="scene">
<stage><hi>Enter</hi> CHARLES, SIR OLIVER, CARELESS, <hi>and</hi> MOSES.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>CHARLES.</speaker>
<p>WALK in gentlemen, walk in; here they are—
the family of the Surfaces up to the Conquest.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>And in my opinion, a good collection.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Aye, there they are, done in the true
spirit and style of portrait painting, and not like your
modern Raphael's, who will make your picture independent
of yourself;—no, the great merit of these are,
the inveterate likeness they bear to the originals. All
stiff and awkward as they were, and like nothing in
human nature besides.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="53" facs="53"/>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Oh, we shall never see such figures of
men again.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>I hope not—You see, Mr. Premium,
what a domestic man I am; here I sit of an evening surrounded
by my ancestors—But come let us proceed to
business—To your pulpit, Mr. Auctioneer.—Oh,
here's a great chair of my father's that seems fit for nothing
else.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Careless.</speaker>
<p>The very thing—but what shall I do for
a hammer, Charles? an Auctioneer is nothing without
a hammer.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>A hammer! <stage>(<hi>looking round</hi>)</stage> let's see,
what have we here—Sir Richard, heir to Robert—a
genealogy in full, egad—Here, Careless, you shall
have no common bit of monogany, here's the family
tree, and now you may knock down my ancesters with
their own pedigree.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>What an unnatural rogue he is!—
An expert facto paracide. <stage>(<hi>Aside.</hi>)</stage></p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Careless.</speaker>
<p>Gad, Charles, this is lucky, for it will
not only serve for a hammer, but a catalogue too if
we should want it.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>True—Come, here's my great uncle Sir
Richard Ravelin, a marvelous good General in his
day—he served in all the Duke of Marlborough's
wars, and got that cut over his eye at the battle of
Malplaquet—He is not dressed out in feathers like
our modern captains, but enveloped in wig and regimentals,
as a General should be.—What say you, Mr.
Premium?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Moses.</speaker>
<p>Mr. Premium would have you speak.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Why you shall have him for ten pounds,
and I'm sure that's cheap enough for a staff officer.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="54" facs="54"/>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Heaven deliver me! his great uncle Sir
Richard going for ten pounds— <stage>(<hi>Aside</hi>)</stage>—Well, sir,
I take him at that price.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Careless, knock down my uncle Richard.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Careless.</speaker>
<p>Going, going—a going—gone.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>This is a maiden sister of his, my great
aunt Deborah, done by Kneller, thought to be one of
his best pictures, and esteemed a very formidable
likeness. There she sits, as a shepherdess feeding her
flock.—You shall have her for five pounds ten. I'm
sure the sheep are worth the money.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Ah, poor aunt Deborah! a woman
that set such a value on herself, going for five pounds
ten— <stage>(<hi>Aside</hi>)</stage>—Well, sir, she's mine.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Knock down my aunt Deborah, Careless.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Careless.</speaker>
<p>Gone.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Here are two cousins of their's—Moses,
these pictures were done when beaux wore perewigs,
and ladies their own hair.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Yes, truly—head-dresses seem to have
been somewhat lower in those days.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Here's a grandfather of my mother's, a
judge well known on the western circuit. What will
you give for him?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Moses.</speaker>
<p>Four guineas.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Four guineas? why you don't bid the
price of his wig. Premium, you have more respect
for the Wool Sack, do let me knock him down at
fifteen.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>By all means.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Careless.</speaker>
<p>Gone.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Here are two brothers, William and
Walter Blunt, Esquires, both members of Parliament,
<pb n="55" facs="55"/>
and great speakers; and what's very extraordinary, I
believe this is the first time they were ever bought or
sold.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>That's very extraordinary indeed!—
I'll take them at your own price, for the honour of
Parliament.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Well said Premium.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Careless</speaker>
<p>I'll knock 'em down at forty pounds—
Going—going—gone.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Here's a jolly, portly fellow, I don't
know what relation he is to the family, but he was
formerly Mayor of Norwich, let's knock him down at
eight pounds.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>No. I think six is enough for a Mayor.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Come, come, make it guineas, and I'll
throw you the two Aldermen into the bargain.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>They are mine.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Careless, knock down the Mayor and
Aldermen.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Careless.</speaker>
<p>Gone.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>But hang it, we shall be all day at this
rate; come, come, give me three hundred pounds,
and take all on this side the room in a lump.—
And that will be the best way.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Well, well, any thing to accommodate
you; they are mine.—But there is one portrait you
have always passed over.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Careless.</speaker>
<p>What, that little ill-looking fellow over
the settee.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Yes, Sir, 'tis that I mean—but I don't
think him so ill-looking a fellow by any means.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>That's the picture of my uncle Oliver—
before he went abroad it was done, and is esteemed a
very great likeness.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="56" facs="56"/>
<speaker>Careless.</speaker>
<p>That your uncle Oliver! Then in my opinion
you will never be friends, for he is one of the most
stern looking rogues I ever beheld; he has an unforgiving
eye, and a damn'd disinheriting countenance.
Don't you think so, little Premium?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Upon my soul, I do not, Sir; I think
it as honest a looking face as any in the room, dead or
alive.—But I suppose your uncle Oliver goes with the
rest of the lumber.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>No hang it, the old gentleman has been
very good to me, and I'll keep his picture as long as
I have a room to put it in.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>The rogue's my nephew, after all—I
forgive him every thing. <stage>(<hi>Aside</hi>)</stage> but Sir, I have some
how taken a fancy to that picture.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>I am sorry for it, Master Broker, for you
certainly won't have it—What the devil, have you not
got enough of the family?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>I forgive him every thing. <stage>(<hi>Aside</hi>)</stage>
Look, Sir, I am a strange sort of a fellow, and when
I take a whim in my head I don't value money: I'll
give you as much for that as for all the rest.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Praythee don't be troublesome—I tell
you I won't part with it, and there's an end on't.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>How like his father the dog is—I did
not perceive it before, but I think I never saw so strong
a resemblance. <stage>(<hi>Aside</hi>)</stage> Well, Sir, here's a draft for
your sum. <stage>(<hi>giving a bill.</hi>)</stage></p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Why this bill is for eight hundred pounds.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>You'll not let Sir Oliver go, then.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>No, I tell you, once for all.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Then never mind the difference, we'll
balance that some other time—But give me your 
hand,
<pb n="57" facs="57"/>
<stage>(<hi>presses it</hi>)</stage> you are a damn'd honest fellow, Charles—
O Lord! I beg pardon, Sir, for being so free—come
along Moses.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>But hark'ye, Premium, you'll provide good
lodgings for these gentlemen, <stage>(<hi>going.</hi>)</stage></p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>I'll send for 'em in a day or two.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>And pray let it be a genteel conveyance,
for I assure you most of 'em have been used to ride in
their own carriages.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>I will for all but Oliver.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>For all but the honest little Nabob.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>You are fixed on that.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Peremtorily.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Ah the dear extravagant dog! <stage>(<hi>Aside</hi>)</stage>
Good day, Sir. Come Moses.—Now let me see
who dares call him profligate.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exit with Moses.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>Careless.</speaker>
<p>Why, Charles, this is the very prince of
Brokers.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>I wonder where Moses got acquainted with
so honest a fellow.—But Careless, step into the company;
I'll wait on you presently, I see old Rowley coming.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Careless.</speaker>
<p>But hark'ye, Charles, don't let that fellow
make you part with any of that money to discharge
musty old debts. Tradesmen, you know, are the most
impertinent people in the world.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>True, and paying them would only be
encouraging them.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Careless.</speaker>
<p>Well, settle your business, and make what
haste you can.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exit.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Eight hundred pounds! Two-thirds of
this are mine by right—five hundred and thirty odd
pounds!—Gad, I never knew till now that my ancestor
were such valuable acquaintance—Kind ladies
<pb n="58" facs="58"/>
and gentlemen, I am your very much obliged, and most
grateful humble servant. <stage>(<hi>bowing to the pictures</hi>)</stage></p>
<stage><hi>Enter</hi> ROWLEY.</stage>
<p>Ah, old Rowley, you are just come in time to take
leave of your old acquaintance.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>Yes, sir, I heard they were going.—But how
can you express such spirits under all your misfortunes?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>That's the cause, Master Rowley; my
misfortunes are so many, that I can't afford to part with
my spirits.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>And can you really take leave of your ancestors
with so much unconcern?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Unconcern! what, I suppose you are surprized
that I am not mere sorrowful at losing the company
of so many worthy friends. It is very distressing
to be sure; but you see they never move a muscle,
then why the devil should I?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>Ah, dear Charles!—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>But come, I have no time for trifling;—
here take this bill and get it changed, and carry an
hundred pounds to poor Stanley, or we shall have
somebody call that has a better right to it.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>Ah, Sir I wish you would remember the
proverb—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>"<hi>be just before you are generous.</hi>"—
Why fool would if I could, but justice is an old, lame,
hobbling beldame, and I can't get her to keep pace
with generosity for the soul of me.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>Do, dear Sir, reflect.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>That's very true, as you say—but Rowley,
while I have, by Heavens I'll give—so damn your morality,
and away to old Stanley with the money.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exeunt.</stage>
<stage><pb n="59" facs="59"/>
And enter Sir <hi>OLIVER</hi> and <hi>MOSES.</hi></stage>
<sp>
<speaker>Moses.</speaker>
<p>Well, Sir, I think, as Sir Peter said, you
have seen Mr. Charles in all his glory—'tis great pity
he's so extravagant.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>True, but he would not sell my picture.—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Moses.</speaker>
<p>And loves wine and women so much.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>But he would not sell my picture.—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Moses.</speaker>
<p>And games so deep.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>But he would not sell my picture.—
Oh, here comes Rowley.</p>
</sp>
<stage><hi>Enter</hi> ROWLEY.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>Well, Sir, I find you have made a purchase.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Yes, our young rake has parted with
his ancestors like tapestry.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>And he has commissioned me to return
you an hundred pounds of the purchase money, but
under your fictitious character of old Stanley. I saw a
taylor and two nosiers dancing attendance, who, I know
will go unpaid, and the two hundred pounds would
just satisfy them.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Well, well, I'll pay his debts and his
benevolence too.—But now I'm no more a broker, and
you shall introduce me to the elder brother as old
Stanley.</p>
</sp>
<stage><hi>Enter</hi> TRIP.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>Trip.</speaker>
<p>Gentlemen, I'm sorry I was not in the way
to shew you out. Hark'ye Moses.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exit with Moses.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>There's a fellow, now—Will you believe
it, that puppy intercepted the Jew on our coming,
and wanted to raise money before he got to his master.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>Indeed!</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>And they are now planning an annuity
business.—Oh, Mr. Rowley, in my time servants were
<pb n="60" facs="60"/>
content with the follies of their masters, when they were
wore a little threadbare; but now they have their vices,
like their birth-day cloaths, with their gloss on.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exeunt.</stage>
</div2>
<div2 type="scene">
<head>SCENE <stage>the Apartments of JOSEPH SURFACE.</stage></head>
<stage><hi>Enter</hi> JOSEPH and a SERVANT.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>JOSEPH.</speaker>
<p>NO letter from Lady Teazle.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Servant.</speaker>
<p>No, Sir.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>I wonder she did not write if she could not
come—I hope Sir Peter does not suspect me—but
Charles's dissipation and extravagance are great points
in my favour <stage>(<hi>knocking at the door</hi>)</stage>—see if it is her.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Servant.</speaker>
<p>'Tis Lady Teazle, sir; but she always
orders her chair to the milliner's in the next street.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Then draw that screen—my opposite neighbour
is a maiden Lady of so curious a temper—you
need not wait. <stage>(<hi>Exit servant</hi>)</stage>—My Lady Teazle,
I'm afraid begins to suspect my attachment to Maria;
but she must not be acquainted with that secret till I
have her more in my power.</p>
</sp>
<stage>Enter Lady <hi>TEAZLE.</hi></stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>What, sentiment in soliloquy!—Have
you been very impatient now? Nay, you look so
grave,—I assure you I came as soon as I could.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Oh! madam, punctuallity is a species of
constancy—a very unfashionable custom among ladies.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>L. Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Nay, now you wrong me; I'm sure
you'd pity me if you knew my situation— <stage>(<hi>both sit</hi>)</stage>—
Sir Peter grows so peevish, and so ill natured, there's
no enduring him; and then, to suspect me with
Charles.—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="61" facs="61"/>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>I'm glad my scandalous friends keep up
that report.</p>
<stage>[Aside.</stage>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>For my part, I wish Sir Peter to let
Maria marry him—Wou'dn't you Mr. Surface?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p><stage>(<hi>Aside</hi>)</stage> Indeed I would not.—Oh, to be
sure; and then my dear Lady Teazle would be convinced
how groundless her suspicions were, of my
having any thoughts of the silly girl.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Then there's my friend Lady Sneerwell,
has propagated malicious stories about me—and what's
very provoking, all too without the least foundation.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Ah! there's the mischief; for when a scandalous
story is believed against me, there's no comfort
like the consciousness of having deserved it.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>And to be continually censured and
suspected, when I know the integrity of my own
heart—it would almost prompt me to give him some
grounds for it.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Certainly, for when a husband grows suspicious,
and withdraws his confidence from his wife,
it then becomes a part of her duty to endeavour to
out wit him.—You owe it to the natural privilege of
your sex.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Indeed!</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Oh, yes; for your husband should never
be deceived in you, and you ought to be frail in compliment
to his discernment.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>This is the newest doctrine.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Very wholesome, believe me.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>So, the only way to prevent his suspicions,
is to give him cause for them.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Certainly.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>But then the consciousness of my innocence.—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="62" facs="62"/>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Ah, my dear lady Teazle, 'tis that consciousness
of your innocence that ruins you.—What
is it that makes you imprudent in your conduct, and
careless of the censures of the world? The consciousness
of your innocence—What is it makes you regardless
of forms, and inattentive to your husband's peace?
Why, the consciousness of your innocence.—Now my
dear Lady Teazel, if you could only be prevailed upon
to make a trifling <hi>faux pas,</hi> you cant imagine how
circumspect you would grow.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Do you think so?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Depend upon it.—Your case at present,
my dear Lady Teazle, resembles that of a person in
a plethora—you are absolutely dying of too much
health.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Why, indeed if my understanding could
be convinced.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Your understanding!—Oh, yes your understanding
<hi>should</hi> be convinced. Heaven forbid that
I should persuade you to any thing that is wrong.
No, no, I have too much honour for that.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Don't you think you may as well leave
honour out of the question? <stage>(<hi>both rise</hi>)</stage></p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Ah, I see, Lady Teazle, the effects of
country education still remain.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>They do, indeed, and I begin to find
myself imprudent; and if I should be brought to act
wrong, it would be sooner from Sir Peter's ill treatment
of me, than from your honourable logic, I
assure you.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Then by this hand which is unworthy—
<stage>(<hi>knowing, a servant enters</hi>)</stage>—What do you want you
scoundrell?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="63" facs="63"/>
<speaker>Servant.</speaker>
<p>I beg pardon, sir—I thought you would
not chuse Sir Peter should come up.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Sir Peter!</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Sir Peter! Oh, I'm undone!—What
shall I do? Hide me somewhere, good Mr. Logic.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Here, here, behind this screen <stage>(<hi>she runs
behind the screen</hi>)</stage> and now reach me a book. <stage>(<hi>Sits down,
and reads.</hi>)</stage></p>
</sp>
<stage>Enter Sir <hi>PETER.</hi></stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Aye, there he is, ever improving himself
—Mr. Surface, Mr. Surface.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p><stage>(<hi>Affecting to gape.</hi>) </stage> Oh, Sir Peter!—I rejoice
to see you—I was got over a sleepy book here—
I am vastly glad to see you—I thank you for this call—
I believe you have not been here since I finished my
library.—Books, books, you know, are the only thing
I am a coxcomb in.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Very pretty, indeed,—why even your
screen is a source of knowledge—hung round with
maps I see.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Yes, I find great use in that screen.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Yes, yes, so you must when you want to
find any thing in a hurry.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Yes, or to hide any thing in a hurry</p>
<stage>[Aside.</stage>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>But my dear friend, I want to have some
private talk with you.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>You need not wait.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exit servant.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Pray sit down— <stage>(<hi>both sit</hi>)</stage>—My dear
friend I want to impart to you some of my distresses.—
In short, Lady Teazle's behaviour of late has given
me very great uneasiness. She not only dissipates and
destroys my fortune, but I have strong reasons to believe
she has formed an attachment elsewhere.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>I am unhappy to hear it.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="64" facs="64"/>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Yes, and between you and me, I believe
I have discovered the person.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>You alarm me exceedingly.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>I know you would sympathize with me.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Believe me, Sir Peter, such a discovery
would affect me—just as much as it does you.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>What a happiness to have a friend we
can trust, even with our family secrets.—Can't you
guess who it is?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>I hav'n't the most distant idea.—It can't be
Sir Benjamin Backbite.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>No, no,—What do you think of Charles?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>My brother! impossible!—I can't think he
would be guilty of such baseness and ingratitude.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Ah, the goodness of your own mind
makes you slow to believe such villainy.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Very true, Sir Peter.—The man who is
conscious of his own integrity of heart, is very slow
to credit another's baseness.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>And yet, that the son of my old friend
should practise against the honour of my family.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Aye, there's the case, Sir Peter,—when
ingratitude barbs the dart of injury, the wound feels
double smart.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>What noble sentiments!—He never
used a sentiment, ungrateful boy! that I acted as guardian
to, and who was brought up under my eye; and
I never in my life refused him—my advice.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>I don't know, Sir Peter,—he may be such
a man—if it be so, he is no longer a brother of mine;
I renounce him, I disclaim him.—For the man who
can break through the laws of hospitality, and seduce
the wife or daughter of his friend, deserves to be
branded as a pest to society.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="56" facs="65"/>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>And yet, Joseph, if I was to make it
public, I should only be sneered and laughed at.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Why, that's very true—No, no, you
must not make it public, people would talk.—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Talk.—They'd say it was all my own
fault; an old doating batchelor to marry a young giddy
girl. They'd paragraph me in the news-papers, and
make ballads on me.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>And yet, Sir Peter, I can't think that my
Lady Teazle's honour.—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Ah, my good friend, what's her honour,
opposed against the flattery of a handsome
young fellow.—But Joseph, she has been upbraiding
me of late, that I have not made her a settlement;
and I think, in our last quarrel, she told me she
should not be very sorry if I was dead. Now I have
drafts of two deeds for your perusal, and she shall
find, if I was to die, that I have not been inattentive
to her welfare while living. By the one, she will enjoy
eight hundred pounds a year during my life; and
by the other, the bulk of my fortune after my death.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>This conduct is truly generous.—I wish
it mayn't corrupt my pupil.</p>
<stage>[Aside.</stage>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>But, I would not have her as yet acquainted
with the least mark of my affection.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Nor I—if you could help it.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>And now I have unburthened myself to
you, let us talk over your affair with Maria.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Not a syllable upon the subject now,
<stage>(<hi>alarmed</hi>)</stage>—Some other time; I am too much affected
by your affairs to think of my own. For the man
who can think of his own happiness, while his friend
is in distress, deserves to be hunted as a monster to society.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="66" facs="66"/>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>I am sure of your affection for her.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Let me intreat you Sir Peter.—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>And though you are so averse to Lady
Teazle's knowing it. I assure you she is not your enemy,
and I am sensibly chagrined you have made no
furthur progress.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Sir Peter, I must not hear you—The
man who— <stage>(<hi>enter servant</hi>)</stage> What do you want
sirrah?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Servant.</speaker>
<p>Your brother, sir, is at the door talking
to a Gentleman; he says he knows you are at home,
that Sir Peter is with you, and he must see you.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>I'm not at home.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Yes, yes, you shall be at home.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p><stage>(<hi>after some hesitation</hi>)</stage> Very well, let him
come up.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exit servant.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Now, Joseph, I'll hide myself, and do
you tax him about the affair with my Lady Teazle,
and so draw the secret from him.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>O fie! Sir Peter,—what join in a plot to
trepan my brother!</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Oh aye, to serve your friend;—besides,
if he is innocent, as you say he is, it will give him an
opportunity to clear himself, and make me very happy.
Hark, I hear him coming—Where shall I go?
Behind this screen—What the devil! here has been
one listner already, for I'll swear I saw a petticoat.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p><stage>(<hi>Affecting to laugh</hi>)</stage> It's very ridiculous,
ha! ha! ha!—a ridiculous affair, indeed—ha! ha! ha!
Hark ye Sir Peter <stage>(<hi>pulling him aside</hi>)</stage> though I hold
a man of intrigue to be a most despicable character,
yet you know it does not follow, that one is to be an
absolute Joseph either. Hark ye, 'tis a little French
<pb n="67" facs="67"/>
milliner, who calls upon me sometimes, and hearing
you were coming, and having some character to loose,
she sliped behind the screen.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>A French milliner! <stage>(<hi>smiling</hi>)</stage> cunning
rogue! Joseph—fly rogue—But zounds, she has over
heard every thing that has passed about my wife.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Oh, never fear—Take my word it will
never go farther for her.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Won't it?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>No, depend upon it.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Well, well, if it will go no farther—
but—where shall I hide myself.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Here, here, slip into this closet, and you
may over hear every word.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Can I steal away.</p>
<stage>(Peeping)</stage>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Hush! hush! don't stir.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Joseph, tax him home.</p>
<stage>(Peeping)</stage>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>In, my dear Sir Peter.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Can't you lock the closet door?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Not a word—You'll be discovered.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Joseph, don't spare him.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>For Heaven's sake lie close—A pretty situation
I am in, to part man and wife in this manner.</p>
<stage>(Aside.)</stage>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>You're sure the little French Milliner
won't blab.</p>
</sp>
<stage><hi>Enter</hi> CHARLES.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Why, how now, brother, your fellow denied
you, they said you were not at home.—What,
have you had a Jew wench with you?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Neither, brother, neither.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>But where's Sir Peter? I thought he was
with you.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="68" facs="68"/>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>He was, brother; but hearing you was
coming, he left the house.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>What, was the old fellow afraid I wanted
to borrow money of him?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Borrow! no brother; but I'm sorry to hear
you have given that worthy man cause for great uneasiness.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Yes, I am told I do that to a great many
worthy men—But how do you mean brother?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Why he thinks you have endavoured to
alienate the affections of Lady Teazle.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Who, I alienate the affections of Lady
Teazle!—Upon my word he accuses me very unjustly.
What has the old gentleman found out that he has
got a young wife, or what is worse, has the Lady found
out that she has got an old husband.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>For shame, brother.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>'Tis true, I did once suspect her Ladyship
had a partiality for me, but upon my soul, I never
gave her the least encouragement, for you know my
attachment was to Maria.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>This will make Sir Peter extremely happy.
—But if she had a partiality for you, sure you would
not have been base enough—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Why, look ye, Joseph, I hope I shall never
deliberately do a dishonourable action; but if a
pretty woman should purposely throw herself in my
way, and as that pretty woman should happen to be
married to a man old enough to be her father.—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>What then?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Why then, I believe I should—have
occasion to borrow a little of your morality brother.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Oh fie, brother—The man who can jest—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="69" facs="69"/>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Oh, that's very true, as you were going to
observe.—But Joseph, do you know that I am surprized
at your suspecting me with Lady Teazle, I
thought you was always the favourite there.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Me!—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Why yes, I have seen you exchange such
significant glances.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>'Pshaw!</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Yes, I have; and don't you remember
when I came in here, and caught her and you at—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p><stage>(<hi>Aside.</hi>)</stage> I must stop him <stage>(<hi>Stops his mouth</hi>)</stage>
Sir Peter has over-heard every word that you have said.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Sir Peter! where is he?—What, in the
closet—'Foregad I'll have him out.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>No, no. <stage>(<hi>Stopping him.</hi>)</stage></p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>I will—Sir Peter Teazle come into court.
<stage>(<hi>Enter Sir Peter.</hi>)</stage> What, my old guardian turn inquisitor,
and take evidence incog.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Give me your hand.—I own, my dear
boy, I have suspected you wrongfully, but you must
not be angry at Joseph, it was all my plot, and I shall
think of you as long I live for what I overheard.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Then 'tis well you did not hear more. Is
it not Joseph?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>What you would have retorted on Joseph,
would you?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>And yet you might as well have suspected
him as me. Might not he Joseph?</p>
</sp>
<stage><hi>Enter</hi> SERVANT.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>Servant.</speaker>
<p><stage>(<hi>Whispering Joseph</hi>)</stage>—Lady Sneerwell, sir,
is just coming up, and says she must see you.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Gentlemen, I must beg your pardon, I have
company waiting for me, give me leave to conduct
you down stairs.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="70" facs="70"/>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>No, no, speak to 'em in another room; I
have not seen Sir Peter a great while, and I want to
talk with him.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Well, I'll send away the person and return
immediately. Sir Peter, not a word of the little
French Milliner.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exit.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Ah, Charles, what a pity it is you don't
associate more with your brother, we might then have
some hopes of your reformation, he's a young man of
such sentiments.—Ah, there's nothing in the world
so noble as a man of sentiment.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Oh, he's too moral by half, and so apprehensive
of his good name, that I dare say, he would
as soon let a priest into his house as a wench.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>No, no, you accuse him wrongfully—
Though Joseph is not a rake, he is no saint.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Oh! a perfect anchorite—a young hermit.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Hush, hush, don't abuse him, or he may
chance to hear of it again.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Why, you won't tell him will you?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>No, no, but—I have a great mind to
tell him <stage>(<hi>Aside</hi>)</stage>— <stage><hi>seems to hesitate</hi>)</stage>—Hark'ye,
Charles, have you a mind for a laugh at Joseph?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>I should like it of all things—let's have it.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Gad I'll tell him—I'll be even with Joseph
for discovering me in the closet.— <stage>(<hi>Aside.</hi>)</stage>—
Hark'ye Charles, he had a girl with him when I called.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Who, Joseph! impossible!</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Yes, a little French Milliner <stage>(<hi>takes him
to the front</hi>)</stage> and the best of the joke is, she is now in
the room.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>The devil she is—Where?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Hush, hush—behind the screen.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>I'll have her out.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="71" facs="71"/>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>No, no, no, no.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Yes.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Sir Peter.</speaker>
<p>No.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>By the Lord I will.—So now for't.
<hi>Both run up to the screen—screen falls, at the same time</hi></p>
</sp>
<stage>JOSEPH <hi>enters.</hi></stage>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Lady Teazle, by all that's wonderful!</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Lady Teazle, by all that's horrible!</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Sir Peter, this is the smartest French milliner
I ever saw. But pray what's the meaning of all
this? You seem to have been playing at hide and seek
here, and for my part, I don't know who's in or who's
out of the secret.—Madam, will you please to explain?
—Not a word!—Brother, is it your pleasure to illustrate?
—Morality dum too!—Well, though I can
make nothing of it, I suppose you can perfectly understand
one another, good folks, and so I'll leave you.
Brother I am sorry you have given that worthy man so
much cause for uneasiness—Sir Peter, there's nothing
in the world so noble as a man of sentiment.—
Ha, ha, ha.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exit.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Sir Peter, notwithstanding appearances are
against me—if—if you'll give me leave—I'll explain
every thing to your satisfaction.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>If you please, sir.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Lady Teazle knowing any—Lady Teazle—
I say—knowing my pretensions—to your ward—Maria
—and—Lady Teazle—I say—knowing the jealousy
of my—of your temper—she called in here—
in order that she—that I—might explain—what these
pretensions were—And—hearing you were coming—
and—as I said before—knowing the jealousy of your
temper—she—my Lady Teazle—I say—went behind
<pb n="72" facs="72"/>
the screen—and—This is a full and clear account of
the whole affair.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>A very clear account truly! and I dare
say the lady will vouch for the truth of every word of
it.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p><stage>(<hi>Advancing</hi>)</stage> For not one syllable, Sir
Peter.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>What the devil! don't you think it
worth your while to agree in the lie.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>There's not one word of truth in what
that Gentleman has been saying.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Zounds, madam, you won't ruin me.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Stand out of the way, Mr. Hypocrite,
I'll speak for myself.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Aye, aye,—let her alone—she'll make
a better story of it than you did.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>I came here with no intention of listening
to his addresses to Maria, and even ignorant of
his pretensions; but seduced by his insidious arts, at
least to listen to his addresses, if not to sacrifice his
honour, as well as my own, to his unwarrantable desires.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Now I believe the truth is coming indeed.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>What! is the woman mad?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>No, sir, she has recovered her senses.
Sir Peter, I cannot expect you will credit me; but
the tenderness you expressed for me, when I am certain
you did not know I was within hearing, has penetrated
so deep into my soul, that could I have
escaped the mortification of this discovery, my future
life should have convinced you of my sincere repentance.
As for that smooth tongued hypocrite, who
<pb n="73" facs="73"/>
would have seduced the wife of his too credulous
friend, while he pretended an honourable passion for
his ward, I now view him in so despicable a light,
that I shall never again respect myself for having listened
to his addresses.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exit.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Sir Peter—Notwithstanding all this—
Heaven is my witness—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>That you are a villain—and so I'll leave
you to your meditations—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Nay, Sir Peter, you must not leave me—
The man who shuts his ears against conviction—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Oh, damn your sentiments—damn your
sentiments.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exit. Joseph following.</stage>
</div2>
<trailer>End of the <hi>FOURTH ACT.</hi></trailer>
</div1>
<div1 n="5" type="act">
<head>ACT V.</head>
<div2 type="scene">
<head>SCENE <stage>JOSEPH SURFACE'S Apartments.</stage></head>
<stage><hi>Enter</hi> JOSEPH <hi>aud a</hi> SERVANT.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>JOSEPH.</speaker>
<p>MR. Stanley!—why should you think I would see
Mr. Stanley; you know well enough he comes
intreating for something.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Servant.</speaker>
<p>They let him in before I knew of it; and
old Rowley is with him.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>'Pshaw, you blockhead; I am so distracted
with my own misfortunes, I am not in a humour to
speak to any one—but shew the fellow up. <stage>[Exit
servant.]</stage> Sure fortune never played a man of my policy
such a trick before—my character ruined with Sir
Peter—my hopes of Maria lost—I'm in a pretty humour
to listen to poor relations truly.—I shan't be
be able to bestow even a benevolent sentiment on old
<pb n="74" facs="74"/>
Stanley. Oh, here he comes; I'll retire, and endeavour
to put a little charity in my face however.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exit.</stage>
<stage>Enter Sir <hi>OLIVER</hi> and <hi>ROWLEY.</hi></stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>What, does he avoid us? That was
him, was it not?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>Yes, sir; but his nerves are too weak to
bear the sight of a poor relation, I should have come
first to break the matter to him.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>A plague of his nerves—yet this is he
whom Sir Peter extols as a man of a most benevolent
way of thinking.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>Yes, he has as much speculative benevolence
as any man in the kingdom, though he is not so
sensual as to indulge himself in the exercise of it.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Yet he has a string of sentiments, I
suppose, at his finger's ends.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>And his favourite one is, <hi>that charity begins
at home.</hi></p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>And his, I presume, is of that domestic
sort, which never stirs abroad at all.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>Well, sir, I'll leave you to introduce
yourself, as old Stanley; I must be here again to announce
you in your real character.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>True, and you'll afterwards meet me
at Sir Peter's.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>Without losing a moment.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exit Rowley.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Here he comes—I don't like the complaisance
of his features.</p>
</sp>
<stage><hi>Enter</hi> JOSEPH.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Sir, your most obedient; I beg pardon for
keeping you a moment—Mr. Stanley, I presume.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>At your service, sir.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Pray be seated Mr. Stanley, I intreat you,
sir.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="75" facs="75"/>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Dear sir, there's no occasion. Too ceremonious
by half.</p>
<stage>[Aside.</stage>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Though I have not the pleasure of your
acquaintance, I am very glad to see you look so well.
—I think, Mr. Stanley you was nearly related to my
mother.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>I was, sir, so nearly, that my present
poverty I fear may do discredit to her wealthy children,
else I would not presume to trouble you now.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Ah, sir, don't mention that—For the man
who is in distress has ever a right to claim kindred
with the wealthy; I am sure I wish I was of that number,
or that it was in my power to afford you even a
small relief.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>If your uncle Sir Oliver was here, I
should have a friend.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>I wish he was, you should not want an advocate
with him, believe me.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>I should not need one, my distresses
would recommend me. But I imagined his bounty
had enabled you to be the agent of his charities.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Ah, sir, you are mistaken; avarice, avarice,)
Mr. Stanley is the vice of age; to be sure it has
been spread abroad that he has been very bountiful to
me, but without the least foundation, though I never
chose to contradict the report.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>And has he never remitted you bullion,
rupees, or pagodas?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Oh, dear sir, no such thing. I have indeed
received some trifling presents from him, such as
shawls, avadavats, and Indian crackers; nothing more,
sir.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>There's gratitude for twelve thousand
<pb n="76" facs="76"/>
pounds! <stage>(<hi>Aside.</hi>)</stage> Shawls, avadavats, and Indian
crackers!</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Then, there's my brother, Mr. Stanley;
one would scarce believe what I have done for that
unfortunate young man.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Not I for one. <stage>(<hi>Aside.</hi>)</stage></p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Oh, the sums I have lent him!—Well,
'twas an amiable weakness—I must own I can't defend
it, though it appears more blameable at present,
as it prevents me from serving you, Mr. Stanley, as
my heart directs.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Dissembler— <stage>(<hi>Aside</hi>)</stage>—then you
cannot assist me.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>I am very unhappy to say it's not in my
power at present; but you may depend upon hearing
from me when I can be of any service to you.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Sweet sir you are too good.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Not at all, sir; to pity without the power
to relieve, is still more painful than to ask and be denied.
Indeed, Mr. Stanley, you have me deeply affected.
Sir, your most devoted; I wish you health and
spirits.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Your ever grateful and perpetual <stage>(<hi>bowing
low</hi>)</stage> humble servant.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>I am extremely sorry, sir, for your misfortunes—
Here, open the door.—Mr. Stanley your most
devoted.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Your most obliged servant. Charles
you are my heir.</p>
<stage>[Aside, and exit.</stage>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>This is another of the evils that attend a
man's having so good a character—It subjects him to
the importunity of the necessitous—the pure and
sterling are of charity, is a very expensive article in the
<pb n="77" facs="77"/>
catalogue of a man's virtues; whereas the sentimental
French plate I use, answers the purpose full as well,
and pays no tax. <stage>(<hi>Going.</hi>)</stage></p>
</sp>
<stage><hi>Enter</hi> ROWLEY.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>Mr. Surface, your most obedient; I wait
on you from your uncle who is just arrived. <stage>(<hi>Gives
him a note.</hi>)</stage></p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>How! Sir Oliver arrived!—Here, Mr.
—call back Mr. Stanley.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>It's too late, sir, I met him going out of
the house.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Was ever any thing so unfortunate! <stage>(<hi>Aside</hi>)</stage>
—I hope my uncle has enjoyed good health and
spirits.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>Oh, very good, sir; he bid me inform you
he'll wait on you within this half hour.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Present him my kind love and duty, and
assure him I'm quite impatient to see him, <stage>(<hi>Bowing.</hi>)</stage></p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>I shall, sir.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exit Rowley.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Pray do, sir <stage>(<hi>bows</hi>)</stage>—This was the most
cursed piece of ill-luck.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exit Joseph.</stage>
</div2>
<div2 type="scene">
<head>SCENE <stage>Sir PETER TEAZLE'S House.</stage></head>
<stage><hi>Enter Mrs.</hi> CANDOUR, and MAID.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>Maid.</speaker>
<p>Indeed, madam, my Lady will see no one
at present.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>Did you tell her it was her friend
Mrs. Candour?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Maid.</speaker>
<p>I did, madam, and she begs to be excused.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>Go again, for I am sure she must be
greatly distressed. <stage>(<hi>Exit Maid</hi>)</stage> How provoking to be
kept waiting I am not mistress of half the circumstances;
<pb n="78" facs="78"/>
—I shall have the whole affair in the newspapers,
with the parties names at full length, before I
have dropped the story at a dozen houses.</p>
</sp>
<stage><hi>Enter Sir</hi> BENJAMIN BACKBITE.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>Oh, Sir Benjamin, I am glad you
are come; have you heard of Lady Teazle's affair?
Well, I never was so surprized—and I am so distressed
for the parties.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>Nay, I can't say I pity Sir Peter, he
was always so partial to Mr. Surface.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>Mr. Surface! Why it was Charles.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>Oh, no, madam, Mr. Surface was the
gallant.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>No, Charles was the lover; and
Mr. Surface, to do him justice, was the cause of the
discovery; he brought Sir Peter, and—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>Oh, my dear madam, no such thing;
for I had it from one—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>Yes, and I had it from one, that
had it from one that knew—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>And I had it from one—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>No such thing—But here comes
my Lady Sneerwell, and perhaps she may have heard
the particulars.</p>
</sp>
<stage>Enter Lady <hi>SNEERWELL.</hi></stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Oh, dear Mrs. Candour, here is a sad
affair about our friend Lady Teazle.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>Why, to be sure poor thing, I am
much concerned for her.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>I protest so am I—though I must
confess she was always too lively for me.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>But she had a great deal of good
nature.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="79" facs="79"/>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>And had a very ready wit.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>But do you know all the particulars.
<stage>(<hi>To Lady Sneerwell.</hi>)</stage></p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>Yet who could have suspected Mr.
Surface?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>Charles you mean.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>No, Mr. Surface.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>Oh, 'twas Charles.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Charles!</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>Yes, Charles.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>I'll not pretend to dispute with you
Mrs. Candour; but be it as it may, I hope Sir Peter's
wounds won't prove mortal.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>Sir Peter's wounds! what! did they
fight! I never heard a word of that.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>No!—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>No!—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Nor I, a syllable; Do, dear Sir Benjamin,
tell us.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>Oh, My dear madam, then you don't
know half the affair—Why—why—I'll tell you—
Sir Peter, you must know, had a long time suspected
Lady Teazle's visits to Mr. Surface.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>To Charles you mean.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>No, Mr. Surface—and upon going
to his house, and finding Lady Teazle there, sir, says
Sir Peter, you are a very ungrateful fellow.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>Aye, that was Charles.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>Mr. Surface.—And old as I am,
says he, I demand immediate satisfaction: upon this,
they both drew their swords, and to it they sell.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour,</speaker>
<p>That must be Charles, for it is very
unlikely that Mr. Surface should fight him in his own
house.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="80" facs="80"/>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>'Sdeath madam, not at all. Lady
Teazle, upon seeing Sir Peter in such danger ran out
of the room in strong hysteries, and was followed by
Charles, calling out for hartshorn and water. They
fought, and Sir Peter received a wound in his right
side by the thrust of a small sword.</p>
</sp>
<stage><hi>Enter</hi> CRABTREE.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>Pistols! Pistols! Nephew.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>Oh, Mr. Crabtree, I am glad you
are come; now we shall have the whole affair.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>No, no, it was a small sword, uncle.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>Zounds, nephew, I say it was a pistol.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>A thrust in second through the
small guts.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>A bullet lodged in the thorax.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>But give me leave, dear uncle, it
was a small sword.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>I tell you it was a pistol—Won't
you suffer any body to know any thing but yourself.—
It was a pistol, and Charles—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>Aye! I knew it was Charles.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>Mr. Surface, uncle.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>Why zounds, I say it was Charles, must
no body speak but yourself. I'll tell you how the
whole affair was.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell. <hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>Ah do, do pray tell us.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Sir Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>I see my uncle knows nothing at
all about the matter.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>Mr. Surface you must know, Ladies,
came late from Salt-hill, where he had been the evening
before with a particular friend of his, who has a
son at Eton; his pistols were left on the bureau,
<pb n="81" facs="81"/>
and unfortunately loaded, and on Sir Peter's taxing
Charles—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>Mr. Surface you mean.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>Do, pray, nephew, hold your tongue,
and let me speak sometimes.—I say, Ladies, upon his
taking Charles to account, and taxing him with the
basest ingratitude.—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>Aye, Ladies, I told you Sir Peter
taxed him with ingratitude.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>They agreed each to take a pistol—
They fired at the same instant—Charles's ball took
place, and lodged in the thorax. Sir Peter's missed,
and what is very extraordinary, the ball grazed against
a little bronze Shakespeare that stood over the chimney,
flew off through the window, at right angles,
and wounded the post man, who was just come to the
door with a double letter from Northamptonshire.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>I heard nothing of all this! I must
own, Ladies, my uncle's account is more circumstantial,
though mine is the true one.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>I am more interested in this affair
than they imagine, and must have better information.</p>
<stage>[Aside and exit.</stage>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>Lady Sneerwell's alarm is very easily
accounted for.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>Why, yes; they do say—but that's
neither here nor there.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>But pray, where is Sir Peter now?
I hope his wound won't prove mortal.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>He was carried home immediately, and
has given positive orders to be denied to every body.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>And I believe Lady Teazle is attending
him.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="82" facs="82"/>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>I do believe so too.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>Certainly—I met one of the faculty as I
came in.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>Gad so! and here he comes.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>Yes, yes, that's the Doctor.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>That certainly must be the physician
—Now we shall get information.</p>
<stage><hi>Enter Sir</hi> OLIVER SURFACE.</stage>
<p>Dear Doctor how is your patient?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>I hope his wounds are not mortal.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>Is he in a fair way of recovery.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>Pray, Doctor, was he not wounded
by a thrust of a sword through the small guts?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>Was it not by a bullet that lodged in
the thorax.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>Nay, pray answer me?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>Dear, dear Doctor speak.</p>
<stage>(All pulling him.)</stage>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Hey, hey, good people, are you all
mad?—Why what the devil is the matter?—a sword
through the small guts, and a bullet lodged in the
thorax! What would you all be at?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>Then perhaps, sir, you are not a
Doctor.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>If I am, sir, I am to thank you for
my degree.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>Only a particular friend, I suppose.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Nothing more, sir.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>Then I suppose, as you are a friend,
you can be better able to give us some account of his
wounds.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Wounds!</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>What! havn't you heard he was
wounded—The saddest accident.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="83" facs="83"/>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>A thrust with a sword through the
small guts.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>A bullet in the thorax.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Good people, speak one at a time, I
beseech you—You both agree, that Sir Peter is
dangerously wounded.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree. <hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>Ay, ay, we both agree in that.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Then I will be bold to say, Sir Peter
is one of the most imprudent men in the world, for
here he comes walking as if nothing had happened.</p>
<stage>Enter Sir <hi>PETER.</hi></stage>
<p>My good friend, you are certainly mad to walk about
in this condition; you should go to bed, you that
have had a sword through your small guts, and a bullet
lodged in your thorax.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>A sword through my small guts and a
bullet lodged in my thorax!</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Yes these worthy people would have
killed you without law or physic, and wanted to dub
me a Doctor, in order to make me an accomplice.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>What is all this!</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>Sir Peter, we are all very glad to
find the story of the duel is not true.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>And exceedingly sorry for your other
misfortunes.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>So, so all over the town already.</p>
<stage>(Aside)</stage>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>Though, as Sir Peter was so good
a husband, I pity him sincerely.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Plague of your pity.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>As you continued so long a batchelor,
you was certainly to blame to marry at all.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="84" facs="84"/>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Sir, I desire you'll consider this is my
own house.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>However, you must not be offended
at the jests you'll meet on this occasion.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>It is no uncommon case, that's one thing.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>I insist upon being master here; in plain
terms I desire you'll leave my house immediately.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Mrs.</hi> Candour.</speaker>
<p>Well, well, sir, we are going, and
you may depend upon it, we shall make the best of
the story.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exit.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Benjamin.</speaker>
<p>And tell how badly you have been
treated.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Leave my house directly.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exit Sir <hi>Benjamin.</hi></stage>
<sp>
<speaker>Crabtree.</speaker>
<p>And how patiently you bare it.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[<hi>Exit</hi> Crabtree.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Leave my house, I say,—Fiends, furies,
there is no bearing it.</p>
</sp>
<stage><hi>Enter</hi> ROWLEY.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Well, Sir Peter, I have seen my Nephews.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>And Sir Oliver is convinced, your judgment
is right after all.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Aye, Joseph is the man.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>Such sentiments.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>And acts up to the sentiments he professes.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>Oh, 'tis edification to hear him talk.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>He is a pattern for the young men of
the age.—But how comes it Sir Peter, that you don't
join in his praises?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Sir Oliver, we live in a damned wicked
world, and the fewer we praise the better.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="85" facs="85"/>
<speaker>Sir Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Right, right, my old friend—But was
you always so moderate in your judgement?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>Do you say so, Sir Peter? You never was
mistaken in your life.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Oh, plague of your jokes—I suppose
you are acquainted with the whole affair.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>I am indeed, sir.—I met Lady Teazle returning
from Mr. Surface's so humbled, that she
deigned to beg even me to become here advocate.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>What! does Sir Oliver know it too?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Aye, aye, every circumstance.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>What! about the closet and the screen.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Yes, and the little French milliner too.
I never laughed more in my life.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>And a very pleasant jest it was.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>This is your man of sentiment, Sir Peter.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Oh, damn his sentiments.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>You must have made a pretty appearance
when Charles dragged you out of the closet.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Yes, yes, that was very diverting.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>And, egad Sir Peter, I should like to have
seen your face when the screen was thrown down.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>My face when the screen was thrown
down! oh yes!—There's no bearing this. <stage>(<hi>Aside.</hi>)</stage></p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>come, come, my old friend, don't be
vexed, for I can't help laughing for the soul of me.
Ha! ha! ha!</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Oh, laugh on—I am not vexed—no, no,
it is the pleasantest thing in the world. To be the
standing jest of all one's acquaintance, 'tis the happiest
situation imaginable.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>See, sir, yonder's my Lady Teazle coming
this way, and in tears, let me beg of you to be reconciled.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="86" facs="86"/>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Well, well, I'll leave Rowley to mediate
between you, and take my leave; but you must
make haste after me to Mr. Surface's, where I go, if
not to reclaim a libertine, at least to expose hypocrisy.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exit.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>I'll be with you at the discovery; I should
like to see it, though it is a vile unlucky place for discoveries.
Rowley <stage>(<hi>looking out</hi>)</stage> she is not coming this
way.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>No, sir, but she has left the room door
open, and writs your coming.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Well, certainly mortification is very becoming
in a wife.—Don't you think I had better let
her pine a little longer.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>Oh, sir, that's being too severe.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>I don't think so; the letter I found from
Charles was evidently intended for her.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>Indeed, Sir Peter, you are much mistaken,</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>If I was convinced of that—see, Master
Rowley, she looks this way—What a remarkable elegant
turn of the head she has—I have a good mind to
go to her.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>Do, dear sir.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>But when it is known that we are reconciled▪
I shall be laughed at more than ever.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>Let them laugh on, and retort their malice
upon themselves, by shewing them you can be
happy in spite of their slander.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Faith, and so I will, Master Rowley,
and my Lady Teazle and I may still be the happiest
couple in the country.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>Oh fie, Sir Peter he that lays aside suspicion—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="87" facs="87"/>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>My dear Rowley, if you have any regard
for me, never let me hear you utter any thing like
a sentiment again; I have had enough of that to last
me the remainder of my life.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exeunt.</stage>
</div2>
<div2 type="scene">
<head>SCENE <stage>JOSEPH'S Library.</stage></head>
<stage><hi>Enter</hi> JOSEPH <hi>and Lady</hi> SNEERWELL.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Impossible! Will not Sir Peter be
immediately reconciled to Charles, and no longer oppose
his union with Maria.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Can passion mend it.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>No, nor cunning neither. I was a
fool to league with such a blunderer.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Sure, my Lady Sneerwell, I am the greatest
sufferer in this affair, and yet, you see, I bear it with
calmness.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Because the disappointment does not
reach your heart; your interest only was concerned.
Had you felt for Maria, what I do for that unfortunate
libertine your brother, you would not be dissuaded
from taking every revenge in your power.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Why will you rail at me for the disappointment.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Are you not the cause? Had you not
a sufficient field for your roguery in imposing upon Sir
Peter, and supplanting your brother, but you must endeavour
to seduce his wife. I hate such an avarice of
crimes; 'tis an unfair monopoly, and never prospers.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Well, I own I am to blame—I have deviated
from the direct rule of wrong, Yet, I cannot think
circumstances are so bad as your Ladyship apprehends.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>No!</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>You tell me you have made another trial
<pb n="88" facs="88"/>
of Snake, that he still proves steady to our interest,
and that he is ready, if occasion requires, to swear to a
contract having passed between Charles and your Ladyship.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>And what then?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Why, the letters which have been so carefully
circulated, will corroborate his evidence, and
prove the truth of the assertion. But I expect my
uncle every moment, and must beg your Ladyship to
retire into the next room.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>But if he should find you out.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>I have no fear of that—Sir Peter won't tell
for his own sake, and I shall soon find out Sir Oliver's
weak side.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Nay, I have no doubt of your abilities▪
only be constant to one villainy at a time.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Well, I will, I will.— <stage>(<hi>Exit Lady Sneerwell</hi>)</stage>
—It is confounded hard though, to be baited by
one's confederate in wickedness— <stage>(<hi>knocking</hi></stage>—Who
have we got here? My uncle Oliver, I suppose—Oh,
old Stanley again! How came he here? He must not
stay—</p>
<stage>Enter Sir <hi>OLIVER.</hi></stage>
<p>I told you already, Mr. Stanley, that it was not in my
power to relieve you.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver</speaker>
<p>But I hear, sir, that Sir Oliver is arrived,
and perhaps he might.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Well, sir; you cannot stay now, sir; but
any other time, sir, you shall certainly be relieved.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Oh, Sir Oliver and I must be acquainted.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>I must insist upon your going. Indeed,
Mr. Stanley, you can't stay.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Positively I must see Sir Oliver.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="89" facs="89"/>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Then positively you shan't stay.</p>
<stage>[Pushing him out.</stage>
</sp>
<stage><hi>Enter</hi> CHARLES.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Hey day! what's the matter? Why, who
the devil have we got here? What, my little Premium.
Oh, brother, you must not hurt my little broker. But
hark'ye Joseph, what have you been borrowing money
too.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Borrowing money! no brother—We expect
my uncle Oliver here every minute, and Mr. Stanley
insists upon seeing him.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Stanley! Why his name is Premium.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>No, no! I tell you his name is Stanley.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>But I tell you again his name is Premium.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>It don't signify what his name is.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>No more it don't, as you say brother, for
I suppose he goes by half a hundred names, besides
A. B. at the Coffee-houses. But old Noll must not
come and catch my little broker here neither.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Mr. Stanley, I beg—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>And I beg Mr. Premium—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>You must go indeed, Mr. Stanley.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Aye, you must go, Mr. Premium.</p>
<stage>(Both pushing him)</stage>
</sp>
<stage><hi>Enter Sir</hi> PETER, <hi>Lady</hi> TEAZLE, MARIA, <hi>and</hi> ROWLEY.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>What, my old friend Sir Oliver! what's
the matter?—In the name of wonder were there
ever two such ungracious nephews, to assault their
uncle at his first visit.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>On my word, sir, it was well we came
to your rescue.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Charles!</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Joseph!</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="90" facs="90"/>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Now our ruin is complete.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Very.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>You find, Sir Oliver, your necessitous
character of old Stanley could not protect you.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>No! nor Premium neither. The necessities
of the former could not extract a shilling from
that benevolent Gentleman there, and with the other
I stood a worse chance than my ancestors, and had
like to have been knocked down without being bid for.
Sir Peter, my friend, and Rowley, look upon that
elder Nephew of mine▪ you both know what I have
done for him, and how gladly I would have looked
upon half my fortune as held only in trust for him.
Judge then, of my surprise and disappointment, at
finding him destitute of truth, charity, and gratitude.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Sir Oliver, I should be as much surprised
as you, if I did not already know him to be artful,
selfish and hypocritical.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>And if he pleads not guilty to all this,
let him call upon me to finish his character.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Then I believe we need not add more,
for if he knows himself, it will be a sufficient punishment
for him that he is known by the world.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles▪</speaker>
<p>If they talk this way to honesty, what
will they say to me by and by.</p>
<stage>(Aside.</stage>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>As for that profligate there— <stage>(pointing to Charles.)</stage></p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Ay, now comes my turn; the damn'd
family pictures will ruin me.</p>
<stage>(Aside.</stage>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Sir Oliver, will you honour me with a
hearing?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Now if Joseph would make one of his
<pb n="91" facs="91"/>
long speeches, I should have time to recollect myself.</p>
<stage>[Aside.</stage>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>I suppose you would undertake to justify
yourself entirely.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>I trust I could, Sir.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>'Pshaw <stage>(<hi>turns away from him</hi>)</stage> and I
suppose you could justify yourself too.</p>
<stage>(To Charles.)</stage>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Not that I know of, sir.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>What, my little Premium was let too
much into the secret.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Why yes, sir; but they were family secrets,
and should go no further.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>Come, come, sir Oliver, I am sure you
cannot look upon Charles's follies with anger.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>No, nor with gravity neither.—Do
you know, sir Peter, the young rogue has been selling
me his ancestors: I have bought judges and staff
officers by the foot, and maiden aunts as cheap as old
china. <stage>(<hi>During this speech, Charles laughs behind his
hat.</hi>)</stage></p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Why, that I have made free with the family
canvas is true, my ancestors may rise in judgment
against me, there's no denying it, but believe me
when I tell you (and upon my soul I would not say it,
if it was not so) if I don't appear mortified at the exposure
of my follies, it is, because I feel at this moment
the warmest satisfaction, at seeing you my liberal
benefactor. <stage>(<hi>embraces him.</hi>)</stage></p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Charles, I forgive you; give me your
hand again, the little ill-looking fellow over the settee
has made your peace for you.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Then, sir, my gratitude to the original
is still increased.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="92" facs="92"/>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Sir Oliver, here is another, with whom
I dare say Charles is no less anxious to be reconciled.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>I have heard of that attachment before,
and with the Lady's leave—if I construe right, that
blush—</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Well, child, speak for yourself.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Maria.</speaker>
<p>I have little more to say, than that I wish
him happy, and for any influence I might once have
had over his affections, I most willingly resign them to
one who has a better claim to them.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Hey! what's the matter now? While he
was a rake and a profligate, you would hear of nobody
else; and now that he is likely to reform, you won't
have him. What's the meaning of all this.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Maria.</speaker>
<p>His own heart, and Lady Sneerwell can
best inform you.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Lady Sneerwell!</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>I am very sorry, brother, I am obliged to
speak to this point, but justice demands it from me;
and Lady Sneerwell's wrongs can no longer be concealed.</p>
</sp>
<stage>Enter Lady <hi>SNEERWELL.</hi></stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Another French milliner!—I believe he
has one in every room in the house.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>Ungrateful Charles! Well you may
seem confounded and surprized, at the indelicate situation
to which your perfidy has reduced me.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Charles.</speaker>
<p>Pray uncle is this another of your plots?
for, as I live, this is the first I ever heard of it.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>There is but one witness, I believe, necessary
to the business.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Sir Peter.</speaker>
<p>And that witness is Mr. Snake—you
were perfectly in the right in bringing him with you.
Let him appear.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<pb n="93" facs="93"/>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>Desire Mr. Snake to walk in.—It is rather
unlucky, madam, that he should be brought to confront,
and not support your Ladyship</p>
</sp>
<stage><hi>Enter</hi> SNAKE.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>I am surprized! what, speak villain!
have you too conspired against me?</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Snake.</speaker>
<p>I beg your Ladyship ten thousand pardons;
I must own you paid me very liberally for the lying
questions, but I have unfortunately been offered double
for speaking the truth.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Plot and counter-plot—I give your
Ladyship much joy of your negociation.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>May the torments of despair and disappointment
light upon you all. <stage>(<hi>going.</hi>)</stage></p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Hold, Lady Sneerwell; before you go,
give me leave to return you thanks, for the trouble
you and this gentleman took, in writing letters in my
name to Charles, and answering them yourself;—
and, at the same time, I must beg you will present my
compliments to the scandalous college, of which you
are president, and inform them, that Lady Teazle,
licentiate, returns the diploma they granted her, as she
leaves off practice, and kills characters no longer.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Sneerwell.</speaker>
<p>You too, madam! Provoking insolent!
may your husband live these fifty years.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exit.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Oh, Lord—what a malicious creature
it is!</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Not for her last wish I hope.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>L.</hi> Teazle.</speaker>
<p>Oh, no, no, no.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Well, sir—what have you to say for
yourself? <stage>(<hi>to Joseph.</hi>)</stage></p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Joseph.</speaker>
<p>Sir, I am so confounded that Lady Sneerwell
should impose upon us all, by suborning Mr.
<pb n="94" facs="94"/>
Snake, that I know not what to say—but—lest
her malice should prompt her to injure my brother—
I had better follow her.</p>
</sp>
<stage>[Exit.</stage>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Moral to the last.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Oliver.</speaker>
<p>Marry her, Joseph, marry her if you
can—Oil and Vinegar—you'll do very well together.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker>Rowley.</speaker>
<p>Mr. Snake, I believe, we have no further
occasion for you.</p>
</sp>
<sp>
<speaker><hi>Sir</hi> Peter.</speaker>
<p>Well,—averse to sentiments, as I am
yet I cannot help observing, that when a knave succeeds
in his designs upon credulity, he can boast of
nothing more than having been a while mistaken for
an honest man; but it would be better, for the continuance
and completion of his happiness, were he to
become, for life, and in reality, what he has only
seemed to be.</p>
</sp>
</div2>
<trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>

</TEI>
